<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/amazon.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:42:42-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/amazon.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Amazon backdoor exposed wishlist mailing addresses</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/01/earlier-amazon-backdoor-exposed-wishlist-mailing-addresses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon backdoor exposed wishlist mailing addresses" /><published>2016-01-24T23:15:22-05:00</published><updated>2016-01-24T23:15:22-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/01/earlier-amazon-backdoor-exposed-wishlist-mailing-addresses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/01/earlier-amazon-backdoor-exposed-wishlist-mailing-addresses/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s an article circulating right now about how <a href="https://medium.com/@espringe/amazon-s-customer-service-backdoor-be375b3428c4#.hqxfxuajw">Amazon customer service can be exploited to reveal targeted mailing addresses</a>. I discovered and reported a similar vulnerability in December of 2014, which was reported to me as fixed in May of 2015. I haven’t publicly documented that process until now.</p>

<p>The vulnerability I discovered relates to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/registry/search">Amazon wishlists</a>. Users can associate wishlists with a private address, so that people can buy and ship them gifts without having the recipient’s private information. That address should be kept confidential throughout the entire process, but I found that third party shippers—routinely used for Amazon sites outside of the United States—would sometimes include it in confirmation emails.</p>

<p>In particular: I used Amazon.ca to send a book to a friend, and Canada Post delivered her full address to me in an email. In this exchange, Amazon’s confirmation email properly showed my friend’s address as redacted, but Canada Post revealed it in its entirety.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screenshot_2016-01-24_19-57-19.png" alt="Amazon confirmation" /></p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/canada-post-confirmation.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>That would be unacceptable in any circumstance. But it’s all the worse because some of the people who use Amazon wishlists are especially vulnerable to targeted harassment. The service is popular, for instance, <a href="http://www.dailydot.com/lifestyle/amazon-sex-worker-wish-lists/">among camgirls and sex workers accepting gifts</a>. I’ve also seen wishlists from Twitter microcelebrities, who get occasional threats and unwanted creepy overtures, as well as wishlists from women who are trying to get some support after leaving an abusive domestic situation. For many of these people, a revealed address can be devastating.</p>

<p>I contacted <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html/ref=hp_left_sib?ie=UTF8&amp;nodeId=201182150">Amazon Security</a> via email, ((They make a PGP key available, but <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=200724850">only distribute it over unauthenticated HTTP</a>. All the more reason Amazon should switch to entirely HTTPS.)) and got a confirmation number and a response from a human that it had been assigned to somebody. The fix, introduced in May, seems to simply removed the second confirmation email direct from Canada Post.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screenshot_2016-01-24_20-05-52.png" alt="My email to Amazon Security" /></p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screenshot_2016-01-24_20-06-23.png" alt="Amazon Security fix" /></p>

<p>Although the five month window to fix this situation seemed too long to me, I didn’t want to go public until it had been addressed. An attacker who knew about this vulnerability could easily exploit it for the cost of the cheapest item on a particular wishlist, and the only fix a user could make was removing their address entirely.</p>

<p>Given that particular combination—easy, cheap exploitation, and no alternative path to security—it seemed irresponsible in this case to disclose the problem publicly. Others may disagree.</p>

<p>This isn’t the first time wishlists have inadvertently leaked address data—it happened <a href="http://wishlistexposed.blogspot.com/">at least once before in 2011</a>. Nor do I know for sure that the fix has been applied worldwide, as I only tested in Canada. Unfortunately, <a href="https://ssd.eff.org/en/module/introduction-threat-modeling">for people who could face threats if their address were revealed</a>, Amazon seems like a dangerous service to share it with.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="amazon" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s an article circulating right now about how Amazon customer service can be exploited to reveal targeted mailing addresses. I discovered and reported a similar vulnerability in December of 2014, which was reported to me as fixed in May of 2015. I haven’t publicly documented that process until now.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accepting Amazon’s DRM makes it impossible to challenge its monopoly</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/accepting-amazons-drm-makes-it-impossible-to-challenge-its-monopoly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accepting Amazon’s DRM makes it impossible to challenge its monopoly" /><published>2014-05-26T18:56:32-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-26T18:56:32-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/accepting-amazons-drm-makes-it-impossible-to-challenge-its-monopoly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/accepting-amazons-drm-makes-it-impossible-to-challenge-its-monopoly/"><![CDATA[<p>Amazon was the target of some well-deserved criticism this week for making the anti-customer move of <a href="http://kottke.org/14/05/hachette-job-amazon-unprime">suspending sales of books published by Hachette</a>, reportedly as a hardball tactic in its ongoing negotiations over ebook revenue splits. In an excellent article, Mathew Ingram connects this with <a href="http://gigaom.com/2014/05/23/giants-behaving-badly-google-facebook-and-amazon-show-us-the-downside-of-monopolies-and-black-box-algorithms/">other recent bad behavior by Internet giants</a> leveraging their monopolies. Others have made the connection between this move and a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/30/technology/30amazon.html">similar one in 2010</a>, when Amazon pulled Macmillan books off its digital shelves.</p>

<p>That dispute took place a little over four years ago, and ended with Amazon giving in and issuing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/forum/kindle/Tx2MEGQWTNGIMHV?_encoding=UTF8&amp;cdForum=Fx1D7SY3BVSESG&amp;displayType=tagsDetail&amp;ref_=cm_cd_tfp_ef_tft_tp">a statement</a> that people found a bit strange. Here’s a quote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We want you to know that ultimately, however, we will have to capitulate and accept Macmillan’s terms because Macmillan has a monopoly over their own titles, and we will want to offer them to you even at prices we believe are needlessly high for e-books.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Monopoly” was a funny choice of words there. The author John Scalzi, whose <a href="http://whatever.scalzi.com/2010/02/01/all-the-many-ways-amazon-so-very-failed-the-weekend/">piece decrying Amazon’s actions at the time</a> is still very much worth reading, memorably took issue:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And not only a forum comment, but a mystifyingly silly one: the bit in the comment about Amazon having no choice but to back down in the fight because “Macmillan has a monopoly over their own titles” was roundly mocked by authors, some of whom <a href="http://www.tobiasbuckell.com/2010/01/31/together-lets-break-the-amazon-monopoly-on-kindles/">immediately started agitating against Amazon’s “monopoly” of the Kindle</a>, or noted <a href="http://leegoldberg.typepad.com/a_writers_life/2010/01/nabisco-has-a-monopoly-on-oreos.html">how terrible it was that Nabisco had a “monopoly” on Oreos</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Monopoly, of course, is <em>economically</em> the correct term. Publishers of books that are restricted by copyright have a set of exclusive rights granted to them by law. Their monopoly looks distinct from Amazon’s near-monopoly bookseller position, though, because it’s one agreed to in public policy. In a sense it is also more absolute, and less vulnerable to challenge, because it’s a <em>legal monopoly</em>, and not just a <em>market monopoly</em>.</p>

<p>To the extent Amazon has a monopoly on selling paper books, then, it could be challenged not just by legal action (such as antitrust investigation) but by other businesses competing. There would be some extreme logistical difficulties, and disparities created by economies of scale that might be impossible to overcome, but in principle other businesses are able to compete for Amazon’s market position on physical books.</p>

<p>Copyright behaves differently: when it comes to Macmillan or Hachette’s books, nobody may undercut prices by making production more efficient, or design prettier covers, or edit the text into a more compelling presentation. Where that’s a good thing, it’s because we’ve reached it by public policy. We’ve granted copyright holders an inviolable (if limited) <em>legal monopoly</em> because we as a society like the results. ((Of course, that is only as true as copyright policy reflects the will of the public, which it doesn’t, but it’s something to aspire to.))</p>

<p>A very real danger, though, is if Amazon can take the challengeable market monopoly it has put together, and ratchet it into an unchallengeable legal monopoly. That is exactly what DRM does.</p>

<p>By putting DRM on its digital products—ebooks and audio books—Amazon gets the legal backing of the Digital Millennium Copyright Act’s anti-circumvention restrictions on its products. This isn’t for the advancement of public policy goals, either; Amazon gets to create the private law it wants to be enforced. Thanks to DRM, Kindle users are no longer free to take their business elsewhere—if you want a Kindle book, you must purchase it from Amazon.</p>

<p>Fortunately Kindle software can, for now, read other non-restricted formats. But the functionality is limited, and not guaranteed to stick around. And it’s a one-way street: other software and hardware may not read ebooks in the Kindle format. Customers who amass a Kindle library will find no compatible non-Amazon reader. The fact that individual users can usually circumvent the DRM, too, doesn’t help businesses trying to compete in that space.</p>

<p>Amazon has a lot of fans, and they tend to ascribe its rise as a bookseller for its aggressively pro-customer stance. If it drops that stance, even major fans would probably agree that it no longer deserves the throne. Unfortunately, DRM takes the conditional monopoly that customers like (you get to be the largest bookseller so long as you’re good to your customers) and replaces it with an unconditional one (you once achieved monopoly and that is now permanent).</p>

<p>This week’s sketchy move against Hachette looks like a willingness to throw its customers under a bus in the name of better business deals. If publishers continue to insist on DRM, and if customers continue to allow it, we lose our ability to object.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="amazon" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="drm" /><category term="ebooks" /><category term="hachette" /><category term="macmillan" /><category term="mathew ingram" /><category term="monopoly" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon was the target of some well-deserved criticism this week for making the anti-customer move of suspending sales of books published by Hachette, reportedly as a hardball tactic in its ongoing negotiations over ebook revenue splits. In an excellent article, Mathew Ingram connects this with other recent bad behavior by Internet giants leveraging their monopolies. Others have made the connection between this move and a similar one in 2010, when Amazon pulled Macmillan books off its digital shelves.]]></summary></entry></feed>