<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/apple.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T22:01:08-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/apple.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">1000 apple cultivars for the corpora project</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/11/1000-apple-cultivars-for-the-corpora-project/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1000 apple cultivars for the corpora project" /><published>2015-11-11T00:45:33-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-11T00:45:33-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/11/1000-apple-cultivars-for-the-corpora-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/11/1000-apple-cultivars-for-the-corpora-project/"><![CDATA[<p>The incredible botmaster Darius Kazemi has a <a href="https://github.com/dariusk/corpora">popular GitHub repository called “<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">corpora</code>“</a>, which contains, well, collections of all kinds of things. It can be really handy to have access to a list of words that all fall into a certain group, and so Kazemi makes it available completely freely and with a <a href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">CC0 waiver</a> to place it in the public domain.</p>

<p>Earlier this week I landed my first contribution to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">corpora</code>: a collection of <a href="https://github.com/dariusk/corpora/blob/master/data/foods/apple_cultivars.json">1000 apple varieties, or cultivars</a>, picked from the metadata of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomological_Watercolor_Collection">USDA Pomological Watercolor collection</a>. They are roughly the 1000 that appear most frequently out of 1500 or so, though a good chunk (200 or so of this corpus, and 700 or so of the overall collection) appear only once.</p>

<p>The names on the list are charming and goofy, and I hope they are useful to somebody. Here are some of my favorite cultivars:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Newtown Spitzenburg</li>
  <li>Shiawassee</li>
  <li>White Winter Pearmain</li>
  <li>Royal Limbertwig</li>
  <li>Sops of Wine</li>
  <li>Peasgood Nonesuch</li>
  <li>Limber Limb Pippin</li>
  <li>Hollandberry Admirable</li>
  <li>Petite Douce Rousse</li>
  <li>Russian Gravenstein</li>
  <li>Sweet Nonesuch</li>
</ul>

<p>It feels like a good way of extending the pomological watercolor work I’ve been doing into a community of artists and botmakers I’d like to support.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="apple" /><category term="darius kazemi" /><category term="pomological watercolors" /><category term="public domain" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The incredible botmaster Darius Kazemi has a popular GitHub repository called “corpora“, which contains, well, collections of all kinds of things. It can be really handy to have access to a list of words that all fall into a certain group, and so Kazemi makes it available completely freely and with a CC0 waiver to place it in the public domain.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ripping CDs like a nerd in Mac OS X</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/10/ripping-cds-like-a-nerd-in-mac-os-x/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ripping CDs like a nerd in Mac OS X" /><published>2013-10-10T02:10:07-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-10T02:10:07-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/10/ripping-cds-like-a-nerd-in-mac-os-x</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/10/ripping-cds-like-a-nerd-in-mac-os-x/"><![CDATA[<p>I haven’t ripped a CD in a long time, so tonight when I had occasion to, I was at a loss for the right method. I used to rip CDs mostly on a computer that runs Ubuntu, but I no longer have an external optical drive, so I was stuck using my Mac. Here are my (loose) requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>No iTunes. I’m sure they’ve improved the ripping and encoding process a lot since I last checked, but I just can’t stand using the software.</li>
  <li>The rip has to be pretty secure. Truthfully, I don’t really have a way of verifying this paranoia, but I want to at least see a log that shows possible errors.</li>
  <li>Output must be lossless, or at least output the lossless step. I want to rip, and then I want to optionally encode, but I don’t want to have the encoder determined by the ripper. FLAC is acceptable, and a mountable disc image is even better.</li>
  <li>Finally, I’d prefer a command line interface. And obviously free software.</li>
</ul>

<p>I looked at a number of options. I used to use <a href="https://code.google.com/p/rubyripper/">rubyripper</a>, which is super paranoid about ripping and checking, but I had a vague recollection that last time I had some compilation issues. Since it’s not in very active development, I decided to keep looking around.</p>

<p>I tried using <a href="https://code.google.com/p/abcde/">abcde</a>, which I’ve used before on Ubuntu, and it worked fine but got inconsistent track names. I’m sure this is something I could debug, but I was eager to try other options.</p>

<p>Finally, I settled on <a href="http://tmkk.undo.jp/xld/index_e.html">XLD</a>. It’s got its own error-checking system, but can also use cdparanoia. It’s built to be easily extensible on the encoder side, so it can output in most any format now and in the future. It’s got a command-line interface and a very subdued GUI. Most importantly, it handled everything I threw at it, including one fairly scratched disc, with no problems.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="apple" /><category term="audio" /><category term="cds" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I haven’t ripped a CD in a long time, so tonight when I had occasion to, I was at a loss for the right method. I used to rip CDs mostly on a computer that runs Ubuntu, but I no longer have an external optical drive, so I was stuck using my Mac. Here are my (loose) requirements:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Radio silence: the empty space in This American Life</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/03/radio-silence-this-american-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Radio silence: the empty space in This American Life" /><published>2012-03-20T02:55:19-04:00</published><updated>2012-03-20T02:55:19-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/03/radio-silence-this-american-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/03/radio-silence-this-american-life/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a common saying in jazz that it’s not about the notes you play, but the notes you don’t play. ((It’s sometimes attributed to Miles Davis, but who knows.))</p>

<p>This American Life did an impressive thing with their most recent episode, <a href="http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/460/retraction">Retraction</a>, which was entirely dedicated to retracting <a href="http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/454/mr-daisey-and-the-apple-factory">an earlier episode about Apple and their Chinese production facilities</a>.</p>

<p>Not only did they make an extremely compelling hour of radio about something that is really an internal affair, but they were also unusually symmetrical in their retraction; that is, they’ve given it as much space and prominence as the original story, which is admirable.</p>

<p>One aspect that makes the episode so interesting is the amount of silence they’ve left in the interview. When lies come to light, it’s an uncomfortable experience for everybody involved. This American Life did a great job of capturing that discomfort, and left more awkward silence than I’ve ever heard on a radio show. To get back to that jazz saying, it was the words they weren’t saying, the rests and pauses, that really told the story.</p>

<p>In that spirit, I’ve made a supercut of some of the longest expanses of silence on the show. I recommend listening to the full program. If you’ve already done that, you may find this interesting.</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="http://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F40345507&amp;show_artwork=false" width="100%"></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="apple" /><category term="mike daisey" /><category term="radio" /><category term="sounds" /><category term="this american life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s a common saying in jazz that it’s not about the notes you play, but the notes you don’t play. ((It’s sometimes attributed to Miles Davis, but who knows.))]]></summary></entry></feed>