<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/art.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:52:36-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/art.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">New Twitter bot after artist Gerhard Richter</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/01/new-twitter-bot-artist-gerhard-richter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Twitter bot after artist Gerhard Richter" /><published>2017-01-26T13:06:35-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-26T13:06:35-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/01/new-twitter-bot-artist-gerhard-richter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/01/new-twitter-bot-artist-gerhard-richter/"><![CDATA[<p>This week I went to the SFMOMA for the first time. It’s great! I spent hours there and felt like I had to rush to see even a fraction of the collection. One of the pieces that really struck me was <a href="https://www.sfmoma.org/artwork/FC.643">Gerhard Richter’s massive 1974 painting “256 Colors”</a> (or “256 Farben” in his original German). I took a picture of it there:</p>

<p><a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/img_3465-1.jpg"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/img_3465-1.jpg" alt="" /></a><br />
He made a few “256 Colors” and a bunch of other color charts, some of which are more explicitly generative—that is, where the colors and their arrangement are left to chance.</p>

<p>Anyway, that sounded like fun, so I’ve put together a <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/256farben">small script that creates paintings</a> that look a bit like “256 Colors.” Here’s one that it made:</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/render-1024x555.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>And naturally, I’ve made a Twitter bot that posts them twice a day: <a href="https://twitter.com/256farben">@256farben</a>. Follow along for two daily reminders of the beauty of randomness.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="art" /><category term="bots" /><category term="gerhard richter" /><category term="painting" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This week I went to the SFMOMA for the first time. It’s great! I spent hours there and felt like I had to rush to see even a fraction of the collection. One of the pieces that really struck me was Gerhard Richter’s massive 1974 painting “256 Colors” (or “256 Farben” in his original German). I took a picture of it there:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Supreme Court Data (2015)</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/12/supreme-court-data-2015/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supreme Court Data (2015)" /><published>2015-12-15T21:18:36-05:00</published><updated>2015-12-15T21:18:36-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/12/supreme-court-data-2015</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/12/supreme-court-data-2015/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s a supercut of all the mentions of the word “data” in last week’s Supreme Court Oral Arguments in <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/evenwel-v-abbott/">Evenwel v. Abbott</a>, a case addressing the question of whether the “one-person, one-vote” principle of the Equal Protection Clause allows states to use total population data instead of voter population data in apportioning legislative districts.</p>

<p>Turns out, “data” came up a lot!</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="435" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/EBCxr14AoBA" width="580"></iframe>

<p>This follows a supercut last year of mentions of the word “cloud” in the ABC v. Aereo argument, <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2014/04/supreme-court-clouds/">“Supreme Court Clouds (2014)”</a>. The process of making this video was largely similar, though I’ve traded in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mencoder</code> for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ffmpeg</code> for cutting up, modifying, and muxing the video.</p>

<p>This time I thought it’d be nice to include some background music, so I turned to the <a href="https://archive.org/details/musopen-chopin">public domain recordings of various Chopin compositions</a>, created by Musopen. For the video, I used a segment of a <a href="https://archive.org/details/6235_Information_Machine_The_01_29_03_15">1958 educational film about computers</a> made by IBM and sourced from the Prelinger Archive.</p>

<p>Both media sources, as well as the Supreme Court audio, are public domain. (All for different reasons, too: the music because of an intentional waiver of rights; the video because it was not noticed-and-registered and was made in an era that required formalities; and the courtroom audio because of <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/17/105">§ 105 barring federal employees from copyright</a> on their official work.)</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="art" /><category term="data" /><category term="mash-ups" /><category term="supercut" /><category term="supreme court" /><category term="video" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s a supercut of all the mentions of the word “data” in last week’s Supreme Court Oral Arguments in Evenwel v. Abbott, a case addressing the question of whether the “one-person, one-vote” principle of the Equal Protection Clause allows states to use total population data instead of voter population data in apportioning legislative districts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mad Generation Loss</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/10/mad-generation-loss/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mad Generation Loss" /><published>2015-10-31T20:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-10-31T20:35:00-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/10/mad-generation-loss</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/10/mad-generation-loss/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Mad generation! down on the rocks of Time!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mad Generation Loss is a project exploring media encoding and the ways in which imperfect copies can descend into a kind of digital madness. It takes an audio file—here, a recording of Allen Ginsberg reading an excerpt from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howl">his seminal poem “Howl”</a>—and adds another layer of mp3 encoding to each second of the sound. That is to say, the first second is encoded directly from the original, the next second is re-encoded from that first lossy copy, and the third encoded again.</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/230756469&amp;color=000000&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=true&amp;show_comments=false&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false" width="100%"></iframe>

<p>That sort of re-encoding from lossy originals, known as transcoding, is supposed to be avoided. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generation_loss">generation loss</a> builds on itself, and the quality degrades quickly. That effect is exaggerated here by its second-by-second compounding. By the end of the 3:18 recording, Ginsberg’s voice is nearly impossible to pick out among the background noise.</p>

<p>The last seconds of the recording have been transcoded nearly 200 times. All together, the recording represents nearly 20,000 individual mp3 encodes.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/ginsberg_glitch19-300x300.jpg" alt="Ginsberg, glitched" />This project takes inspiration from earlier efforts to explore generation loss. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_Am_Sitting_in_a_Room">“I Am Sitting In A Room” (1969)</a> by Alvin Lucier was perhaps the earliest, and featured a 4-sentence narration recorded on taped, and re-recorded over and over to hear the tape loss. As the narration notes, that process “smooths out” the irregularities of speech, reflecting instead the rhythm and resonant frequencies of the room of the recording.</p>

<p>More recently, an artist named Canzona documented the process of <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5555359/the-weirdness-of-a-youtube-video-re-uploaded-1000-times">downloading and re-uploading a video to YouTube 1000 times</a>, and the effect of its compound video encoding. He described that project as a tribute to Alvin Lucier.</p>

<p>Unlike those projects, Mad Generation Loss shows the effect of transcoding and loss on a linear recording, not a repeated phrase. The degredation is apparent not from comparing identical inputs and diminished outputs, but from hearing the creep of the telltale white noise and the regular pulse of the mp3s getting stitched together.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/mad-generation-loss">code to create the Mad Generation Loss audio is freely available under the GPLv3</a>. It is written in Ruby and depends on free software like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lame</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mp3splt</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mp3wrap</code>. Thanks are due to Eric Mill and Ben Gleitzman for technical assistance (though please do not attribute my sloppy code on them), and to Caroline Sinders and Ethan Chiel for their encouragement.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="allen ginsberg" /><category term="art" /><category term="audio" /><category term="encoding" /><category term="free software" /><category term="howl" /><category term="mp3" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mad generation! down on the rocks of Time!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Supreme Court Clouds (2014)</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/supreme-court-clouds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supreme Court Clouds (2014)" /><published>2014-04-26T11:52:05-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-26T11:52:05-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/supreme-court-clouds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/supreme-court-clouds/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s a supercut of audio from April 22, 2014’s Supreme Court argument in <em><a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/american-broadcasting-companies-inc-v-aereo-inc/">ABC v. Aereo</a></em> featuring every use (in order) of the word “cloud.” The video track is from <a href="http://www.coryarcangel.com/things-i-made/supermarioclouds/">Cory Arcangel’s “Super Mario Clouds” (2002)</a>.</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="435" loading="lazy" src="//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/nJ_eX7HFTbQ?rel=0" width="580"></iframe>

<p>Here’s a version of the audio only (yes, I put my cloud sound on SoundCloud):</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/146518737%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-k3sc9&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=true&amp;show_artwork=false" width="100%"></iframe>

<h2 id="how-i-made-this">How I made this</h2>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/IMG_20140425_202703-300x300.jpg" alt="IMG_20140425_202703" />The Supreme Court makes <a href="http://www.supremecourt.gov/oral_arguments/argument_transcripts.aspx">transcripts</a> of its oral arguments available on the day of the argument, and puts up <a href="http://www.supremecourt.gov/oral_arguments/argument_audio.aspx">audio</a> the Friday after. I edited the audio in Audacity, and the transcript is indexed, so I had a list of all the uses of the word “cloud” that I could check off as I went.</p>

<p>Once I had the audio, I grabbed a copy of Cory Arcangel’s video and used <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mencoder</code> to put them together. The commands I used to add the audio was:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mencoder -ovc copy -audiofile supremecourtclouds.mp3 -oac copy supermarioclouds.mp4 -o supremecourtclouds-unclipped.mp4</code></p>

<p>And to clip the video to the length of the audio, I did:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mencoder -endpos 00:00:56 -ovc copy -oac copy supremecourtclouds-unclipped.mp4 -o supremecourtclouds.mp4</code></p>

<p>Attending oral arguments on Tuesday was a great experience. Glad I’ve got this little memento.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="art" /><category term="clouds" /><category term="cory arcangel" /><category term="mash-ups" /><category term="supreme court" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s a supercut of audio from April 22, 2014’s Supreme Court argument in ABC v. Aereo featuring every use (in order) of the word “cloud.” The video track is from Cory Arcangel’s “Super Mario Clouds” (2002).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Andy Warhol’s recovered digital artworks and copyright notice</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/andy-warhols-recovered-digital-artworks-and-copyright-notice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Andy Warhol’s recovered digital artworks and copyright notice" /><published>2014-04-25T01:07:41-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-25T01:07:41-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/andy-warhols-recovered-digital-artworks-and-copyright-notice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/andy-warhols-recovered-digital-artworks-and-copyright-notice/"><![CDATA[<p>So this is a pretty neat thing: artists and retrocomputing enthusiasts have <a href="http://studioforcreativeinquiry.org/events/warhol-discovery">worked together to uncover a collection of previously unknown works by Andy Warhol</a> from 1985, pieced together from files on aging floppy disks. The coolest bit, I think, is the recovery effort was kicked off when the artist Cory Arcangel watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3oqUd8utr14">a video demo of Warhol using an Amiga to paint Deborah Harry</a>, and on a hunch went digging for more from that era.</p>

<div class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_1343" style="width: 485px">![© 2014 The Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, Inc. / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York. Used here for commentary and criticism in accordance with the fair use doctrine.](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2_Andy_Warhol_Campbells_1985_AWF_475px.jpg)© 2014 The Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, Inc. / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York. Used here for commentary and criticism in accordance with the fair use doctrine.

</div>
<p>One thing that might seem surprising is the copyright notice on each of the works. It’s listed as © 2014 The Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, Inc. / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York. But it’s actually totally correct: copyright notice hasn’t been required on works since 1989, but when it is given, the date refers to the first publication date—not the creation date. ((That’s per the <a href="http://www.copyright.gov/circs/circ03.pdf">Copyright Office’s Circular 3</a> [pdf].))</p>

<p>Why might that matter? For one thing, it could possibly affect the <a href="http://copyright.cornell.edu/resources/publicdomain.cfm">duration of the copyright term</a>. The works are described as “the products of a commission by Commodore International,” but it seems unlikely that they are considered a work-for-hire. If that were the case, copyright would last for 95 years from first publication—in this case 2109. If the earlier date were put in the notice, copyright could be found to expire that much earlier, as soon as 2080.</p>

<p>But if it were a work for hire, it’d be Commodore, and not Warhol(‘s Foundation) that held the copyright. That’s not the case. Instead, it’s just a standard unpublished work, so copyright lasts for Warhol’s life plus 70 years: until just 2057.</p>

<p>Anyway, for the most part this is an exciting find for art history. But there are a few things I find really sad. For one, the fact that his works will be locked up until 2057 is terrible. His fondness for appropriation just lends a grim irony. Of course, by understanding what the copyright notice date meant I got the work into the public domain almost 50 years earlier, but that ambiguity can still cast a shadow of uncertainty over the use for decades.</p>

<p>Also, of course, a “stronger” copyright system could have prevented Arcangel from ever seeing the Warhol video that led to this discovery. “Strong” copyright encourages rightsholders to publish works only in ways that will provide known value; discoveries like Arcangel’s are the kind of surprise value that a more lax system allows.</p>

<p>It’s sad, too, that the hurdles these retrocomputing experts faced are exacerbated by DRM and anti-circumvention laws. And without the cooperation of the Warhol foundation, this restoration work could have been deemed impossible. Advocates for stricter copyright like to wave the flag of the artists. But surely the fact that so much art history is at risk hurts those artists, too.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="andy warhol" /><category term="art" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="cory arcangel" /><category term="notice" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So this is a pretty neat thing: artists and retrocomputing enthusiasts have worked together to uncover a collection of previously unknown works by Andy Warhol from 1985, pieced together from files on aging floppy disks. The coolest bit, I think, is the recovery effort was kicked off when the artist Cory Arcangel watched a video demo of Warhol using an Amiga to paint Deborah Harry, and on a hunch went digging for more from that era.]]></summary></entry></feed>