<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/audio.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T18:13:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/audio.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">How AOL kept its free disk campaign to itself</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/06/how-aol-kept-its-free-disk-campaign-to-itself/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How AOL kept its free disk campaign to itself" /><published>2016-06-30T00:47:47-04:00</published><updated>2016-06-30T00:47:47-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/06/how-aol-kept-its-free-disk-campaign-to-itself</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/06/how-aol-kept-its-free-disk-campaign-to-itself/"><![CDATA[<p>AOL’s “carpet-bombing” free disk campaign in the 90s and 2000s <a href="http://mashable.com/2014/08/21/aol-disc-marketing-jan-brandt/">worked incredibly well</a>. But the woman responsible for it, Jan Brandt, wouldn’t let anyone acknowledge that, for fear of encouraging copycats. And while she didn’t speak much to the press at the time, she let loose in an <a href="http://www.internethistorypodcast.com/2014/08/chapter-3-supplemental-2-she-gave-the-world-a-billion-aol-cds-an-interview-with-marketing-legend-jan-brandt/">interview with the Internet History Podcast in 2014</a>. (Side note: I’ve been listening non-stop to episodes of this show, and they’re amazing.)</p>

<p>This is my favorite anecdote from her interview, where she explains how nervous she was that AOL’s competitors would follow their strategy.</p>

<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" controls="controls" id="audio-1629-4" preload="none" style="width: 100%;"><source src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/brandt-aol-cds.mp3?_=4" type="audio/mpeg" />&lt;/source&gt;&lt;https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/brandt-aol-cds.mp3&gt;</audio>

<blockquote>
  <p>I say I wake up every morning worried that I’m going to see Prodigy or CompuServe using the disks the way that we’re using them. That I’m going to see it stuck onto the front of a magazine, or that I’m going to see it in the mail.</p>

  <p>And the thing that was really interesting about that point, and one of the reasons—you know, I gave very few interviews. In fact, it’s noted somewhere that I really wouldn’t talk to the press at that point, and the reason I wouldn’t—and I would never have talked to them then the way that I’m talking to you about it now—is because I felt like I was sitting there with the secret sauce, and everyone was going to want to know what were the responses? What were the costs? And I wasn’t going to tell them. So I didn’t think I’d make for a good story.</p>

  <p>But <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted_Leonsis">Ted Leonsis</a> was once on a panel with someone from CompuServe. And the guy from CompuServe, I don’t remember who it was at the time, said to Ted, “You guys are crazy, and the person running marketing has got to be a nutcase with the amount of money that you’re spending on these disks.”</p>

  <p>Ted comes back and reports this to me, and I said, “Next time someone says that, agree that I’m a dumb broad, and that you’ve been trying to get me fired from the company for a long time and you haven’t been able to figure out why you haven’t been able to do that.” And the reason for that, really, is that I couldn’t believe that they weren’t trying it! And it’s because they were making a really common, frightfully common mistake about not understanding the economics of the business.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Listen to the whole episode and, really, the <a href="http://www.internethistorypodcast.com/">whole podcast</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="aol" /><category term="audio" /><category term="internet history podcast" /><category term="jan brandt" /><category term="marketing" /><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AOL’s “carpet-bombing” free disk campaign in the 90s and 2000s worked incredibly well. But the woman responsible for it, Jan Brandt, wouldn’t let anyone acknowledge that, for fear of encouraging copycats. And while she didn’t speak much to the press at the time, she let loose in an interview with the Internet History Podcast in 2014. (Side note: I’ve been listening non-stop to episodes of this show, and they’re amazing.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mad Generation Loss</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/10/mad-generation-loss/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mad Generation Loss" /><published>2015-10-31T20:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-10-31T20:35:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/10/mad-generation-loss</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/10/mad-generation-loss/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Mad generation! down on the rocks of Time!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mad Generation Loss is a project exploring media encoding and the ways in which imperfect copies can descend into a kind of digital madness. It takes an audio file—here, a recording of Allen Ginsberg reading an excerpt from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howl">his seminal poem “Howl”</a>—and adds another layer of mp3 encoding to each second of the sound. That is to say, the first second is encoded directly from the original, the next second is re-encoded from that first lossy copy, and the third encoded again.</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/230756469&amp;color=000000&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=true&amp;show_comments=false&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false" width="100%"></iframe>

<p>That sort of re-encoding from lossy originals, known as transcoding, is supposed to be avoided. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generation_loss">generation loss</a> builds on itself, and the quality degrades quickly. That effect is exaggerated here by its second-by-second compounding. By the end of the 3:18 recording, Ginsberg’s voice is nearly impossible to pick out among the background noise.</p>

<p>The last seconds of the recording have been transcoded nearly 200 times. All together, the recording represents nearly 20,000 individual mp3 encodes.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/ginsberg_glitch19-300x300.jpg" alt="Ginsberg, glitched" />This project takes inspiration from earlier efforts to explore generation loss. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_Am_Sitting_in_a_Room">“I Am Sitting In A Room” (1969)</a> by Alvin Lucier was perhaps the earliest, and featured a 4-sentence narration recorded on taped, and re-recorded over and over to hear the tape loss. As the narration notes, that process “smooths out” the irregularities of speech, reflecting instead the rhythm and resonant frequencies of the room of the recording.</p>

<p>More recently, an artist named Canzona documented the process of <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5555359/the-weirdness-of-a-youtube-video-re-uploaded-1000-times">downloading and re-uploading a video to YouTube 1000 times</a>, and the effect of its compound video encoding. He described that project as a tribute to Alvin Lucier.</p>

<p>Unlike those projects, Mad Generation Loss shows the effect of transcoding and loss on a linear recording, not a repeated phrase. The degredation is apparent not from comparing identical inputs and diminished outputs, but from hearing the creep of the telltale white noise and the regular pulse of the mp3s getting stitched together.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/mad-generation-loss">code to create the Mad Generation Loss audio is freely available under the GPLv3</a>. It is written in Ruby and depends on free software like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lame</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mp3splt</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mp3wrap</code>. Thanks are due to Eric Mill and Ben Gleitzman for technical assistance (though please do not attribute my sloppy code on them), and to Caroline Sinders and Ethan Chiel for their encouragement.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="allen ginsberg" /><category term="art" /><category term="audio" /><category term="encoding" /><category term="free software" /><category term="howl" /><category term="mp3" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mad generation! down on the rocks of Time!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Musical quote: They Might Be Giants and Darlene Love</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/01/musical-quote-might-giants-darlene-love/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Musical quote: They Might Be Giants and Darlene Love" /><published>2015-01-12T00:52:45-05:00</published><updated>2015-01-12T00:52:45-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/01/musical-quote-might-giants-darlene-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/01/musical-quote-might-giants-darlene-love/"><![CDATA[<p>For the first time today I noticed that the They Might Be Giants song “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MyqbckE9kIU">Lucky Ball and Chain</a>” off <em>Flood</em> quotes melody and reversed lyrics from a Phil Spector produced Darlene Love song “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GhmWOBq1xMc">(Today I Met) The Boy I’m Gonna Marry</a>“. Hear the two segments back to back:</p>

<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" controls="controls" id="audio-1442-3" preload="none" style="width: 100%;"><source src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/theregoesthebride.mp3?_=3" type="audio/mpeg" />&lt;/source&gt;&lt;https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/theregoesthebride.mp3&gt;</audio>

<p>I wrote a <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/12/a-closer-look-at-the-girl-on-fire-copyright-lawsuit/">bit about musical quotes</a> in the context of a lawsuit involving Alicia Keys two years ago. We see it all the time in film (Quentin Tarantino and Wes Anderson make an art of it) but it still feels uncommon in pop music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="audio" /><category term="darlene love" /><category term="they might be giants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the first time today I noticed that the They Might Be Giants song “Lucky Ball and Chain” off Flood quotes melody and reversed lyrics from a Phil Spector produced Darlene Love song “(Today I Met) The Boy I’m Gonna Marry“. Hear the two segments back to back:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Netflick, Hulu</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/04/netflick-hulu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Netflick, Hulu" /><published>2014-04-25T17:49:13-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-25T17:49:13-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/04/netflick-hulu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/04/netflick-hulu/"><![CDATA[<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" controls="controls" id="audio-1339-1" preload="none" style="width: 100%;"><source src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/netflickhulu.mp3?_=1" type="audio/mpeg" />&lt;/source&gt;&lt;https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/netflickhulu.mp3&gt;</audio>

<p>Here’s Justice Sonia Sotomayor, at 0:50:59 of the Aereo oral arguments, saying the word “Netflick.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="aereo" /><category term="audio" /><category term="sonia sotomayor" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;/source&gt;&lt;https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/netflickhulu.mp3&gt;]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy birthday to me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/12/happy-birthday-to-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy birthday to me" /><published>2013-12-16T02:13:17-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-16T02:13:17-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/12/happy-birthday-to-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/12/happy-birthday-to-me/"><![CDATA[<p>Today’s my birthday. And although <a href="http://unhappybirthday.com/">I believe</a> that the traditional “Happy Birthday” song is <a href="http://variety.com/2013/biz/news/court-keeps-candles-lit-on-dispute-over-happy-birthday-copyright-1200703048/">in the public domain</a> but for <a href="http://www.copyfraud.com/">copyfraud</a> of enormous proportion, it’d still be nice to partake in a new musical tradition. The Free Music Archive held a contest this year to write a new birthday tune. <a href="http://www.freemusicarchive.org/curator/FMA/blog/Announcing_the_Happy_Birthday_Replacement_Songs">They picked some pretty great winners</a>!</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="450" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/playlists/3795648&amp;color=ff6600&amp;auto_play=false&amp;show_artwork=true" width="100%"></iframe>

<p>If singing isn’t your jam, I recommend today only the <a href="http://www.opengoldbergvariations.org/">Open Goldberg</a> free culture recording of Bach’s Goldberg Variation 26. The whole collection is great, but 26 for my birthday.</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/47731651&amp;color=ff6600&amp;auto_play=false&amp;show_artwork=false" width="100%"></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="audio" /><category term="birthday" /><category term="public domain" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today’s my birthday. And although I believe that the traditional “Happy Birthday” song is in the public domain but for copyfraud of enormous proportion, it’d still be nice to partake in a new musical tradition. The Free Music Archive held a contest this year to write a new birthday tune. They picked some pretty great winners!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What did Jay Z and Paul McCartney think of the Grey Album?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/12/what-did-jay-z-and-paul-mccartney-think-of-the-grey-album/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What did Jay Z and Paul McCartney think of the Grey Album?" /><published>2013-12-09T02:28:39-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-09T02:28:39-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/12/what-did-jay-z-and-paul-mccartney-think-of-the-grey-album</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/12/what-did-jay-z-and-paul-mccartney-think-of-the-grey-album/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been working on a writing project around <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Grey_Album">the Grey Album</a>, and that’s required a lot of research and digging into events that unfolded in 2003 and 2004. In some ways that’s incredibly frustrating: nearly every link I encounter is broken and requires more searching or an Internet Archive lookup ((thank god for the Internet Archive!)), and in some cases can’t be dug up at all. But in other ways it’s great, as the years between have been plenty of time for new information to come to light and sometimes heated issues to cool down.</p>

<p>One basic thing is that, in the years since the Grey Album was released, Jay Z and Paul McCartney have both said on the record that they considered it a tribute and weren’t bothered by its creation.</p>

<p>Jay Z <a href="http://www.npr.org/2010/11/16/131334322/the-fresh-air-interview-jay-z-decoded">was asked by Terry Gross on Fresh Air</a> in 2010, when he was doing promotion for his book “Decoded”. Here’s what he said:</p>

<audio controls="controls" preload="none"><source src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/jayz-greyalbum.mp3" />&lt;/source&gt;</audio>

<p>Paul McCartney was asked less directly on a BBC1 special called “<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00vfgvw">The Beatles &amp; Black Music</a>“. The whole special is fascinating, but here’s what he had to say about the Grey Album in particular:</p>

<audio controls="controls" preload="none"><source src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/paulmccartney-greyalbum.mp3" />&lt;/source&gt;</audio>

<p>I haven’t found any record of Ringo commenting. If you find it, please let me know.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="audio" /><category term="grey album" /><category term="jay z" /><category term="mash-ups" /><category term="paul mccartney" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been working on a writing project around the Grey Album, and that’s required a lot of research and digging into events that unfolded in 2003 and 2004. In some ways that’s incredibly frustrating: nearly every link I encounter is broken and requires more searching or an Internet Archive lookup ((thank god for the Internet Archive!)), and in some cases can’t be dug up at all. But in other ways it’s great, as the years between have been plenty of time for new information to come to light and sometimes heated issues to cool down.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ripping CDs like a nerd in Mac OS X</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/10/ripping-cds-like-a-nerd-in-mac-os-x/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ripping CDs like a nerd in Mac OS X" /><published>2013-10-10T02:10:07-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-10T02:10:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/10/ripping-cds-like-a-nerd-in-mac-os-x</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/10/ripping-cds-like-a-nerd-in-mac-os-x/"><![CDATA[<p>I haven’t ripped a CD in a long time, so tonight when I had occasion to, I was at a loss for the right method. I used to rip CDs mostly on a computer that runs Ubuntu, but I no longer have an external optical drive, so I was stuck using my Mac. Here are my (loose) requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>No iTunes. I’m sure they’ve improved the ripping and encoding process a lot since I last checked, but I just can’t stand using the software.</li>
  <li>The rip has to be pretty secure. Truthfully, I don’t really have a way of verifying this paranoia, but I want to at least see a log that shows possible errors.</li>
  <li>Output must be lossless, or at least output the lossless step. I want to rip, and then I want to optionally encode, but I don’t want to have the encoder determined by the ripper. FLAC is acceptable, and a mountable disc image is even better.</li>
  <li>Finally, I’d prefer a command line interface. And obviously free software.</li>
</ul>

<p>I looked at a number of options. I used to use <a href="https://code.google.com/p/rubyripper/">rubyripper</a>, which is super paranoid about ripping and checking, but I had a vague recollection that last time I had some compilation issues. Since it’s not in very active development, I decided to keep looking around.</p>

<p>I tried using <a href="https://code.google.com/p/abcde/">abcde</a>, which I’ve used before on Ubuntu, and it worked fine but got inconsistent track names. I’m sure this is something I could debug, but I was eager to try other options.</p>

<p>Finally, I settled on <a href="http://tmkk.undo.jp/xld/index_e.html">XLD</a>. It’s got its own error-checking system, but can also use cdparanoia. It’s built to be easily extensible on the encoder side, so it can output in most any format now and in the future. It’s got a command-line interface and a very subdued GUI. Most importantly, it handled everything I threw at it, including one fairly scratched disc, with no problems.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="apple" /><category term="audio" /><category term="cds" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I haven’t ripped a CD in a long time, so tonight when I had occasion to, I was at a loss for the right method. I used to rip CDs mostly on a computer that runs Ubuntu, but I no longer have an external optical drive, so I was stuck using my Mac. Here are my (loose) requirements:]]></summary></entry></feed>