<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/australia.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:46:58-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/australia.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Copyright reform in Australia and Brazil</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/01/copyright-reform-in-australia-and-brazil/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copyright reform in Australia and Brazil" /><published>2014-01-20T04:18:35-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-20T04:18:35-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/01/copyright-reform-in-australia-and-brazil</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/01/copyright-reform-in-australia-and-brazil/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the excellent things about running <a href="https://www.eff.org/copyrightweek">Copyright Week</a>—and there were many—is that copyright activists around the world gave some top-level overviews about what is going on in their countries. Two of my favorite came from regions where copyright reform has been long promised but yet to materialize: Australia and Brazil.</p>

<p>Here’s <a href="http://blog.iinet.net.au/copyright-copywrong/">what’s going on in Australia</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <a href="http://www.alrc.gov.au/news-media/2011-2013/copyright-enews-issue-9-final-report-delivered-g">Australian Law Reform Commission</a> (ALRC) has now delivered its final report on Copyright to the government. Current copyright exceptions have not kept pace with the digital world, and don’t adequately protect important internet-related activities such as <a href="http://www.alrc.gov.au/publications/issues-paper/caching-indexing-and-other-internet-functions">caching</a> or <a href="http://www.alrc.gov.au/publications/issues-paper/cloud-computing">cloud computing</a>. From a consumer perspective, sharing photos (when you don’t own the copyright) on sites such as Facebook and Tumblr is <a href="http://faircopyright.com.au/social-media-sharing">off-limits</a> – unless you have permission from the rights-holder. Or, in a professional context, you can watch a video on YouTube, but you <a href="http://faircopyright.com.au/no-youtube-conference">can’t include it</a> in a presentation to colleagues at work, or for a conference. (Check out other examples of how Australia’s current copyright law is out of touch at the Australian Digital Alliance’s <a href="http://faircopyright.com.au/">#copywrong</a> site.)</p>

  <p>The Attorney-General <a href="http://digital.org.au/content/alrc-recommends-fair-use">announced</a> in December that the ALRC recommended “the introduction of a flexible fair-use exception as a defence to copyright infringement”, similar to that in place in the US.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And <a href="http://creativecommons.org.br/blog/copyright-week-en/">here’s what’s going on in Brazil</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…what is most troubling about the future ahead is that the entire copyright reform process could lose considerable momentum in 2014. A lot was already lost during 2013, considering civil society has turned its focus to Marco Civil. On top of that, the Snowden leaks and the upcoming <a href="http://brmeeting.br/">Global Multistakeholder Meeting on the Future of Internet Governance</a>, to be held in São Paulo, have turned copyright into a secondary concern. Privacy and surveillance seem to have taken the front stage.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s great to follow copyright around the world, especially as deals like <a href="https://www.eff.org/issues/tpp">the Trans-Pacific Partnership</a> threaten to export laws from all different countries. So it’s nice to have people in these countries laying out what’s happening on the ground there.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="australia" /><category term="brazil" /><category term="copyright" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the excellent things about running Copyright Week—and there were many—is that copyright activists around the world gave some top-level overviews about what is going on in their countries. Two of my favorite came from regions where copyright reform has been long promised but yet to materialize: Australia and Brazil.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Answering Paul Kelly’s “how many?” questions</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/answering-paul-kellys-how-many-questions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Answering Paul Kelly’s “how many?” questions" /><published>2012-09-03T04:09:55-04:00</published><updated>2012-09-03T04:09:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/answering-paul-kellys-how-many-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/answering-paul-kellys-how-many-questions/"><![CDATA[<p>I like this song by Paul Kelly, called “Careless.” It’s embedded below:</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="435" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Fq7X_6PlilE" width="580"></iframe>

<p>He asks a few questions in the song, and I’ve got the answers.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many cabs in New York City?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are <a href="http://www.nyc.gov/html/tlc/html/about/about.shtml">13,237 taxis</a> regulated by the New York City Taxi and Limousine Commission.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many angels on a pin?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think the answer to this is pretty conclusively <a href="http://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?db=comics&amp;id=2576">between one and 30 vigintillion</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many notes in a saxophone?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This one’s a bit tougher. These days, the standard accepted range for saxophone is between a B♭ below the treble clef to an F♯ above it. That’s about two and a half octaves, or a total of 32 notes. ((The glib answer, of course, is that there are twelve notes, repeated in various octaves.)) It’s possible, if a bit convoluted, to play a low A and a high G, so we can add two for a total of 34 notes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many tears in a bottle of gin?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Assuming an average bottle size of 750 mL, and an average tear size of 6.2 µl (as per the research of <a href="http://www.iovs.org/content/5/3/264.full.pdf">S. Mishima, A. Gasset, S. D. Klyce, Jr., and J. L. Baum [pdf]</a>), a bottle of gin could fit <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=750+ml+%2F+6.2+µl">121,000 tears</a>. I don’t know why you’d want to do that, though.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="australia" /><category term="music" /><category term="paul kelly" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I like this song by Paul Kelly, called “Careless.” It’s embedded below:]]></summary></entry></feed>