<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:29:15-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/blog.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">200 Deeplinks at EFF</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/09/200-deeplinks-at-eff/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="200 Deeplinks at EFF" /><published>2015-09-28T01:48:06-04:00</published><updated>2015-09-28T01:48:06-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/09/200-deeplinks-at-eff</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/09/200-deeplinks-at-eff/"><![CDATA[<p>The article I published about the <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2015/09/happy-birthday-everybody-victory-public-domain-asterisk">(qualified) public domain victory in the Happy Birthday case</a> this week was my 200th post on EFF’s blog Deeplinks, an event that—<a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/08/my-first-100-eff-deeplinks/">like the 100th post two years ago</a>—calls for a little reflection. I’ve picked out some of my favorites in posts 101-200, below.</p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/pushing-perfect-forward-secrecy-important-web-privacy-protection">Pushing For Perfect Forward Secrecy, an Important Web Privacy Protection</a>, I worked with our tech folks to explain a property that actually really matters for cryptography, but at that point—in August 2013—hadn’t really been set out for lay people. Since then it’s been described even better, but for a while this post had the honor of being one of the more widely-shared explainers on the topic.</p>

<p>The post <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/silk-road-case-dont-blame-technology">In the Silk Road Case, Don’t Blame the Technology</a> was published the day the criminal complaint against Ross Ulbricht was released. It goes through some of the technologies that he was alleged to have used, talking about how essential they are for enabling important speech, and how they’ve been demonized before.</p>

<p>It’s more specialized, but <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/mobile-tracking-code-conduct-falls-short-protecting-consumers">Mobile Tracking Code of Conduct Falls Short of Protecting Consumers</a> was a fun combination of legal and technical talk. One of the points I got to make in there was how the space of MAC address hashes is possible to brute force, alongside general concerns about people finding retail mobile tracking creepy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/remembering-aaron">Remembering Aaron</a> was a difficult one to write, emotionally. It’s become an important thing for me to look over the work I’m doing, and see how it lines up with his ideals. This post was a chance to do that across the whole organization, and speculate what he might have thought about the developments in this space in the year since his death.</p>

<p>There’s maybe no post that I hope more will be vindicated by history than <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/09/how-bad-supreme-court-decision-might-have-good-constitutional-consequences">How a Bad Supreme Court Decision Could Have Good Constitutional Consequences for Copyright</a>, which is basically a short look at a law review article by Neil Netanel arguing that the Golan decision could render 1201 a violation of the First Amendment.</p>

<p>A pair of articles about TPP written 18 months apart are favorites for different reasons. <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/tpps-attack-artists-termination-rights">The TPP’s Attack on Artists’ Termination Rights</a> was the first thing I co-wrote with Sarah Jeong, and was both obviously correct and intensely aggravating to people who set up camp on “the other side” of copyright issues from EFF. <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2015/07/tpp-copyright-trap-our-last-stand-against-undemocratic-international-agreements">TPP’s Copyright Trap</a> is a long look at copyright terms that is one of the most widely shared things I’ve written.</p>

<p>Finally, <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2015/02/who-really-owns-your-drones">Who Really Owns Your Drones?</a> is so far my most thorough look at one of The Big Questions about DRM and connected devices. It builds on earlier posts like How DRM Harms Our Computer Security and that weird news story from February about the drone downed on the White House lawn.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="blog" /><category term="EFF" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The article I published about the (qualified) public domain victory in the Happy Birthday case this week was my 200th post on EFF’s blog Deeplinks, an event that—like the 100th post two years ago—calls for a little reflection. I’ve picked out some of my favorites in posts 101-200, below.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first 100 EFF deeplinks</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/08/my-first-100-eff-deeplinks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first 100 EFF deeplinks" /><published>2013-08-31T11:04:37-04:00</published><updated>2013-08-31T11:04:37-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/08/my-first-100-eff-deeplinks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/08/my-first-100-eff-deeplinks/"><![CDATA[<p>Over on the EFF “Deeplinks” blog, I’ve just published my 100th post, <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/pushing-perfect-forward-secrecy-important-web-privacy-protection">an intro to the cryptographic property of perfect forward secrecy</a>. One hundred strikes me as a nice big round number, averaging a little more than one a week since I started in November 2011. Here are some of my favorite posts of the first 100.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/02/dear-hollywood-open-letter-hardworking-men-and-women-entertainment-industries">Dear Hollywood: An Open Letter to the Hardworking Men and Women in the Entertainment Industries</a> – In the wake of SOPA (and the petty response from the top lobbyists that failed to get it passed), this letter speaks to the actual people that those lobbying groups purports to represent. I got a number of responses from people who work in the film industry, including an email from a director whose work I really admire, and it was generally pretty fun to write this.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/google-abandons-open-standards-instant-messaging">Google Abandons Open Standards for Instant Messaging</a> – As Google is switching from Talk to Hangouts as its instant message platform, it’s also dropping support for federated XMPP connections. That’s a pretty technical issue, so I wanted to make sure that I communicated it in a way that expressed the significance of the issue to people who aren’t familiar with all the specifics. I got a lot of feedback while drafting, and I’m proud of the way this turned out.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/why-isnt-gatsby-public-domain">Why Isn’t Gatsby in the Public Domain?</a> – This was maybe my favorite to actually write, as I got the idea one evening and whipped through it the next morning in a generally really enjoyable situation. Every piece we post on Deeplinks has had at least two sets of eyes, but the person I worked for to edit this one is my favorite.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/these-are-critical-fixes-computer-fraud-and-abuse-act">Critical Fixes for the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act</a> – For weeks after <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/01/goodbye-aaron-swartz-1986-2013/">Aaron Swartz’s death</a>, EFF attorneys worked with other prominent legal experts and even got feedback from Congressional staffers on how to improve the statutory language in the CFAA. But after a few weeks, there was still no generally readable summary of the changes that need to be made. This was my intro-to-CFAA-reform document in the form of a call to action. I was paid the highest possible compliment on this one: copies were printed out and left on every seat at Aaron’s DC memorial service.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/best-practices-respect-mobile-user-bill-rights">Mobile User Privacy Bill of Rights</a> – These are some basic rights that any phone user deserves, but that carriers, app developers, and even OS makers have at times undermined. Most can be addressed by the app developers, though, which is why this is targeted at them in addition to us users ourselves. When the California AG <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/california-attorney-general-releases-mobile-privacy-recommendations">released its guidelines for mobile privacy</a>, it tracked this list of rights pretty closely.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/11/congress-shouldnt-debate-copyright-reality-free-zone">Congress Shouldn’t Debate Copyright in a Reality-Free Zone</a> – Many of the facts that should inform the copyright debate are as undisputed as they could possibly be, but Congress refuses to engage in an evidence-based debate. There’s a lot of political pressure on them not to, in fact. But really, copyright is fundamentally an economic policy, and its stated goal can be measured and achieved. We’ll get real, meaningful reform when Congress stops debating copyright in a reality-free zone.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="blog" /><category term="EFF" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over on the EFF “Deeplinks” blog, I’ve just published my 100th post, an intro to the cryptographic property of perfect forward secrecy. One hundred strikes me as a nice big round number, averaging a little more than one a week since I started in November 2011. Here are some of my favorite posts of the first 100.]]></summary></entry></feed>