<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/books.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:46:58-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/books.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">“A Mind At Play” and Claude Shannon’s grave</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/09/a-mind-at-play-and-claude-shannons-grave/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“A Mind At Play” and Claude Shannon’s grave" /><published>2017-09-20T16:55:16-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-20T16:55:16-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/09/a-mind-at-play-and-claude-shannons-grave</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/09/a-mind-at-play-and-claude-shannons-grave/"><![CDATA[<p>As the “father of information theory,” Claude Shannon’s contributions to the development of modern digital technology are hard to overstate. That work puts him in the ranks of the Einsteins, Turings, and Feynmans of the world; somehow, though, he never seemed to get the credit and public recognition that those scientists received.</p>

<p>A great new biography of Shannon, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01M5IJN1P">“A Mind At Play,”</a> tells the story of his work and may provide an explanation. In contrast to the stereotype of a single-minded scholar who doggedly pursues a particular theory for an entire lifetime, Shannon seemed to hop around to whatever captured his imagination—and in more than a few cases, advanced the state of the art or provided entirely new frameworks with which to consider its thorniest problems. (I was fortunate enough to be sent a copy of this book by its author because I had <a href="https://twitter.com/xor/status/727008565278306304">previously posted about</a> a long <em>New Yorker</em> profile of Shannon commemorating the centennial of his birth.)</p>

<p>That professional pathway meant he probably never had a dull moment, but also that he wasn’t around to lead the fields he revolutionized. Beyond that, it makes it difficult to distill his work down to an equation, or even a few sentences. If you had to, though, you could do worse than his formulation of information as entropy. One fascinating detail from the end of “A Mind At Play” was that that equation appears on his grave stone at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Auburn_Cemetery">Mount Auburn Cemetery</a> in Cambridge where he’s buried.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What’s concealed, however, is a message on the reverse: covered by a bush, the open section of the marble on the back of the tombstone holds Shannon’s entropy formula.Shannon’s children had hoped the formula would grace the front of the stone; their mother thought it more modest to engrave it on the back.</p>

  <p>And so Claude Shannon’s resting place is marked by a kind of code: a message hidden from view, invisible except to those looking for it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This struck me as amazing, and I wanted to see how it was rendered. But, perhaps unsurprisingly, it is difficult to find a picture of the back of a tombstone—even one marking the grave of a person as notable as Claude Shannon. So <a href="https://twitter.com/xor/status/896411797447684096">I turned to Twitter</a>, posting that passage and asking if anybody in or around Cambridge was available to take a picture for me.</p>

<p>Fortunately, it seems many people were as intrigued by that detail as I was, and the tweet was pretty widely circulated. To my surprise and delight, a few groups of people reached out to tell me they were available to go, and a few more just set out for there. I had inadvertently prompted a small flashmob at the grave of a scientist who had passed some 16 years earlier.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There it is! <a href="https://t.co/wjz7PqxVeN">pic.twitter.com/wjz7PqxVeN</a></p>

  <p>— Space User 583 (@User583) <a href="https://twitter.com/User583/status/896496769923764224">August 12, 2017</a></p>
</blockquote>

<script async="" charset="utf-8" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"></script>

<p>The equation is in fact pretty well hidden, but a few folks were able to duck into the bush behind the grave and grab a shot. I love the way it looks, and I was very excited that this new book prompted me and a few nerds around the world to share a moment of appreciation for the great Claude Shannon over a network that his work made possible.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="books" /><category term="claude shannon" /><category term="information theory" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the “father of information theory,” Claude Shannon’s contributions to the development of modern digital technology are hard to overstate. That work puts him in the ranks of the Einsteins, Turings, and Feynmans of the world; somehow, though, he never seemed to get the credit and public recognition that those scientists received.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“We will need writers who can remember freedom”: Ursula K Le Guin at the National Book Awards</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/will-need-writers-can-remember-freedom-ursula-k-le-guin-national-book-awards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“We will need writers who can remember freedom”: Ursula K Le Guin at the National Book Awards" /><published>2014-11-19T23:38:35-05:00</published><updated>2014-11-19T23:38:35-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/will-need-writers-can-remember-freedom-ursula-k-le-guin-national-book-awards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/will-need-writers-can-remember-freedom-ursula-k-le-guin-national-book-awards/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Screen-Shot-2014-11-19-at-8.39.31-PM.png" alt="Screen Shot 2014-11-19 at 8.39.31 PM" /></p>

<p>Ursula K. Le Guin was honored at the National Book Awards tonight and gave a fantastic speech about the dangers to literature and how they can be stopped. As far as I know it’s not available online yet (update: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Et9Nf-rsALk">the video is now online</a>), so I’ve transcribed it from the livestream below. The parts in parentheses were ad-libbed directly to the audience, and the Neil thanked is Neil Gaiman, who presented her with the award.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thank you Neil, and to the givers of this beautiful reward, my thanks from the heart. My family, my agent, editors, know that my being here is their doing as well as mine, and that the beautiful reward is theirs as much as mine. And I rejoice at accepting it for, and sharing it with, all the writers who were excluded from literature for so long, my fellow authors of fantasy and science fiction—writers of the imagination, who for the last 50 years watched the beautiful rewards go to the so-called realists.</p>

  <p>I think hard times are coming when we will be wanting the voices of writers who can see alternatives to how we live now and can see through our fear-stricken society and its obsessive technologies to other ways of being, and even imagine some real grounds for hope. We will need writers who can remember freedom. Poets, visionaries—the realists of a larger reality.</p>

  <p>Right now, I think we need writers who know the difference between the production of a market commodity and the practice of an art. Developing written material to suit sales strategies in order to maximize corporate profit and advertising revenue is not quite the same thing as responsible book publishing or authorship. (Thank you, brave applauders.)</p>

  <p>Yet I see sales departments given control over editorial; I see my own publishers in a silly panic of ignorance and greed, charging public libraries for an ebook six or seven times more than they charge customers. We just saw a profiteer try to punish a publisher for disobedience and writers threatened by corporate fatwa, and I see a lot of us, the producers who write the books, and make the books, accepting this. Letting commodity profiteers sell us like deodorant, and tell us what to publish and what to write. (Well, I love you too, darling.)</p>

  <p>Books, you know, they’re not just commodities. The profit motive often is in conflict with the aims of art. We live in capitalism. Its power seems inescapable. So did the divine right of kings. Any human power can be resisted and changed by human beings. Resistance and change often begin in art, and very often in our art—the art of words.</p>

  <p>I have had a long career and a good one. In good company. Now here, at the end of it, I really don’t want to watch American literature get sold down the river. We who live by writing and publishing want—and should demand—our fair share of the proceeds. But the name of our beautiful reward is not profit. Its name is freedom.</p>

  <p>Thank you.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="books" /><category term="ebooks" /><category term="ursula k le guin" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scripts for book scanning</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/11/scripts-for-book-scanning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scripts for book scanning" /><published>2013-11-28T16:50:54-05:00</published><updated>2013-11-28T16:50:54-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/11/scripts-for-book-scanning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/11/scripts-for-book-scanning/"><![CDATA[<p>I had the pleasure of using <a href="https://www.noisebridge.net/wiki/Digital_Archivists">Noisebridge’s book scanner</a> to “rip” a couple of rare or unusual books I had lying around. So far as I could tell, none of these had been digitized yet, so that’s kind of exciting. Here’s a picture of me at work, taken by <a href="https://twitter.com/maira">Maira</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://instagram.com/p/grwrRAxgj3/"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/jpeg-300x300.jpg" alt="jpeg" /></a></p>

<p>Anyway, the scanner is really great, and a work in progress, so for now all it does is dump the photographs—high res images taken by DSLRs affixed to the machine—as sequentially numbered JPEGs in a directory on an attached computer. For a 600 page book, that’s over a gigabyte of photos, and not terribly useful as a digitized book.</p>

<p>So I used <a href="http://scantailor.sourceforge.net/">ScanTailor</a>, which is a great piece of free software, to take a page that looked like the one on the left and (basically running on autopilot) output one like that on the right.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/comparedscans.png" alt="comparedscans" /></p>

<p>But then I had a directory full of TIFFs, which looked great but were not as portable as a PDF or OCRed to be treated like text. With a little help from smart people like <a href="https://twitter.com/konklone">Eric</a> and <a href="http://loyalty.org/~schoen/">Seth</a>, I was able to write a script to loop through that directory and output a big PDF, and another to run the images through <a href="https://code.google.com/p/tesseract-ocr/">Tesseract</a> and output an OCRed text file.</p>

<p>These are really really simple scripts (which is good because I’ve got no idea what I’m doing), but in case those are useful to anybody I’ve <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/bookscanning">put them up on GitHub</a> (and even released those three-line loops into the public domain, ha.)</p>

<p>The next step, I think, is manual proofreading. Unfortunately, I don’t think that can be scripted.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="books" /><category term="bookscanning" /><category term="e-books" /><category term="noisebridge" /><category term="programming" /><category term="scanning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had the pleasure of using Noisebridge’s book scanner to “rip” a couple of rare or unusual books I had lying around. So far as I could tell, none of these had been digitized yet, so that’s kind of exciting. Here’s a picture of me at work, taken by Maira.]]></summary></entry></feed>