<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/computers.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:52:36-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/computers.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Introducing: cursewords, a crossword puzzle solving interface for the terminal</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing: cursewords, a crossword puzzle solving interface for the terminal" /><published>2019-03-03T13:55:35-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-03T13:55:35-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m releasing <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/cursewords">new software today for solving crossword puzzles in the terminal</a>. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> is a small Python program to open, navigate, and solve puzzles stored as .puz files. If you’re a Mac or Linux user, you can install it today by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pip3 install --user cursewords</code> in your terminal, and then use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> command to open a .puz file on your computer.</p>

<p>In case you’re not a crossword nerd: the .puz file was developed for popular solving software called AcrossLite, and it remains the most popular format for transmitting crosswords online, from independent creators all the way up to the <em>New York Times</em>.</p>

<figure><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/demo.gif" /><figcaption>cursewords in action on my terminal</figcaption></figure>

<p>In fact, many independent puzzle creators <em>only</em> distribute their puzzles as digital files. For example, I subscribe to a handful of excellent puzzle outlets—<a href="https://avxwords.com/#/">American Values Club</a>, <a href="https://inkubatorcrosswords.com/">The Inkubator</a>, <a href="https://www.crosswordnation.com/">Crossword Nation</a>, <a href="http://www.fireballcrosswords.com/">Fireball Crosswords</a>—that don’t offer an online solver or an app like the <em>Times</em> does. As a Linux user, I didn’t have a lot of options to open them: AcrossLite isn’t compatible, Web-based solutions have their limitations, and beyond that, I wanted to be able to introduce fun features like a “downs only” mode that hides the across clues. (You can try it: running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code>with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--downs-only</code> flag activates this very challenging mode.)</p>

<p>But also, I liked the challenge of writing my own software as a way of thinking more about how crosswords are built and how we hold them in our head for navigation. I also love the retro-computing aesthetic that comes with terminal applications, and—while I think this is the first ever terminal crossword client—that it’s mostly based on tech that has remained unchanged for decades. In that way I’ve likened it to efforts to, say, imagine what <a href="https://jalopnik.com/the-greeks-had-the-technology-to-build-a-car-in-60-a-d-5888188">a car built with first-century technology would look like</a>: it’s not necessarily the most useful or the best, but it’s instructive (and in my case, actually works)!</p>

<p>As the name may suggest, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> relies on a famed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curses_(programming_library)">programming library called curses</a> that helps to build text-based user interfaces. It is also heavily indebted to <a href="https://github.com/jquast/blessed">a curses wrapper called blessed</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/alexdej/puzpy">a library called puz that reads and writes .puz files</a>.</p>

<p>If you’re interested in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code>, please give it a try and let me know how it works for you. I’ve been very interested in how to solve this problem for over a month now and I am excited to talk about it more publicly.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="computers" /><category term="crosswords" /><category term="cursewords" /><category term="new york times" /><category term="programming" /><category term="python" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m releasing new software today for solving crossword puzzles in the terminal. cursewords is a small Python program to open, navigate, and solve puzzles stored as .puz files. If you’re a Mac or Linux user, you can install it today by running pip3 install --user cursewords in your terminal, and then use the cursewords command to open a .puz file on your computer.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Screenshot_2019-03-03_13-05-40.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Screenshot_2019-03-03_13-05-40.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">“Computers: The Truth of the Matter”</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Computers: The Truth of the Matter”" /><published>2015-07-13T02:45:32-04:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T02:45:32-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter/"><![CDATA[<p>Disney Educational made a short film in 1983 that depicts the devil and an angel arguing over whether a young woman should learn about computers. It’s called “Computers: The Truth of the Matter,” and I got to see it at the Oddball Films archive on Friday as part of <a href="http://oddballfilms.blogspot.com/2015/07/computerized-yesterdays-technology-for.html">a screening of retro-computing shorts</a>. I looked it up online later and found <a href="http://disney.wikia.com/wiki/List_of_Disney_live-action_shorts">basically nothing</a>, so I thought I’d write up a few words for future searchers.</p>

<p>The film starts with the young woman Jessica slipping into her school’s computer lab, excited for a few quiet moments alone to work with the machines. Her practice time is interrupted a second later when Luke, a devil-figure in a red fedora, appears in a puff of smoke and starts trying to dissuade her from learning, arguing that computers are hard and not really that useful anyway.</p>

<p>A minute later, the classroom door opens and blinding light appears behind it. Angelo, a chubby guy in white gold-trimmed sweats and a winged baseball cap steps out to argue the opposite, that computers are worthwhile to learn. When Jessica shows interest, he pulls her in and they teleport around seeing the applications of computer systems, and then back into the classroom to talk about input devices, CPUs, and output devices like displays and printers. At one point he shrinks the two of them down to walk on top of a microprocessor.</p>

<div class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_1515" style="width: 550px">![Image via Oddball Films](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/computers-matter-1024x745.jpg)Image via [Oddball Films](http://oddballfilms.blogspot.com/2015/07/computerized-yesterdays-technology-for.html)

</div>
<p>Throughout this, the devil figure keeps interjecting that she doesn’t really want to learn, that computers are unpredictable, and so forth.</p>

<p>Eventually Jessica’s convinced, and the devil zaps out of the classroom. In the last shot, we see him at a fiery desk counting the tally at this point: millions of converts for Angelo, zero for himself. Of course, he’s keeping the tally on a computer. When he sees the camera come in, he tries denying it, saying he was watching TV and typing a letter.</p>

<p>The movie is funny in a bit of a forced way, and of course very little of the substantive material “holds up,” in the sense that it would be useful educational material in a computer class today. The high level stuff is still correct, but the examples are decades out of date. But I couldn’t disagree more with the <a href="http://www.dvdizzy.com/forum/viewtopic.php?p=343952&amp;sid=9f6daa37e33b9c6f2ea1ed80f1d7c78c#p343952">folks in, say, this forum thread</a> who claim that it’s no longer relevant and so shouldn’t be prioritized for re-release.</p>

<p>Films like “The Truth of the Matter” have a really important place in the history of computers. It’s remarkable to see the lessons it teaches, not because of the content itself but because of what it says about what was once assumed, or needed to be explicit. One line in this movie that caught me by surprise was when it showed a student working on a term paper, and the narrator remarked that even though it would get corrections and multiple drafts, she would only need to type it up once. Surely it’s worth something to get a glimpse into a world where that was a point that needed to be made.</p>

<p>Anyway, the film hasn’t been reissued, and <a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter/oclc/81479604">glancing through Worldcat</a> it looks tricky to track down a copy. I might try nonetheless. I’m also interested to see some of the other Disney Educational shorts from that era, like the 1983 “Skills for a New Technology: What a Kid needs to Know Today: Living with Computers,” or the 1984 “Ethics in the Computer Age.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="computers" /><category term="disney" /><category term="film" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disney Educational made a short film in 1983 that depicts the devil and an angel arguing over whether a young woman should learn about computers. It’s called “Computers: The Truth of the Matter,” and I got to see it at the Oddball Films archive on Friday as part of a screening of retro-computing shorts. I looked it up online later and found basically nothing, so I thought I’d write up a few words for future searchers.]]></summary></entry></feed>