<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/cryptoparty.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:52:36-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/cryptoparty.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Implementing a CryptoParty Oneself</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/implementing-a-cryptoparty-oneself/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Implementing a CryptoParty Oneself" /><published>2012-11-19T04:01:17-05:00</published><updated>2012-11-19T04:01:17-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/implementing-a-cryptoparty-oneself</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/implementing-a-cryptoparty-oneself/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s an important rule in the cryptography world: you should never implement it yourself. So much can go wrong in the implementation of a crypto-system that you’d better leave it up to experts. Funny, then, that <a href="https://twitter.com/starchy/status/269879585741615104">exactly the opposite rule applies to planning CryptoParties</a>.</p>

<p>Saturday I hosted the first CryptoParty SF at Mozilla’s San Francisco headquarters, where for a few hours a few dozen people got together and participated in lectures, discussions, and workshops about privacy, security, and cryptography. It was fun, and I think people enjoyed it, but there are a lot of things I plan to improve the next time around. Here are some of my thoughts about the event:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We had a limit on the size of the gathering because of the venue — 100 people — and we were able to hit that many registrations without much promotion at all. But in retrospect I realize that we needed to focus on not just hitting a certain number of participants, but also making sure the right people find out about it. In fact, it’s not much of a surprise that the people who find out about an event like CryptoParty without you doing outreach are crypto nerds. It’s great that they want to attend, but it would’ve been nice to get more people who were curious and not yet experts.</li>
  <li>Building on that point: there’s a risk of making too onerous a registration process, but it would have been very nice to get an impression of how much background participants had in cryptography. Primarily to give that information to the speakers, who could have shaped their talks better. Unfortunately, several of the speakers expressed concern to me during and after Saturday’s event that the talk they prepared was too basic for the audience. I actually think every talk went smoothly, but it’s unfair to put the speakers in that position.</li>
  <li>There’s no substitute for planning and preparing. Yes, this is a general event tip, but it applies here. I did a pretty poor job of lining things up in advance, and I was very lucky that things went as smoothly as they did. In large part, that smoothness was due to really talented and generous speakers who were willing to be flexible and work with me on short notice. But no matter how hard you work in the few days leading up to an event, you can’t beat talking with presenters well in advance and doing real event promotion for a few weeks or months.</li>
  <li>That said, everybody in the room wanted the event to succeed. That’s a lifesaver. I really owe great thanks to not only the presenters but really the attendees, who were all on board and excited. It’s easy to get worried about an adversarial crowd — fortunately that wasn’t what I was facing.</li>
</ul>

<p>Had CryptoParty SF failed it would have been my fault, but that it was (more-or-less) successful really falls on many others. Thanks to Tom Lowenthal at Mozilla who helped with organization, motivation, and providing a venue; to my colleague Micah Lee who built the registration site and provided all kinds of support; to all of the fantastic speakers (aestetix, Marcia Hofmann, Morgan Marquis-Boire, Eva Galperin, Lee from the Guardian Project, Seth Schoen, starchy, and Quinn Norton) who gave such great presentations; to <a href="https://twitter.com/Asher_Wolf">Asher Wolf</a> for hatching a pretty wonderful idea for an event series; and of course to all the people who came out to participate in this crazy experiment.</p>

<p>I’m already buzzing on a follow-up event, which I think will take place in January. More details, as they say, to come.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="asher wolf" /><category term="crypto" /><category term="cryptoparty" /><category term="san francisco" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s an important rule in the cryptography world: you should never implement it yourself. So much can go wrong in the implementation of a crypto-system that you’d better leave it up to experts. Funny, then, that exactly the opposite rule applies to planning CryptoParties.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stanford Cryptography and #CryptoParty</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/stanford-cryptography-and-cryptoparty/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stanford Cryptography and #CryptoParty" /><published>2012-08-24T01:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-24T01:30:00-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/stanford-cryptography-and-cryptoparty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/stanford-cryptography-and-cryptoparty/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently finished the free online <a href="https://class.coursera.org/crypto">Stanford cryptography course</a> offered through Coursera and taught by Dan Boneh. It’s a challenging class, with at least four hours of lectures a week, and it actually took me two attempts to get all the way through it. I’m really glad I did though: cryptography is a tremendously empowering subject, and learning the theoretical foundation can be not just educational but inspirational. In one early lecture, Boneh lays out a basic tenet that really spoke to me:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There’s a very central theorem in crypto, and it really is quite a surprising fact, that says that any computation you’d like to do, any function F you’d like to compute, that you can compute with a trusted authority, you can also do without a trusted authority. …</p>

  <p>Instead, what the parties are gonna do, is they’re gonna talk to one another using some protocol, such that at the end of the protocol all of the sudden the value of the function becomes known to everybody.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Boneh is talking, in this example, about elections and private auctions, but the broader message is striking. Any function that’s possible with an authority is possible without one. Any group can devise a method for communicating internally and producing results without a requirement to put trust in a party on the outside.</p>

<p>This central theorem gave me new perspective on the connection between anarchy and cypherpunks. I knew that the government classified crypto technology as a munition during the “crypto wars” of the ’80s and ’90s, but I’d always assumed that the government feared its use to assist in acts of violence. I realize now how much more subversive it can be.</p>

<p>I had looked in the wrong place of Weber’s model of governmental authority as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monopoly_on_violence">monopoly on the legitimate use of physical force</a>; while the government could claim to be concerned about crypto’s use in creating violence, it may have really been worried about its undermining the government’s monopoly on legitimacy. Any function that’s possible with an authority is possible without one.</p>

<p>The rest of the class was interesting as well, and the math involved feels clever but simple, complex but not complicated. I recommend it to anybody who’s given some thought to cryptography but wants to know more.</p>

<p>Of course, for some purposes a full class on cryptography is total overkill. It’s useful to gain a more complete understanding of the theoretical background, but for most it suffices simply to be literate. For everybody, but especially for people in high-risk situations — people who face threats from sophisticated, even state-level attackers — it’s important to know how to use the sophisticated tools that are available.</p>

<p>That, so far as I understand it, is the genesis of <a href="https://twitter.com/Asher_Wolf/status/238389782634459136">#CryptoParty</a>. It’s a set of global get-togethers where more experienced users can teach beginners how to use the commonly available tools that tap into the incredibly powerful technology of cryptography. I hope that a beginner walks away from a #CryptoParty with an understanding of not just PGP, OTR, and the like, but with an idea of why threat models are important, what attack vectors she ought to consider, and — most importantly — a network of people and resources she can contact for even more knowledge.</p>

<p>As far as I know, #CryptoParty is still less than 48 hours old, but it’s popping up with events all over the world. I’m planning to get together the SF chapter, if you can help with that, please drop me a line!</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="crypto" /><category term="cryptoparty" /><category term="dan boneh" /><category term="encryption" /><category term="stanford" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently finished the free online Stanford cryptography course offered through Coursera and taught by Dan Boneh. It’s a challenging class, with at least four hours of lectures a week, and it actually took me two attempts to get all the way through it. I’m really glad I did though: cryptography is a tremendously empowering subject, and learning the theoretical foundation can be not just educational but inspirational. In one early lecture, Boneh lays out a basic tenet that really spoke to me:]]></summary></entry></feed>