<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/cursewords.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T22:31:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/cursewords.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">New Rossword puzzle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2021/03/new-rossword-puzzle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Rossword puzzle" /><published>2021-03-07T07:05:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-07T07:05:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2021/03/new-rossword-puzzle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2021/03/new-rossword-puzzle/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://coryarcangel.com/news/2010/08/sorry-i-havnt-posted">Sorry I Haven’t Posted</a> for a while!</p>

<p>I do of course intend to return to the blog, yadda yadda, lots of updates to share. One quick thing that merits an update <em>today</em> is that I’ve co-constructed a crossword puzzle with Ross Trudeau over at <a href="https://rosswordpuzzles.com/2021/03/07/babys-first-word">Rossword Puzzles</a>. Go check it out.</p>

<p>Ross is a mentor to many in the crossword world, and I’m lucky to have weaseled my way into that cohort through being friends with him. We also (and this should be the subject of another blog post! The inspiration is returning, see!) host a regular Twitch stream called <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/cursewordslive/">Cursewords Live</a>, which involves a lot of solving puzzles in <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal/">my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> software</a>.</p>

<p>Ross and I previously co-constructed a Universal Sunday puzzle (<a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/usun210110.pdf">available as a PDF</a>) published on January 10 this year.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="crosswords" /><category term="cursewords" /><category term="cursewords live" /><category term="ross trudeau" /><category term="twitch" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sorry I Haven’t Posted for a while!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing: cursewords, a crossword puzzle solving interface for the terminal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing: cursewords, a crossword puzzle solving interface for the terminal" /><published>2019-03-03T13:55:35-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-03T13:55:35-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2019/03/cursewords-crossword-puzzle-solving-interface-terminal/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m releasing <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/cursewords">new software today for solving crossword puzzles in the terminal</a>. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> is a small Python program to open, navigate, and solve puzzles stored as .puz files. If you’re a Mac or Linux user, you can install it today by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pip3 install --user cursewords</code> in your terminal, and then use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> command to open a .puz file on your computer.</p>

<p>In case you’re not a crossword nerd: the .puz file was developed for popular solving software called AcrossLite, and it remains the most popular format for transmitting crosswords online, from independent creators all the way up to the <em>New York Times</em>.</p>

<figure><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/demo.gif" /><figcaption>cursewords in action on my terminal</figcaption></figure>

<p>In fact, many independent puzzle creators <em>only</em> distribute their puzzles as digital files. For example, I subscribe to a handful of excellent puzzle outlets—<a href="https://avxwords.com/#/">American Values Club</a>, <a href="https://inkubatorcrosswords.com/">The Inkubator</a>, <a href="https://www.crosswordnation.com/">Crossword Nation</a>, <a href="http://www.fireballcrosswords.com/">Fireball Crosswords</a>—that don’t offer an online solver or an app like the <em>Times</em> does. As a Linux user, I didn’t have a lot of options to open them: AcrossLite isn’t compatible, Web-based solutions have their limitations, and beyond that, I wanted to be able to introduce fun features like a “downs only” mode that hides the across clues. (You can try it: running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code>with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--downs-only</code> flag activates this very challenging mode.)</p>

<p>But also, I liked the challenge of writing my own software as a way of thinking more about how crosswords are built and how we hold them in our head for navigation. I also love the retro-computing aesthetic that comes with terminal applications, and—while I think this is the first ever terminal crossword client—that it’s mostly based on tech that has remained unchanged for decades. In that way I’ve likened it to efforts to, say, imagine what <a href="https://jalopnik.com/the-greeks-had-the-technology-to-build-a-car-in-60-a-d-5888188">a car built with first-century technology would look like</a>: it’s not necessarily the most useful or the best, but it’s instructive (and in my case, actually works)!</p>

<p>As the name may suggest, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code> relies on a famed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curses_(programming_library)">programming library called curses</a> that helps to build text-based user interfaces. It is also heavily indebted to <a href="https://github.com/jquast/blessed">a curses wrapper called blessed</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/alexdej/puzpy">a library called puz that reads and writes .puz files</a>.</p>

<p>If you’re interested in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cursewords</code>, please give it a try and let me know how it works for you. I’ve been very interested in how to solve this problem for over a month now and I am excited to talk about it more publicly.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="computers" /><category term="crosswords" /><category term="cursewords" /><category term="new york times" /><category term="programming" /><category term="python" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m releasing new software today for solving crossword puzzles in the terminal. cursewords is a small Python program to open, navigate, and solve puzzles stored as .puz files. If you’re a Mac or Linux user, you can install it today by running pip3 install --user cursewords in your terminal, and then use the cursewords command to open a .puz file on your computer.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Screenshot_2019-03-03_13-05-40.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Screenshot_2019-03-03_13-05-40.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>