<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/drones.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:33:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/drones.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">An update on the Christopher Dorner drone situation</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/an-update-on-the-christopher-dorner-drone-situation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An update on the Christopher Dorner drone situation" /><published>2013-02-17T18:09:58-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-17T18:09:58-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/an-update-on-the-christopher-dorner-drone-situation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/an-update-on-the-christopher-dorner-drone-situation/"><![CDATA[<p>Last week <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax/">I dug into some claims that struck me as bogus</a>, claiming that the LAPD was flying drones to track Christopher Dorner through Southern California. It looks like my suspicions were correct. <a href="http://mashable.com/2013/02/11/lapd-drones-dorner/">Lorenzo Francheschi-Bicchierai at Mashable posted a write-up just a few hours after mine</a>, but since he’s a real journalist he called the CBP and checked with them: they stated that “CPB UAS are not flying in support of the search.”</p>

<p>Of course, the CBP drones weren’t the only option. The day after Lorenzo’s story, <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/future_tense/2013/02/12/christopher_dorner_manhunt_faa_dhs_say_no_drones_are_being_used.html">Ryan Gallagher at Slate got in touch with the FAA</a>, who said that “no agency has asked us to issue a certificate of authorization for operating UAS as part of this search.” That pretty much rules out the option that the LAPD was flying drones, even if they were officially refusing to confirm or deny the story.</p>

<p>On Wednesday, the morning after Dorner was discovered and killed, <a href="http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/nation/la-na-domestic-drones-20130216,0,1021089,full.story">the LAPD confirmed that it was not flying a drone, but that it wished it could have</a>. A police spokesman said, “The search would have been much wider and quicker because you’d have an unmanned aircraft looking. You can cover more ground.”</p>

<p>Given that Dorner was discovered in close proximity to a police outpost, it seems unlikely that a drone covering more territory would have been much help. But now we know, more or less, that it wasn’t used in this case.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="christopher dorner" /><category term="drones" /><category term="los angeles" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last week I dug into some claims that struck me as bogus, claiming that the LAPD was flying drones to track Christopher Dorner through Southern California. It looks like my suspicions were correct. Lorenzo Francheschi-Bicchierai at Mashable posted a write-up just a few hours after mine, but since he’s a real journalist he called the CBP and checked with them: they stated that “CPB UAS are not flying in support of the search.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Did the Internet just fall for a massive drone hoax?</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did the Internet just fall for a massive drone hoax?" /><published>2013-02-11T04:40:12-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-11T04:40:12-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax/"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been on Twitter today, you’ve probably seen it promoted as fact that surveillance drones have been sent into operation over Los Angeles as part of the multi-state manhunt for former cop Christopher Dorner alleged to be on a killing spree. The <a href="http://now.msn.com/christopher-dorner-is-first-drone-target-on-us-soil">worst articles imply</a> that the drones are armed and the government has authorized Dorner’s death, using language that’s ambiguous to the point of being deceptive, which is almost certainly untrue. But a closer look at the articles raises another concern: all of the reports are citing a single article which is flawed at best, and at worst may even be fabricated. Are the police using a drone at all?</p>

<p>Sunday Morning, the <a href="http://www.express.co.uk/news/world/376732/Man-hunt-for-ex-soldier-who-shot-police-chief-s-daughter-and-killed-policeman">UK publication “Express” published an article about the manhunt</a>, and provided its drone claims, with its main claim coming from an anonymous source within the Los Angeles police department. The relevant facts presented in the article are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Dorner has become the first human target for remotely-controlled airborne drones on US soil.”</li>
  <li>“A senior police source said: ‘The thermal imaging cameras the drones use may be our only hope of finding him. On the ground, it’s like looking for a needle in a haystack.’”</li>
  <li>Riverside PD Chief Sergio Diaz was asked directly about drones, and responded “We are using all the tools at our disposal.”</li>
  <li>Customs and Border Patrol spokesman Ralph DeSio confirmed the drone use, and provided the quote: “This agency has been at the forefront of domestic use of drones by law enforcement. That’s all I can say at the moment.”</li>
</ul>

<p>These claims have been cited in dozens or hundreds of subsequent articles, <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5983175/report-ex+cop-christopher-dorner-is-now-a-target-for-drones">beginning with Gizmodo</a>. But each of these claims is suspect, and taken collectively I believe they are false. Taking a look at each:</p>

<h2 id="the-first-human-target">“The first human target”</h2>

<p>That Dorner would be the first human target for drone surveillance on US soil is true only if you take a very particular, and unusual, read on some of the words. If there are drones tracking him, he is at least the second case on US soil, after <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/2011/dec/10/nation/la-na-drone-arrest-20111211">a 2011 arrest based on drone evidence in North Dakota</a>. In that case, as is alleged in this case, the drones were Customs and Border Protection MQ-9 “Reaper” drones (a model previously known as “Predator B”). In that case, the suspects’ general location was known, and the drone was used to determine their specific location on a single property, and whether they were armed or not. If that makes them ineligible to be the “first human target[s] for remotely-controlled airborne drones on US soil”, it’s not clear how.</p>

<h2 id="senior-police-source-on-thermal-imaging">Senior police source on thermal imaging</h2>

<p>It’s not clear why this source would be attributed anonymously, or where this quote comes from. Without a name or the circumstances of its delivery, it’s difficult or impossible to verify the quote. And how did a tiny paper in the United Kingdom get such a juicy source more than 10,000 miles away in the Los Angeles police department?</p>

<h2 id="chief-sergio-diaz-using-all-the-tools-at-his-disposal">Chief Sergio Diaz “using all the tools” at his disposal</h2>

<p>If Chief Sergio Diaz said that the task force is using all the tools at its disposal to hunt down Dorning, it’s likely he said it at a press conference on Thursday morning, February 7, 2013. If so, it’s not clear why the line didn’t get more attention. An online student-run newspaper from the University of Southern California — “Neon Tommy” — <a href="http://www.neontommy.com/news/2013/02/are-drones-being-used-dorner-manhunt">attributes the quote to him in an article published on the 7th</a>. However, that article is explicitly about LAPD’s declining to state whether drones are being used — not presented as evidence that they’re in use.</p>

<p>What’s more, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pAUWjjXuuCo">this video from the press conference</a> does not appear to include that question or response, and despite the obvious newsworthiness of such a quote, it doesn’t show up in other publications.</p>

<h2 id="cbp-confirmation-and-spokesman-quote">CBP confirmation and spokesman quote</h2>

<p>If CBP spokesman Ralph DeSio did confirm drone usage, it’s not clear how or where he did so. <a href="http://www.neontommy.com/news/2013/02/are-drones-being-used-dorner-manhunt">The same Neon Tommy article mentioned above</a> cites Ralph DeSio as the source for information about where CPB drones are deployed. Curiously, the very next quote in that article is identical to what Express alleged DeSio to have said: “The agency has been on the forefront of domestic use of drones by law enforcement.” However, that quote is attributed — and linked — to <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/11/19/us-border-drones-deal-wit_n_2159255.html">an article by the investigative reporting group California Watch</a>. Did a hasty read of the Neon Tommy article lead to a bad attribution in the Express? Unfortunately, the addition of the next sentence, “That’s all I can say at the moment” gives the impression of unclean hands.</p>

<p>Yes, it’s possible that Express contacted Ralph DeSio over the weekend, got the confirmation, and then a quote from him that is out-of-character for the organization and plagiarized from a California Watch piece. But that seems unlikely.</p>

<h2 id="sorting-out-loose-ends">Sorting out loose ends</h2>

<p>In a rush to clarify that CPB drones aren’t in fact armed, and teasing out information on whether the drones in question were, say, launched from the <a href="http://www.163rw.ang.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123309053">a nearby Air Force Base that has recently tested search-and-rescue flights</a>, there are some deeper unanswered questions.</p>

<p>The story is plausible. <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/2012/aug/05/nation/la-na-drones-testing-20120805">The Department of Homeland Security (CPB’s parent agency) does loan out drones to police agencies</a>, and they’ve kept the terms of such deals almost completely secret. <a href="https://www.eff.org/press/releases/eff-demands-answers-about-predator-drone-flights-us">EFF is currently suing DHS to find more information about that program</a>. But in this case, the factual support isn’t there.</p>

<p>Whether or not these drones are being used in this manhunt, and whether or not they’re armed (they’re not), there is real cause for concern. A secret aerial surveillance program wherein federal agencies loan military technology to local police forces raises serious questions and we should demand to know more. The expansion of warrantless surveillance to unarmed vehicles with capabilities that exceed any helicopter or light plane currently in operation is also a problem. The general militarization of police is well-documented and alarming, as is the shift in rhetoric and actions in the Dorner case from capture-and-try to capture-and-kill.</p>

<p>But we do a disservice to our efforts at resolving these important issues when we resort to untruths or conspiracy theories.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="christopher dorner" /><category term="drones" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="los angeles" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you’ve been on Twitter today, you’ve probably seen it promoted as fact that surveillance drones have been sent into operation over Los Angeles as part of the multi-state manhunt for former cop Christopher Dorner alleged to be on a killing spree. The worst articles imply that the drones are armed and the government has authorized Dorner’s death, using language that’s ambiguous to the point of being deceptive, which is almost certainly untrue. But a closer look at the articles raises another concern: all of the reports are citing a single article which is flawed at best, and at worst may even be fabricated. Are the police using a drone at all?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SXSW panel proposals</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/sxsw-panel-proposals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SXSW panel proposals" /><published>2012-08-20T02:21:29-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-20T02:21:29-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/sxsw-panel-proposals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/sxsw-panel-proposals/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve submitted two proposals for panels at next year’s South by Southwest festival in Austin. I really hope one of them gets picked. The PanelPicker is currently open for voting (I’d appreciate your votes!) and then I’ll know later this year if I’m in.</p>

<p><a href="http://panelpicker.sxsw.com/vote/4022">Ebooks: A Coming War for the Soul of the Library</a> will be with my friends Audrey Evans and Nancy Sims (<a href="https://twitter.com/copyrightlibn">@CopyrightLibn</a>) and cover the issues libraries face as publishers push for an ebook licensing model to replace the current <a href="http://www.copyright.gov/title17/92chap1.html#108">108</a> and first sale regime. I made a video to explain the panel:</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/HncrSUaJMfI" width="560"></iframe>

<p>The second panel proposal is called <a href="http://panelpicker.sxsw.com/vote/6458">Drones Gone Wild</a>, and will be with my colleague Trevor, as well as <a href="http://twitter.com/rcalo">Ryan Calo</a> and Nabiha Syed, who’s currently a First Amendment Fellow for the New York Times and who has been instrumental in <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/eff-and-muckrock-partner-see-how-your-local-police-are-using-drones">the EFF/MuckRock drone request campaign</a>. (Trevor and I previously <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/07/pwn-the-drones-presentation-at-hope/">spoke together about drones at HOPE</a> and we co-operate <a href="https://twitter.com/drones">@drones</a>.) We’ll be talking about the rise of domestic drones and the privacy problems they introduce.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="drones" /><category term="e-books" /><category term="EFF" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="sxsw" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve submitted two proposals for panels at next year’s South by Southwest festival in Austin. I really hope one of them gets picked. The PanelPicker is currently open for voting (I’d appreciate your votes!) and then I’ll know later this year if I’m in.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pwn the Drones presentation at HOPE</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/07/pwn-the-drones-presentation-at-hope/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pwn the Drones presentation at HOPE" /><published>2012-07-30T01:16:27-04:00</published><updated>2012-07-30T01:16:27-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/07/pwn-the-drones-presentation-at-hope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/07/pwn-the-drones-presentation-at-hope/"><![CDATA[<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="428" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/EXI-rGIq0iw" width="570"></iframe>

<p>Last week my colleague (and fellow <a href="https://twitter.com/drones">@drones</a> operator) Trevor and I had the opportunity to present at the <a href="http://www.hopenumbernine.net/">HOPE9</a> conference at the Hotel Pennsylvania in New York. It was an amazing conference and I was really honored to get to speak there.</p>

<p>Our presentation was titled “<a href="http://www.hopenumbernine.net/schedule/#pwn">Pwn the Drones</a>: A Survey of UAV Hacks and Exploits,” and covered three major points:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Drones are already in widespread use, and that is set to expand dramatically over the next few years.</li>
  <li>They do not have the best safety record, and have been compromised in attacks on their ground networks, GPS modules, data transmission, and in kinetic attacks on the aircraft itself. Related systems, such as the control satellites, have also been exploited.</li>
  <li>Drones have also been used to deliver payloads in other unusual hacks and exploits, by activists, artists, law enforcement agents, and others.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve already cleaned up the talk once to give a shorter version at <a href="http://dorkbot.org/dorkbotsf/archive/201207/">dorkbot sf</a>. It’s so important that information about the capabilities of — and weaknesses in — this drone technology gets more widely understood as these get deployed, so I’m happy to do what I can to help that endeavor.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="drones" /><category term="hope" /><category term="new york" /><category term="trevor timm" /><category term="video" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>