<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/ebooks.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:04:09-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/ebooks.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">“We will need writers who can remember freedom”: Ursula K Le Guin at the National Book Awards</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/will-need-writers-can-remember-freedom-ursula-k-le-guin-national-book-awards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“We will need writers who can remember freedom”: Ursula K Le Guin at the National Book Awards" /><published>2014-11-19T23:38:35-05:00</published><updated>2014-11-19T23:38:35-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/will-need-writers-can-remember-freedom-ursula-k-le-guin-national-book-awards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/will-need-writers-can-remember-freedom-ursula-k-le-guin-national-book-awards/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Screen-Shot-2014-11-19-at-8.39.31-PM.png" alt="Screen Shot 2014-11-19 at 8.39.31 PM" /></p>

<p>Ursula K. Le Guin was honored at the National Book Awards tonight and gave a fantastic speech about the dangers to literature and how they can be stopped. As far as I know it’s not available online yet (update: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Et9Nf-rsALk">the video is now online</a>), so I’ve transcribed it from the livestream below. The parts in parentheses were ad-libbed directly to the audience, and the Neil thanked is Neil Gaiman, who presented her with the award.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thank you Neil, and to the givers of this beautiful reward, my thanks from the heart. My family, my agent, editors, know that my being here is their doing as well as mine, and that the beautiful reward is theirs as much as mine. And I rejoice at accepting it for, and sharing it with, all the writers who were excluded from literature for so long, my fellow authors of fantasy and science fiction—writers of the imagination, who for the last 50 years watched the beautiful rewards go to the so-called realists.</p>

  <p>I think hard times are coming when we will be wanting the voices of writers who can see alternatives to how we live now and can see through our fear-stricken society and its obsessive technologies to other ways of being, and even imagine some real grounds for hope. We will need writers who can remember freedom. Poets, visionaries—the realists of a larger reality.</p>

  <p>Right now, I think we need writers who know the difference between the production of a market commodity and the practice of an art. Developing written material to suit sales strategies in order to maximize corporate profit and advertising revenue is not quite the same thing as responsible book publishing or authorship. (Thank you, brave applauders.)</p>

  <p>Yet I see sales departments given control over editorial; I see my own publishers in a silly panic of ignorance and greed, charging public libraries for an ebook six or seven times more than they charge customers. We just saw a profiteer try to punish a publisher for disobedience and writers threatened by corporate fatwa, and I see a lot of us, the producers who write the books, and make the books, accepting this. Letting commodity profiteers sell us like deodorant, and tell us what to publish and what to write. (Well, I love you too, darling.)</p>

  <p>Books, you know, they’re not just commodities. The profit motive often is in conflict with the aims of art. We live in capitalism. Its power seems inescapable. So did the divine right of kings. Any human power can be resisted and changed by human beings. Resistance and change often begin in art, and very often in our art—the art of words.</p>

  <p>I have had a long career and a good one. In good company. Now here, at the end of it, I really don’t want to watch American literature get sold down the river. We who live by writing and publishing want—and should demand—our fair share of the proceeds. But the name of our beautiful reward is not profit. Its name is freedom.</p>

  <p>Thank you.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="books" /><category term="ebooks" /><category term="ursula k le guin" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ebooks and ethics in the New York Times</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/10/ebooks-ethics-new-york-times/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ebooks and ethics in the New York Times" /><published>2014-10-13T01:27:55-04:00</published><updated>2014-10-13T01:27:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/10/ebooks-ethics-new-york-times</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/10/ebooks-ethics-new-york-times/"><![CDATA[<p>When Chuck Klosterman <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/28/magazine/steal-this-e-book.html">weighed in on the ethics of downloading ebooks</a> last month, he became the third writer for the New York Times ethicist column to do so in the last four years—starting with <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/04/magazine/04FOB-ethicist-t.html">Randy Cohen in 2010</a>, and continuing with <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/15/magazine/to-mooch-or-not-to-mooch.html#p[TmpNW]">Philip Corbett in 2012</a>. I’ve enjoyed some of Klosterman’s writing a lot, but I’m not thrilled with his work as Ethicist. This answer follows that trend, forgoing ethical insight for a rigid application of contractual terms.</p>

<p>The question comes from a reader who has purchased the hardcover edition of a book, and then downloaded another copy without authorization for convenience’s sake. Klosterman says he’d prefer that a book purchase were a license to read a book in any format the purchaser likes, but that publishers disagree and they write the rules. From his column:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The publisher ultimately decides if buying a physical copy of my book entitles you to automatically own it across multiple platforms. And in almost every case I’ve encountered, it does not. Publishers tend to view the electronic version of a book as a separate entity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s some awfully shallow analysis: that defying the wishes of a publisher is per se unethical—and despite an ethicist weighing in that it <em>should</em> be otherwise. It stubbornly subordinates readers’ rights to the profit-maximizing goals of publishing companies, ignoring the many ways they have attempted to control secondary uses. (Would a turn-of-the-century Klosterman say it was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobbs-Merrill_Co._v._Straus">unethical to sell a copy of <em>The Castaway</em> for 50 cents</a>? What would Klosterman have said last year about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobbs-Merrill_Co._v._Straus">re-selling a book bought overseas</a>?)</p>

<p>Contrast that to <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/04/magazine/04FOB-ethicist-t.html">Randy Cohen’s 2010 answer</a>. Despite being four years old, it works almost perfectly as a response to Klosterman’s recent answer. Cohen:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s true that you might have thwarted the publisher’s intent — perhaps he or she has a violent antipathy to trees, maybe a wish to slaughter acres of them and grind them into Stephen King novels. Or to clog the highways with trucks crammed with Stephen King novels. Or perhaps King himself wishes to improve America’s physique by having readers lug massive volumes.</p>

  <p>So be it. Your paying for the hardcover put you in the clear as a matter of ethics, forestry and fitness training.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good answer. An ethicist that won’t prize ethics over non-negotiable one-sided boilerplate rights-grab agreements isn’t much of an ethicist at all.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="chuck klosterman" /><category term="ebooks" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="new york times" /><category term="randy cohen" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When Chuck Klosterman weighed in on the ethics of downloading ebooks last month, he became the third writer for the New York Times ethicist column to do so in the last four years—starting with Randy Cohen in 2010, and continuing with Philip Corbett in 2012. I’ve enjoyed some of Klosterman’s writing a lot, but I’m not thrilled with his work as Ethicist. This answer follows that trend, forgoing ethical insight for a rigid application of contractual terms.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accepting Amazon’s DRM makes it impossible to challenge its monopoly</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/accepting-amazons-drm-makes-it-impossible-to-challenge-its-monopoly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accepting Amazon’s DRM makes it impossible to challenge its monopoly" /><published>2014-05-26T18:56:32-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-26T18:56:32-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/accepting-amazons-drm-makes-it-impossible-to-challenge-its-monopoly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/accepting-amazons-drm-makes-it-impossible-to-challenge-its-monopoly/"><![CDATA[<p>Amazon was the target of some well-deserved criticism this week for making the anti-customer move of <a href="http://kottke.org/14/05/hachette-job-amazon-unprime">suspending sales of books published by Hachette</a>, reportedly as a hardball tactic in its ongoing negotiations over ebook revenue splits. In an excellent article, Mathew Ingram connects this with <a href="http://gigaom.com/2014/05/23/giants-behaving-badly-google-facebook-and-amazon-show-us-the-downside-of-monopolies-and-black-box-algorithms/">other recent bad behavior by Internet giants</a> leveraging their monopolies. Others have made the connection between this move and a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/30/technology/30amazon.html">similar one in 2010</a>, when Amazon pulled Macmillan books off its digital shelves.</p>

<p>That dispute took place a little over four years ago, and ended with Amazon giving in and issuing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/forum/kindle/Tx2MEGQWTNGIMHV?_encoding=UTF8&amp;cdForum=Fx1D7SY3BVSESG&amp;displayType=tagsDetail&amp;ref_=cm_cd_tfp_ef_tft_tp">a statement</a> that people found a bit strange. Here’s a quote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We want you to know that ultimately, however, we will have to capitulate and accept Macmillan’s terms because Macmillan has a monopoly over their own titles, and we will want to offer them to you even at prices we believe are needlessly high for e-books.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Monopoly” was a funny choice of words there. The author John Scalzi, whose <a href="http://whatever.scalzi.com/2010/02/01/all-the-many-ways-amazon-so-very-failed-the-weekend/">piece decrying Amazon’s actions at the time</a> is still very much worth reading, memorably took issue:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And not only a forum comment, but a mystifyingly silly one: the bit in the comment about Amazon having no choice but to back down in the fight because “Macmillan has a monopoly over their own titles” was roundly mocked by authors, some of whom <a href="http://www.tobiasbuckell.com/2010/01/31/together-lets-break-the-amazon-monopoly-on-kindles/">immediately started agitating against Amazon’s “monopoly” of the Kindle</a>, or noted <a href="http://leegoldberg.typepad.com/a_writers_life/2010/01/nabisco-has-a-monopoly-on-oreos.html">how terrible it was that Nabisco had a “monopoly” on Oreos</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Monopoly, of course, is <em>economically</em> the correct term. Publishers of books that are restricted by copyright have a set of exclusive rights granted to them by law. Their monopoly looks distinct from Amazon’s near-monopoly bookseller position, though, because it’s one agreed to in public policy. In a sense it is also more absolute, and less vulnerable to challenge, because it’s a <em>legal monopoly</em>, and not just a <em>market monopoly</em>.</p>

<p>To the extent Amazon has a monopoly on selling paper books, then, it could be challenged not just by legal action (such as antitrust investigation) but by other businesses competing. There would be some extreme logistical difficulties, and disparities created by economies of scale that might be impossible to overcome, but in principle other businesses are able to compete for Amazon’s market position on physical books.</p>

<p>Copyright behaves differently: when it comes to Macmillan or Hachette’s books, nobody may undercut prices by making production more efficient, or design prettier covers, or edit the text into a more compelling presentation. Where that’s a good thing, it’s because we’ve reached it by public policy. We’ve granted copyright holders an inviolable (if limited) <em>legal monopoly</em> because we as a society like the results. ((Of course, that is only as true as copyright policy reflects the will of the public, which it doesn’t, but it’s something to aspire to.))</p>

<p>A very real danger, though, is if Amazon can take the challengeable market monopoly it has put together, and ratchet it into an unchallengeable legal monopoly. That is exactly what DRM does.</p>

<p>By putting DRM on its digital products—ebooks and audio books—Amazon gets the legal backing of the Digital Millennium Copyright Act’s anti-circumvention restrictions on its products. This isn’t for the advancement of public policy goals, either; Amazon gets to create the private law it wants to be enforced. Thanks to DRM, Kindle users are no longer free to take their business elsewhere—if you want a Kindle book, you must purchase it from Amazon.</p>

<p>Fortunately Kindle software can, for now, read other non-restricted formats. But the functionality is limited, and not guaranteed to stick around. And it’s a one-way street: other software and hardware may not read ebooks in the Kindle format. Customers who amass a Kindle library will find no compatible non-Amazon reader. The fact that individual users can usually circumvent the DRM, too, doesn’t help businesses trying to compete in that space.</p>

<p>Amazon has a lot of fans, and they tend to ascribe its rise as a bookseller for its aggressively pro-customer stance. If it drops that stance, even major fans would probably agree that it no longer deserves the throne. Unfortunately, DRM takes the conditional monopoly that customers like (you get to be the largest bookseller so long as you’re good to your customers) and replaces it with an unconditional one (you once achieved monopoly and that is now permanent).</p>

<p>This week’s sketchy move against Hachette looks like a willingness to throw its customers under a bus in the name of better business deals. If publishers continue to insist on DRM, and if customers continue to allow it, we lose our ability to object.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="amazon" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="drm" /><category term="ebooks" /><category term="hachette" /><category term="macmillan" /><category term="mathew ingram" /><category term="monopoly" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon was the target of some well-deserved criticism this week for making the anti-customer move of suspending sales of books published by Hachette, reportedly as a hardball tactic in its ongoing negotiations over ebook revenue splits. In an excellent article, Mathew Ingram connects this with other recent bad behavior by Internet giants leveraging their monopolies. Others have made the connection between this move and a similar one in 2010, when Amazon pulled Macmillan books off its digital shelves.]]></summary></entry></feed>