<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/feminism.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:46:58-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/feminism.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Misogyny on Mars</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/08/misogyny-on-mars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Misogyny on Mars" /><published>2015-08-15T16:09:56-04:00</published><updated>2015-08-15T16:09:56-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/08/misogyny-on-mars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/08/misogyny-on-mars/"><![CDATA[<p>Even though <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martian_%28Weir_novel%29"><em>The Martian</em></a> was only officially released last year, I felt like it sat in my to-read pile for way too long before I finally got to it this week. And while I really enjoyed the book, I was disappointed by the lonely protagonist’s occasional sexist comments, which were unnecessary, a little cheap, and (one hopes) out of place in an era where humans are making repeat visits to Mars.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Curiosity-Rover-Portrait-Mars-Mojave-Selfie-pia19142-MALHI-br2.jpg" alt="Curiosity-Rover-Portrait-Mars-Mojave-Selfie-pia19142-MALHI-br2" /></p>

<p><em>Note: This post is mostly spoiler-free, unless you have no idea what the book is about at all and want to preserve that complete innocence. Basically, everything in here is the background you’d get in the one sentence synopsis: Mark Watney gets left for dead on Mars and he and NASA spend the book trying to figure out how to get him back.</em></p>

<p>What sorts of comments caught my attention? Among others: at one point he disparages a committee conducting an investigation by telling another NASA employee that “each and every one of their mothers is a prostitute.” He refers to his mission’s chief computer scientist as “a hot chick who went to Mars.” Perhaps worst, he uses the word “rape” to describe intrusive modifications he had to make to a spacecraft.</p>

<p>That sucks. It sucks because it’s a distraction from the gripping story, because it makes Watney seem like more of an insensitive oaf than a likable smart-ass, and because it suggests a cynicism about science work remaining uninviting.</p>

<p>But mostly, it sucks because <em>The Martian</em> is an engaging story of space exploration that could spark a desire in young people to pursue interests in STEM. Unfortunately, these offhand remarks also sends the message that half of those young readers will be less welcome if they do so.</p>

<p>And for a novel so widely praised for its ingenuity and attention to detail, it seems like a weird example of lazy character development. An interview response from author Andy Weir doesn’t do much to assuage that concern:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It was a really easy book to write; I just had him say what I would say.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When <em>The Martian</em> was self-published in 2011—and even when it was released by a publisher in early 2014—these concerns may have been off people’s radar. A lot of that changed in late 2014, when the excellent Rose Eveleth ((Did you read her article on <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/07/futurism-sexism-men/400097/">futurism’s lack of women</a>? Go do that, I’ll wait.)) started a global conversation about women in STEM when she called out the <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/11/13/7213819/your-bowling-shirt-is-holding-back-progress">inappropriate sexist shirt one scientist wore</a> to celebrate landing a spacecraft on a comet.</p>

<p>Matt Taylor’s shirt wasn’t intended to send any larger message, just as Mark Watney’s comments are surely “just a joke.” And it’s true, that scientist’s shirt doesn’t define him any more than a few lines of dialogue define a character over the course of 370 pages. But in both cases, it projects an air of hostility and unwelcomeness to women in a field that has historically excluded them.</p>

<p>I hope this is an arena where we’re making progress. I hope the issues that Eveleth highlighted are getting better—and I hope they’re getting better fast enough that the real 17th person on Mars doesn’t think in sexist terms about his colleagues and crew. In that optimistic worldview, Watney’s comments feel weirdly anachronistic.</p>

<p>But there’s also a degree of self-fulfilling prophecy, and this kind of dialogue from a generally likable character doesn’t help the cause. With <em>The Martian</em> as a best-seller, and its movie adaptation coming out later this year, it is one of the most prominent public representations of space exploration out there right now. It’s disappointing that, despite placing women in powerful mission roles, it perpetuates stereotypes of misogyny and sexism in space.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="andy weir" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="mars" /><category term="nasa" /><category term="the martian" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Even though The Martian was only officially released last year, I felt like it sat in my to-read pile for way too long before I finally got to it this week. And while I really enjoyed the book, I was disappointed by the lonely protagonist’s occasional sexist comments, which were unnecessary, a little cheap, and (one hopes) out of place in an era where humans are making repeat visits to Mars.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art+Feminism Wikipedia edit-a-thon</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art+Feminism Wikipedia edit-a-thon" /><published>2014-02-03T04:11:30-05:00</published><updated>2014-02-03T04:11:30-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon/"><![CDATA[<p>I had a great time this weekend editing Wikipedia at the San Francisco satellite of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Meetup/ArtAndFeminism">Art+Feminism edit-a-thon</a>. Check out the venue:</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/BfaobBGCMAE0C4N.jpg" alt="Art and Feminism edit-a-thon" /></p>

<p>There were a few dozen people there, mostly new to editing, all excited to contribute some work. And we got a lot of great stuff done! I spent most of the day teaching people how to use the markup (lots of people needed additional help with the citation format) and finding information about the reclusive but increasingly popular artist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutz_Bacher">Lutz Bacher</a>. I hadn’t heard of her before, but in the course of putting together that article I became very interested. I am now trying to get my hands on an early copy of a new major book of her work to see if there’s anything I can add to her bio.</p>

<p>It’s always great to see people make their first few edits, and people were so excited to make a new page and all of a sudden have the thing actually be there and available online. I think that Wikipedia’s ubiquity has really had a lot of influence on that process: people have used hundreds or thousands of articles before, and now they can actually make their own, and it’s a full-fledged part of the site immediately. That’s great.</p>

<p>Another fun thing was talking to people about copyright. Obviously, since the event focused on artists, people wanted to include images and art from the subjects. Sometimes I feel that the case for copyright reform and a freer culture requires a lot of abstraction, but this situation was dramatic and concrete. I probably converted a number of new copyfighters that day.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Meetup/ArtAndFeminism#Results">The results</a> are impressive: dozens of new articles created, dozens more cleaned up or improved, and countless new people editing Wikipedia and slowly—but surely—improving the quality of representation for all kinds of issues.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="san francisco" /><category term="wikipedia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had a great time this weekend editing Wikipedia at the San Francisco satellite of the Art+Feminism edit-a-thon. Check out the venue:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Susan B. Anthony teaches Elizabeth Cady Stanton how to use an iPad</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/12/susan-b-anthony-teaches-elizabeth-cady-stanton-how-to-use-an-ipad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Susan B. Anthony teaches Elizabeth Cady Stanton how to use an iPad" /><published>2013-12-09T02:42:36-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-09T02:42:36-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/12/susan-b-anthony-teaches-elizabeth-cady-stanton-how-to-use-an-ipad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/12/susan-b-anthony-teaches-elizabeth-cady-stanton-how-to-use-an-ipad/"><![CDATA[<p>I made this goofy picture for something on Twitter, but I want to make sure I save this one for posterity. Anyway, here’s Susan B. Anthony teaching elder stateswoman Elizabeth Cady Stanton how to use her new iPad.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/ecsandsba.png" alt="Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony on an iPad" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="elizabeth cady stanton" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="photoshop" /><category term="pictures" /><category term="susan b. anthony" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I made this goofy picture for something on Twitter, but I want to make sure I save this one for posterity. Anyway, here’s Susan B. Anthony teaching elder stateswoman Elizabeth Cady Stanton how to use her new iPad.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two great pieces on women in tech</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/two-great-pieces-on-women-in-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two great pieces on women in tech" /><published>2013-02-09T03:32:54-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-09T03:32:54-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/two-great-pieces-on-women-in-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/two-great-pieces-on-women-in-tech/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s recently been a lot of great writing on women and the problem of gender inequality in the tech field. I recommend these three pieces in particular:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://marihuertas.tumblr.com/post/42437255194">“Not a Beard”</a> by Mari Huertas, who was a member of Obama’s re-election tech team. In an effort to indicate that the team was more San Francisco than Washington, many articles joke about the beards on the team. Needless to say, Mari does not have a beard. From the piece:</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>I want other females, young and old, to feel encouraged by the women who worked on this re-election campaign and in technology, civics, and government as a whole. I want girls and young professionals to find their way by the determined wakes we leave. We’re doing important, satisfying, fun work – we should broaden and extend our purview so more can wade into the fray.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://firstround.com/article/How-Etsy-Grew-their-Number-of-Female-Engineers-by-500-in-One-Year">“How Etsy Grew their Number of Female Engineers by Almost 500% in One Year”</a> by Brett Berson, a member of an investment group that hosted Etsy’s CTO for a talk on the subject. It’s important to note that it wasn’t a cheap or easy fix: it involved spending money intelligently on “Hacker Grants” and consistently and proactively reaching out. But it’s also been worth it, increasing diversity on the team and increasing the quality of applicants, male and female.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Even science recognizes that diversity is important: research from both the Kellogg and Sloan Schools suggest that cognitively diverse teams perform better on hard problems.</p>

      <p>Beyond that, though, hiring for diversity will set up better recruiting opportunities.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’m consistently frustrated by the homogeny of the tech scene in San Francisco and generally, and it’s encouraging to see that people are addressing the problem. It’s a long road ahead, and it extends even beyond gender issues. Another great piece called <a href="http://jamellebouie.net/blog/2013/2/3/and-read-all-over">“And Read All Over”</a> by Jamelle Bouie has done an excellent job, for example, of demonstrating the (mostly) unbearable whiteness of the tech journalism community.</p>

<p>Anyway, I think the importance of these issues is even greater than their obvious effect on the discussion around equality in the tech community. As technical developments increasingly have profound effects on our privacy, speech, and civil liberties, I feel much more comfortable with diverse teams making those decisions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="etsy" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="mari huertas" /><category term="technology" /><category term="women" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s recently been a lot of great writing on women and the problem of gender inequality in the tech field. I recommend these three pieces in particular:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Women’s suffrage and the world’s oldest person</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/womens-suffrage-and-the-worlds-oldest-person/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women’s suffrage and the world’s oldest person" /><published>2012-08-29T12:30:43-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-29T12:30:43-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/womens-suffrage-and-the-worlds-oldest-person</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/womens-suffrage-and-the-worlds-oldest-person/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nineteenth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">Nineteenth Amendment to the US Constitution</a>, which granted women the right to vote, was ratified 92 years ago this month. ((It had been introduced 41 years earlier by Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton, but sometimes it takes a few decades to move the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overton_window">Overton window</a> towards sanity.))</p>

<p>Less than a century is certainly short enough that some women who are alive today were born without the right to vote. But, then, they would’ve been too young to vote at the time anyway. Is there still a woman alive today who could have been denied a vote in a presidential election on the basis of her gender? ((Of course, considering the shocking war on women being waged by the current GOP, there must be plenty of examples of disenfranchisement on the basis of gender. In this post I’m just looking at the timing of the Nineteenth Amendment.))</p>

<p>As it turns out, the answer to that question seems to be yes. The world’s oldest living person happens to be an American woman named Besse Cooper, and <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2012/08/worlds-oldest-person-besse-cooper-turns-116/">she celebrated her 116th birthday this weekend</a>. She was born in 1896 in Sullivan, Tennessee, but moved to Monroe, Georgia during World War I. That means she would have been living in Georgia when she turned 21 on August 26, 1917. (I’m going with 21 instead of 18, because that was the national voting age before the passage of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty-sixth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">Twenty-sixth Amendment in 1971</a>.)</p>

<p>1918 was a Senate election year, and Ms. Cooper would have been denied the right to vote in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate_elections,_1918">that race</a>. Incumbent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_W._Hardwick">Thomas Hardwick</a> lost in the Democratic primary, but two years later was elected governor. One of his most notable acts, incidentally, was appointing the first woman to serve in the Senate, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rebecca_Latimer_Felton">Rebecca Latimer Felton</a>. Her appointment was basically ceremonial — she only served for one day — but to date she’s still Georgia’s only female Senator.</p>

<p>Anyway, cut to two years later and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_1920">the first presidential election since Ms. Cooper’s 21st birthday</a>. Because of the recent ratification, women all over the country were set to vote for the president for the first time. Georgia, however, was not only the first state to reject the amendment, but also continued to resist it even after its ratification. In particular, the legislature <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=rIoEAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA133&amp;lpg=PA133&amp;dq=women+georgia+1920+election+presidential&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Wt-vhlwpa1&amp;sig=BuDzrLZcNu4UcUR-LjGPHeSNJfs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Z4E8UOaYLs7ciQKgyIHYDg&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=women%20georgia%201920%20election%20presidential&amp;f=false">refused to allow women to vote at the polling station</a> because they had failed to register in April and May of that year, before they were legally allowed to do so. ((This point is actually a bit contentious. The source I link to seems credible, but I’d like to hear from people who know more about this.)) Women in Georgia apparently weren’t allowed to vote until the 1922 mid-term election, and the state didn’t formally ratify the amendment until 1970.</p>

<p>Georgia went to James M. Cox, but Warren Harding won the national vote in a landslide. Four years later, Ms. Cooper may have been able to vote for the president after being denied the first time. Ninety-two years later, she may be the only living woman in the country to have had that experience.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="equality" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Nineteenth Amendment to the US Constitution, which granted women the right to vote, was ratified 92 years ago this month. ((It had been introduced 41 years earlier by Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton, but sometimes it takes a few decades to move the Overton window towards sanity.))]]></summary></entry></feed>