<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/film.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:29:15-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/film.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">“The Florida Project” and questions of control</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/10/the-florida-project-and-questions-of-control/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“The Florida Project” and questions of control" /><published>2017-10-13T17:28:22-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-13T17:28:22-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/10/the-florida-project-and-questions-of-control</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/10/the-florida-project-and-questions-of-control/"><![CDATA[<p>I had the opportunity to catch the new movie <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5649144/"><em>The Florida Project</em></a> this week, without any background on how it was made or what it is about. That’s my preferred context for seeing movies, but it does sometimes lead to my feeling a bit adrift in the theater, or—in this case—stressed that something catastrophic was about to go down. Still, I feel like I end up with a better idea of what the movie is actually about if I don’t know the plot going into it. Here’s the trailer, if you want a sense of it.</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/WwQ-NH1rRT4?rel=0" width="560"></iframe>

<p>That was certainly the case with <em>The Florida Project</em>, which has attracted nearly <a href="https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_florida_project/">universally positive reviews</a> from critics (and some confusion from audiences about the ending). Just about every review I’ve read since seeing the movie describes is as “empathetic,” which is spot on, but none really dive into what the audience is feeling empathy for. This post lays out my explanation, and to do so includes some very minor spoilers. I don’t really think this movie can be “spoiled,” but skip this post if you want to.</p>

<p>To my mind, what the movie does a great job of showing is how people seek spaces where they can be autonomous and in control. It shows children exploring and imagining, but (most importantly) testing out their agency. At the same time, it shows adults, living precarious existences, staking out small pieces of space where they are in charge.</p>

<p>The building manager Bobby is an obvious example, and his arguments with tenants can almost always be framed in this light: whether he’s enforcing the pool rules, confronting unwelcome strangers, or (most tellingly) moving tenants around to prevent them from establishing residency, he is exerting control over his designated space and limiting the autonomy of the people in it. In that last example, too, he alludes to the fact that he’s an agent of another level of power, specifically pointing at the surveillance cameras to explain how his hands are tied.</p>

<p>Halley’s actions in this area are even more illuminating. You can see it best when she gets into conflict with her best friend Ashley. Though Halley doesn’t even know the basis of their argument, she takes it out on her friend by finding a space where Ashley has no autonomy—her workplace—and exercises arbitrary control over her. From that perspective, it’s only a matter of degree when their dispute escalates to violence, and then when Ashley (it’s implied) calls for an intervention by the state.</p>

<p>In that penultimate scene, where Halley is arguing with DCF agents, she makes this unspoken theme somewhat explicit, saying that they’re on her “property.” Throughout the film there are a lot of reasons to think that unit 323 isn’t really Halley’s “property,” but in that moment she reaches for that language to express that she is in control.</p>

<p>The final scene takes that declaration and escalates it to a sort of surreal and metaphorical place. Echoing the film’s tagline (“Find your kingdom”), Moonee and her friend run to a place that feels like their kingdom, where they are the kings. It’s a bit jarring in a film that’s seemed so grounded and “real” to get such a visual metaphor in the closing moments, but it works (and at the same time drives home the juxtaposition between poverty and expensive fantasy that runs under the whole story).</p>

<p>Maybe most movies could be described in these terms—as Octavia Butler said, “all struggles are, essentially, power struggles.” But I think it brings a lot to <em>The Florida Project</em> in particular to think of areas of control and autonomy. The characters shown in the movie are living precarious existences, and seek that kind of control where they can get it. One message from the film is that, where these kinds of spaces aren’t really available, people will find a way to exert control nonetheless. The empathy in this movie is showing the decisions of people who have been rendered powerless in society.</p>

<p>Policies that perpetuate wealth inequality or pervasive surveillance make communities feel that powerlessness. When people talk about those communities “voting against their interests,” it’s worth considering that interest in exercising some kind of control.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="control" /><category term="film" /><category term="power" /><category term="the florida project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had the opportunity to catch the new movie The Florida Project this week, without any background on how it was made or what it is about. That’s my preferred context for seeing movies, but it does sometimes lead to my feeling a bit adrift in the theater, or—in this case—stressed that something catastrophic was about to go down. Still, I feel like I end up with a better idea of what the movie is actually about if I don’t know the plot going into it. Here’s the trailer, if you want a sense of it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Computers: The Truth of the Matter”</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Computers: The Truth of the Matter”" /><published>2015-07-13T02:45:32-04:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T02:45:32-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter/"><![CDATA[<p>Disney Educational made a short film in 1983 that depicts the devil and an angel arguing over whether a young woman should learn about computers. It’s called “Computers: The Truth of the Matter,” and I got to see it at the Oddball Films archive on Friday as part of <a href="http://oddballfilms.blogspot.com/2015/07/computerized-yesterdays-technology-for.html">a screening of retro-computing shorts</a>. I looked it up online later and found <a href="http://disney.wikia.com/wiki/List_of_Disney_live-action_shorts">basically nothing</a>, so I thought I’d write up a few words for future searchers.</p>

<p>The film starts with the young woman Jessica slipping into her school’s computer lab, excited for a few quiet moments alone to work with the machines. Her practice time is interrupted a second later when Luke, a devil-figure in a red fedora, appears in a puff of smoke and starts trying to dissuade her from learning, arguing that computers are hard and not really that useful anyway.</p>

<p>A minute later, the classroom door opens and blinding light appears behind it. Angelo, a chubby guy in white gold-trimmed sweats and a winged baseball cap steps out to argue the opposite, that computers are worthwhile to learn. When Jessica shows interest, he pulls her in and they teleport around seeing the applications of computer systems, and then back into the classroom to talk about input devices, CPUs, and output devices like displays and printers. At one point he shrinks the two of them down to walk on top of a microprocessor.</p>

<div class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_1515" style="width: 550px">![Image via Oddball Films](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/computers-matter-1024x745.jpg)Image via [Oddball Films](http://oddballfilms.blogspot.com/2015/07/computerized-yesterdays-technology-for.html)

</div>
<p>Throughout this, the devil figure keeps interjecting that she doesn’t really want to learn, that computers are unpredictable, and so forth.</p>

<p>Eventually Jessica’s convinced, and the devil zaps out of the classroom. In the last shot, we see him at a fiery desk counting the tally at this point: millions of converts for Angelo, zero for himself. Of course, he’s keeping the tally on a computer. When he sees the camera come in, he tries denying it, saying he was watching TV and typing a letter.</p>

<p>The movie is funny in a bit of a forced way, and of course very little of the substantive material “holds up,” in the sense that it would be useful educational material in a computer class today. The high level stuff is still correct, but the examples are decades out of date. But I couldn’t disagree more with the <a href="http://www.dvdizzy.com/forum/viewtopic.php?p=343952&amp;sid=9f6daa37e33b9c6f2ea1ed80f1d7c78c#p343952">folks in, say, this forum thread</a> who claim that it’s no longer relevant and so shouldn’t be prioritized for re-release.</p>

<p>Films like “The Truth of the Matter” have a really important place in the history of computers. It’s remarkable to see the lessons it teaches, not because of the content itself but because of what it says about what was once assumed, or needed to be explicit. One line in this movie that caught me by surprise was when it showed a student working on a term paper, and the narrator remarked that even though it would get corrections and multiple drafts, she would only need to type it up once. Surely it’s worth something to get a glimpse into a world where that was a point that needed to be made.</p>

<p>Anyway, the film hasn’t been reissued, and <a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/computers-the-truth-of-the-matter/oclc/81479604">glancing through Worldcat</a> it looks tricky to track down a copy. I might try nonetheless. I’m also interested to see some of the other Disney Educational shorts from that era, like the 1983 “Skills for a New Technology: What a Kid needs to Know Today: Living with Computers,” or the 1984 “Ethics in the Computer Age.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="computers" /><category term="disney" /><category term="film" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disney Educational made a short film in 1983 that depicts the devil and an angel arguing over whether a young woman should learn about computers. It’s called “Computers: The Truth of the Matter,” and I got to see it at the Oddball Films archive on Friday as part of a screening of retro-computing shorts. I looked it up online later and found basically nothing, so I thought I’d write up a few words for future searchers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 years of cinematic copyright</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/10/100-years-of-cinematic-copyright/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 years of cinematic copyright" /><published>2012-10-15T02:58:36-04:00</published><updated>2012-10-15T02:58:36-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/10/100-years-of-cinematic-copyright</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/10/100-years-of-cinematic-copyright/"><![CDATA[<p>I know this is a wonky thing, but I was reading the Library of Congress blog this week when I saw <a href="http://blogs.loc.gov/loc/2012/10/centennial-of-cinema-under-copyright-law/">an article about the centennial of copyright for film works</a>. Prior to that date, film was not on the list of classes of work that were eligible. Filmmakers would instead send in collections of stills from the film, because photographs had already been eligible since 1865, like this series from 1894 of a man named Fred Ott sneezing in an Edison Kinetoscope movie. By the way, I love that this is what movies used to be.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/sneeze_crop2a.jpeg" alt="" title="Sneeze film" /></p>

<p>It’s telling — if not surprising — that film studios lobbied at the time for a limit on the statutory damages that could be issued against them for unintentional copying. From the post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At the urging of the movie industry, the amendment also limited statutory damages that could be awarded against movie studios for innocent infringement of nondramatic works.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>How things change. Today’s movie industry, of course, has been one of the largest institutional supporters of insane levels of statutory damages, even <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/mpaa-joins-riaa-in-monstrous-jammie-thomas-appeal-120106/">filing a brief in support of the RIAA</a> and a $1.92 million fine against a p2p song downloader.</p>

<p>The tragedy, of course, is that the content industry’s addiction to expanding copyright scope has caused it to discard its own history. And that’s our cultural history, too. In William Patry’s latest book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Fix-Copyright-William-Patry/dp/0199760098/">How to Fix Copyright</a>,” he goes into the sad history of film archiving: Hollywood doesn’t even own copies of many of the films it has produced, and the distended term length has made it difficult to be certain of the legality of preservation efforts by archives and the like. The Library of Congress initially refused to collect samples, because the film was printed on highly flammable nitrate film, but now holds copies of some 200,000 movies. But there is also difficult-to-find and rare footage spread across 1,750 archives.</p>

<p>The failure to archive is real and frustrating. The article refers to one of the first films that was submitted for copyright protection, another of Edison’s films called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Charge_of_the_Light_Brigade_(1912_film)">The Charge of the Light Brigade</a>.” (Another non-surprise: it’s based on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Charge_of_the_Light_Brigade_(poem)">an earlier poem by Alfred, Lord Tennyson</a>, and inspired a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Charge_of_the_Light_Brigade_(1968_film)">1968 film by the same name</a>.) It was apparently issued as an extra on the Region 2 DVD release of that 1968 film, but I can’t find it online.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="film" /><category term="thomas edison" /><category term="william patry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I know this is a wonky thing, but I was reading the Library of Congress blog this week when I saw an article about the centennial of copyright for film works. Prior to that date, film was not on the list of classes of work that were eligible. Filmmakers would instead send in collections of stills from the film, because photographs had already been eligible since 1865, like this series from 1894 of a man named Fred Ott sneezing in an Edison Kinetoscope movie. By the way, I love that this is what movies used to be.]]></summary></entry></feed>