<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/gadgets.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:33:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/gadgets.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Conversation’s just fine, thanks: a response to Sherry Turkle</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/04/conversations-just-fine-thanks-a-response-to-sherry-turkle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conversation’s just fine, thanks: a response to Sherry Turkle" /><published>2012-04-30T01:46:55-04:00</published><updated>2012-04-30T01:46:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/04/conversations-just-fine-thanks-a-response-to-sherry-turkle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/04/conversations-just-fine-thanks-a-response-to-sherry-turkle/"><![CDATA[<p>Every once in a while, my <a href="http://iron-blogger-sf.com/participants/">Iron Blogger group</a> decides to take on a common topic. At our meet-up this week, a handful of us agreed to take on <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/22/opinion/sunday/the-flight-from-conversation.html?pagewanted=all">last week’s Sherry Turkle op-ed in the New York Times</a>. It’s called “The Flight from Conversation,” and it seems to cover some of the same territory as her book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alone-Together-Expect-Technology-Other/dp/0465010210/">Alone Together</a>”: namely, that we’re allowing gadgets to get in the way of interpersonal communication, favoring “sips” of online contact over a “big gulp of real conversation.”</p>

<p>I disagree with Turkle on both her premise and its conclusion. I’m just not convinced that the anecdotes she collects amount to more than <a href="http://www.poynter.org/latest-news/making-sense-of-news/105778/how-slates-jack-shafer-calls-out-bogus-trend-stories/">the kind of bogus trend story NY Times is notorious for</a>. Worse, it has the particular flavor of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moral_panic">moral panic</a>, where the issue raised threatens to disrupt the social order. But just as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/26/health/26teen.html">teen texting</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seduction_of_the_Innocent">comic books</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_controversies#Psychological_impact">Dungeons and Dragons</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mods_and_Rockers">rock and roll</a>, and many others failed to unravel the threads of society, we may just make it through the “handheld gadget” era.</p>

<p>In fact, of course, the sort of conversations we have today are the result of refinement over thousands of years, and it would require extraordinary evidence to support the extraordinary claim that this latest change is different in kind and the one that will finally undo us.</p>

<p>And really, the examples Turkle cites don’t seem new. Quiet offices, 16-year-old boys who wish they knew how to hold a conversation, high school students who don’t want to speak with their parents about dating — are these really the products of mobile devices, or the way things always have been? Am I mistaken to think that a high school sophomore in 1952 would have wanted an alternative to asking his father for dating advice, even if he couldn’t characterize it as a sophisticated AI?</p>

<p>More importantly, though, I object to the idea that the inclusion of technology in conversation makes it any less “real,” or even less good. Certain kinds of conversations seem less likely, like those between passengers on a bus or elevator, or, say, patients in a waiting room. But — and I don’t mean to be flip here — so what? These aren’t the “big gulp” conversation Turkle’s concerned with. What’s more, they seem institutionally biased towards extroverts.</p>

<p>I will grant, though, that I’ve seen plenty of occasions where somebody has been rude or anti-social with a device in hand. But they’re rude because they’re violating social norms and expectations, not because those specific norms and expectations are fixed and unchanging. To the extent that gadgets affect our conversations, communities need to evaluate their own experiences, and come to their own conclusions. At South by Southwest this year, for example, I was very comfortable using my phones at meals or in conversations, because that was the community norm there. Turkle’s model doesn’t seem to account for that.</p>

<p>She does get close though, with the suggestion that certain physical spaces or times are gadget-free. I like that suggestion, even if I disagree with the reasoning that drives it. Coming up with a smart way to manage our relationships so that people don’t feel neglected doesn’t require throwing away the smartphone, it just requires being sensitive and respectful to what people expect, gadgets or otherwise.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cell phones" /><category term="conversation" /><category term="extrovert" /><category term="gadgets" /><category term="introvert" /><category term="ny times" /><category term="sherry turkle" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Every once in a while, my Iron Blogger group decides to take on a common topic. At our meet-up this week, a handful of us agreed to take on last week’s Sherry Turkle op-ed in the New York Times. It’s called “The Flight from Conversation,” and it seems to cover some of the same territory as her book “Alone Together”: namely, that we’re allowing gadgets to get in the way of interpersonal communication, favoring “sips” of online contact over a “big gulp of real conversation.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Voluntary obsolescence: checking out of the upgrade cycle</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/voluntary-obsolescence-checking-out-of-the-upgrade-cycle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voluntary obsolescence: checking out of the upgrade cycle" /><published>2012-01-16T01:43:37-05:00</published><updated>2012-01-16T01:43:37-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/voluntary-obsolescence-checking-out-of-the-upgrade-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/voluntary-obsolescence-checking-out-of-the-upgrade-cycle/"><![CDATA[<p>This week I purchased a new cell phone. I’ve been using my current phone, an HTC Desire Z (dubbed the G2 by T-Mobile in the US), for a little over a year and it’s time for an upgrade.</p>

<p>Or maybe it’s a sidegrade. Instead of buying the newest model on the market (or waiting for one of the half a million or so introduced at CES this month) I re-bought the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nexus_One">Nexus One</a>, a phone released almost two years ago.</p>

<p>I bought my first Nexus One directly from Google when it came out, and it quickly became my all-time favorite phone. The hardware fits me perfectly — just the right weight, great screen and buttons. It’s had two follow-ups in the Nexus S and the Galaxy Nexus, but neither one has struck me the same way. Because of its background, as the first “Google Experience” phone, it fell into the hands of a lot of able hackers, and so has great community support and quick releases for the <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.com/">CyanogenMod</a> and <a href="http://www.whispersys.com/">Whisper Systems</a> software I like to use.</p>

<p>When that Nexus One was stolen in November 2010, I thought I’d appreciate the upgrade. But while the phone I got featured some souped-up specs and an upgraded OS, I just didn’t like the experience as much.</p>

<p>So for now, I’ve chosen to check out of the upgrade cycle and stick with a device that I know works for me. It’s tempting to think I’ll be out of some loop, but the truth is, the hardware I need for my phone is not that greatly different from what I needed two years ago.</p>

<p>Keeping off of the high-end upgrade cycle — because really, having the shiniest phone in your pocket is not a one-time choice, but a commitment to regular upgrades — is cheaper, less disappointing, and less likely to contribute to a mountain of stuff in my house that is just too expensive to throw away. Much better, if you know what works, to stick with it.</p>

<p>Of course, there are other approaches. Lore Sjöberg, a writer for Wired, wrote about <a href="http://www.wired.com/underwire/2009/10/alt-text-cult/">founding the Cult of the Somewhat Delayed</a> a few years back. His cult would consist of people who kept on top of the latest advances in technology and culture, but with a two-year offset. This month, devotees would be checking out the movies, news, and gadgets from January 2010, which makes my new phone a crazy device from the future.</p>

<p>Those not ready to take the two-year plunge might check out <a href="http://lastyearsmodel.org/">Last Year’s Model</a>, a project to get people to hold on to their devices a little longer. They advertise their MySpace page as a way to keep up with the project, which makes me think it’s either a bit out of date, or they’re very committed to the cause.</p>

<p>In any case, I’m happy to live at a time where the progress we can achieve in two years is enough to give the feeling of obsolescence. But I’m also happy to know that I’m not really out of the loop if I decide to skip the upgrade.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="android" /><category term="cell phones" /><category term="gadgets" /><category term="gear" /><category term="nexus one" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This week I purchased a new cell phone. I’ve been using my current phone, an HTC Desire Z (dubbed the G2 by T-Mobile in the US), for a little over a year and it’s time for an upgrade.]]></summary></entry></feed>