<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/journalism.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:04:09-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/journalism.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Archiving threatened outlets for the Freedom of the Press Foundation</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2018/03/archiving-threatened-outlets-for-the-freedom-of-the-press-foundation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Archiving threatened outlets for the Freedom of the Press Foundation" /><published>2018-03-12T23:07:24-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-12T23:07:24-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2018/03/archiving-threatened-outlets-for-the-freedom-of-the-press-foundation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2018/03/archiving-threatened-outlets-for-the-freedom-of-the-press-foundation/"><![CDATA[<p>A little over a month ago, I launched one of the Special Projects I’ve been working on at my new job at the <a href="https://freedom.press">Freedom of the Press Foundation</a>. The <a href="https://archive-it.org/collections/9790">Threatened Outlets collection at Archive-It</a> aims to capture the archives of news sites that we deem vulnerable to “the billionaire problem,” wherein wealthy individuals or organizations can eliminate unflattering coverage through litigation or by purchasing media companies altogether. From <a href="https://freedom.press/news/archiving-alternative-press-threatened-wealthy-buyers/">the launch announcement</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Those efforts help individual journalists. But another important thing we can do to reduce the effectiveness of this kind of attack on press freedom is to commit ourselves to the wholesale preservation of threatened sites.</p>

  <p>In this case, we seek to reduce the “upside” for wealthy individuals and organizations who would eliminate embarrassing or unflattering coverage by purchasing outlets outright. In other words, we hope that sites that can’t simply be made to disappear will show some immunity to the billionaire problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To my surprise and delight, our launch received some nice and encouraging coverage, in <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/gawker-archives-freedom-of-press-foundation-toast-la-weekly/">WIRED</a>, <a href="https://beta.techcrunch.com/2018/02/01/freedom-of-the-press-foundation-will-preserve-gawkers-archives/">TechCrunch</a>, <a href="https://thenextweb.com/insider/2018/01/31/meet-archivists-saving-alt-news-sites-permanent-deletion/">The Next Web</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/01/business/media/gawker-archives-press-freedom.html">The New York Times</a>, and others. Sometimes when you’ve got your head down on something that feels like a niche topic, it’s nice to come up for air and realize that the general public is interested, too.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="archives" /><category term="freedom of the press foundation" /><category term="gawker" /><category term="internet archive" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A little over a month ago, I launched one of the Special Projects I’ve been working on at my new job at the Freedom of the Press Foundation. The Threatened Outlets collection at Archive-It aims to capture the archives of news sites that we deem vulnerable to “the billionaire problem,” wherein wealthy individuals or organizations can eliminate unflattering coverage through litigation or by purchasing media companies altogether. From the launch announcement:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interminable copyrights and the (future) history of journalism</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/11/interminable-copyrights-and-the-future-history-of-journalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interminable copyrights and the (future) history of journalism" /><published>2015-11-08T23:53:06-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-08T23:53:06-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/11/interminable-copyrights-and-the-future-history-of-journalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/11/interminable-copyrights-and-the-future-history-of-journalism/"><![CDATA[<p>Over on Techdirt, I wrote a <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20151102/16255832697/copyright-terms-how-historical-journalism-is-disappearing.shtml">short piece about how uncertainty surrounding ridiculously long copyright terms</a> is likely keeping newspapers from the 1920s onward out of major archives. We’re very likely in the midst of a sea change in journalism, but future generations may not be able to study what we’re producing and exploring as likely business shifts make the copyright question even thornier. From the article:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the world of media journalism, we talk a lot about the future. But we can’t have a coherent conversation about that without thinking about the past and the present. And those thoughts, in turn, rely on access to the history that we’ve allowed to be locked up under effectively unlimited copyright restrictions or as orphan works.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Per usual, the comments over at Techdirt, too, have been lively.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="newspapers" /><category term="techdirt" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over on Techdirt, I wrote a short piece about how uncertainty surrounding ridiculously long copyright terms is likely keeping newspapers from the 1920s onward out of major archives. We’re very likely in the midst of a sea change in journalism, but future generations may not be able to study what we’re producing and exploring as likely business shifts make the copyright question even thornier. From the article:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic crypto errors and no public review at the Washington Post</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/basic-crypto-errors-and-no-public-review-at-the-washington-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic crypto errors and no public review at the Washington Post" /><published>2015-07-20T01:25:27-04:00</published><updated>2015-07-20T01:25:27-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/basic-crypto-errors-and-no-public-review-at-the-washington-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/basic-crypto-errors-and-no-public-review-at-the-washington-post/"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>Washington Post</em> doubled down this weekend on <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/putting-the-digital-keys-to-unlock-data-out-of-reach-of-authorities/2015/07/18/d6aa7970-2beb-11e5-a250-42bd812efc09_story.html">its ridiculous argument for new encryption that uses a “Golden Key”</a> available only to law enforcement under a court order. This proposal has a few weaknesses; perhaps chief among them is that it is literally impossible.</p>

<p>Given that putative authorities like FBI Director James Comey are willing to ignore the reality of how cryptography works, it’s weird but understandable that the Washington Post could basically disregard the feedback from experts about the same. Still, to see the editorial board of such a major outlet to tell the nerds to <a href="https://twitter.com/bdbreedlove/status/622916962914537472">get back to double-checking how math works</a> is frustrating.</p>

<p>Compounding that frustration is the fact that the <em>Washington Post</em> has basically no public escalation track for review. The <em>Post</em>‘s <em>reporting</em> on cryptography issues can be very good, but when the editorial board makes serious factual mistakes, they go unchallenged.</p>

<p>The <em>New York Times</em> has Public Editor Margaret Sullivan, who takes feedback from readers and says when the paper has erred. That’s not enough in itself—that the <em>Times</em> makes <a href="https://twitter.com/bluechoochoo/status/622985405479170048">the same kinds of mistakes over and over</a> is a pretty good indicator of its course correction ability—but it <em>feels</em> better than having no recourse. It also helps to defuse arguments from people (like Comey himself) who would cite the editorial approvingly if the paper’s own oversight has found problems with it.</p>

<p>The <em>Post</em> had an ombudsman until 2013, when they discontinued the role—<a href="http://mediamatters.org/blog/2013/02/12/former-washington-post-ombudsmen-cutting-positi/192630">over protests from former ombudsmen</a>. They replaced it with a “reader representative,” who was a Post employee. The <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/omblog/post/doug-feaver-named-the-washington-posts-first-reader-representative/2013/03/07/83254b7a-8744-11e2-999e-5f8e0410cb9d_blog.html">first person to hold the role was Doug Feaver</a>, after he’d retired from an editorial role with 37 years at the paper. He held the reader rep spot for less than a year, when he left and was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/pr/wp/2014/02/20/alison-coliagnese-to-become-reader-representative/">replaced by Alison Coglianese</a>.</p>

<p>Doug Feaver was supposed to hold the paper accountable, but he did little of that. Per <a href="http://mediamatters.org/blog/2014/01/08/exclusive-washington-post-reader-representative/197483">this Media Matters breakdown</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Of his 28 blog posts since April 5, 2013, 26 consisted simply of Feaver aggregating reader comments from Post articles and columns without additional commentary. The other two consisted of a piece declaring the paper free of any conflict of interest regarding the Post’s Jerusalem correspondent and Feaver’s initial post chronicling the initial inquiries he had received in his position (“the biggest issue to come to my attention was the disappearing print button on the article pages of washingtonpost.com”).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As far as I can tell, Coglianese only wrote one post as reader rep, about the stock and mutual fund listings accidentally being <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ask-the-post/wp/2014/02/26/sunday-stock-tables-gone-for-the-moment-but-not-forgotten/">left out of the Sunday Business section one week</a>. Searching her name on the site produces nothing more recent than that, and no announcements that the reader rep role had been discontinued. It just faded away.</p>

<p>So as it stands, there’s no public representative at the paper noting that the <em>Post</em> continues to propose a physical impossibility in its editorial pages. Unfortunately, it’s hard to imagine the conversation progressing intelligently while it continues to do so.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="crypto" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="washington post" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Washington Post doubled down this weekend on its ridiculous argument for new encryption that uses a “Golden Key” available only to law enforcement under a court order. This proposal has a few weaknesses; perhaps chief among them is that it is literally impossible.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Did the Internet just fall for a massive drone hoax?</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did the Internet just fall for a massive drone hoax?" /><published>2013-02-11T04:40:12-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-11T04:40:12-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/did-the-internet-just-fall-for-a-massive-drone-hoax/"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been on Twitter today, you’ve probably seen it promoted as fact that surveillance drones have been sent into operation over Los Angeles as part of the multi-state manhunt for former cop Christopher Dorner alleged to be on a killing spree. The <a href="http://now.msn.com/christopher-dorner-is-first-drone-target-on-us-soil">worst articles imply</a> that the drones are armed and the government has authorized Dorner’s death, using language that’s ambiguous to the point of being deceptive, which is almost certainly untrue. But a closer look at the articles raises another concern: all of the reports are citing a single article which is flawed at best, and at worst may even be fabricated. Are the police using a drone at all?</p>

<p>Sunday Morning, the <a href="http://www.express.co.uk/news/world/376732/Man-hunt-for-ex-soldier-who-shot-police-chief-s-daughter-and-killed-policeman">UK publication “Express” published an article about the manhunt</a>, and provided its drone claims, with its main claim coming from an anonymous source within the Los Angeles police department. The relevant facts presented in the article are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Dorner has become the first human target for remotely-controlled airborne drones on US soil.”</li>
  <li>“A senior police source said: ‘The thermal imaging cameras the drones use may be our only hope of finding him. On the ground, it’s like looking for a needle in a haystack.’”</li>
  <li>Riverside PD Chief Sergio Diaz was asked directly about drones, and responded “We are using all the tools at our disposal.”</li>
  <li>Customs and Border Patrol spokesman Ralph DeSio confirmed the drone use, and provided the quote: “This agency has been at the forefront of domestic use of drones by law enforcement. That’s all I can say at the moment.”</li>
</ul>

<p>These claims have been cited in dozens or hundreds of subsequent articles, <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5983175/report-ex+cop-christopher-dorner-is-now-a-target-for-drones">beginning with Gizmodo</a>. But each of these claims is suspect, and taken collectively I believe they are false. Taking a look at each:</p>

<h2 id="the-first-human-target">“The first human target”</h2>

<p>That Dorner would be the first human target for drone surveillance on US soil is true only if you take a very particular, and unusual, read on some of the words. If there are drones tracking him, he is at least the second case on US soil, after <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/2011/dec/10/nation/la-na-drone-arrest-20111211">a 2011 arrest based on drone evidence in North Dakota</a>. In that case, as is alleged in this case, the drones were Customs and Border Protection MQ-9 “Reaper” drones (a model previously known as “Predator B”). In that case, the suspects’ general location was known, and the drone was used to determine their specific location on a single property, and whether they were armed or not. If that makes them ineligible to be the “first human target[s] for remotely-controlled airborne drones on US soil”, it’s not clear how.</p>

<h2 id="senior-police-source-on-thermal-imaging">Senior police source on thermal imaging</h2>

<p>It’s not clear why this source would be attributed anonymously, or where this quote comes from. Without a name or the circumstances of its delivery, it’s difficult or impossible to verify the quote. And how did a tiny paper in the United Kingdom get such a juicy source more than 10,000 miles away in the Los Angeles police department?</p>

<h2 id="chief-sergio-diaz-using-all-the-tools-at-his-disposal">Chief Sergio Diaz “using all the tools” at his disposal</h2>

<p>If Chief Sergio Diaz said that the task force is using all the tools at its disposal to hunt down Dorning, it’s likely he said it at a press conference on Thursday morning, February 7, 2013. If so, it’s not clear why the line didn’t get more attention. An online student-run newspaper from the University of Southern California — “Neon Tommy” — <a href="http://www.neontommy.com/news/2013/02/are-drones-being-used-dorner-manhunt">attributes the quote to him in an article published on the 7th</a>. However, that article is explicitly about LAPD’s declining to state whether drones are being used — not presented as evidence that they’re in use.</p>

<p>What’s more, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pAUWjjXuuCo">this video from the press conference</a> does not appear to include that question or response, and despite the obvious newsworthiness of such a quote, it doesn’t show up in other publications.</p>

<h2 id="cbp-confirmation-and-spokesman-quote">CBP confirmation and spokesman quote</h2>

<p>If CBP spokesman Ralph DeSio did confirm drone usage, it’s not clear how or where he did so. <a href="http://www.neontommy.com/news/2013/02/are-drones-being-used-dorner-manhunt">The same Neon Tommy article mentioned above</a> cites Ralph DeSio as the source for information about where CPB drones are deployed. Curiously, the very next quote in that article is identical to what Express alleged DeSio to have said: “The agency has been on the forefront of domestic use of drones by law enforcement.” However, that quote is attributed — and linked — to <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/11/19/us-border-drones-deal-wit_n_2159255.html">an article by the investigative reporting group California Watch</a>. Did a hasty read of the Neon Tommy article lead to a bad attribution in the Express? Unfortunately, the addition of the next sentence, “That’s all I can say at the moment” gives the impression of unclean hands.</p>

<p>Yes, it’s possible that Express contacted Ralph DeSio over the weekend, got the confirmation, and then a quote from him that is out-of-character for the organization and plagiarized from a California Watch piece. But that seems unlikely.</p>

<h2 id="sorting-out-loose-ends">Sorting out loose ends</h2>

<p>In a rush to clarify that CPB drones aren’t in fact armed, and teasing out information on whether the drones in question were, say, launched from the <a href="http://www.163rw.ang.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123309053">a nearby Air Force Base that has recently tested search-and-rescue flights</a>, there are some deeper unanswered questions.</p>

<p>The story is plausible. <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/2012/aug/05/nation/la-na-drones-testing-20120805">The Department of Homeland Security (CPB’s parent agency) does loan out drones to police agencies</a>, and they’ve kept the terms of such deals almost completely secret. <a href="https://www.eff.org/press/releases/eff-demands-answers-about-predator-drone-flights-us">EFF is currently suing DHS to find more information about that program</a>. But in this case, the factual support isn’t there.</p>

<p>Whether or not these drones are being used in this manhunt, and whether or not they’re armed (they’re not), there is real cause for concern. A secret aerial surveillance program wherein federal agencies loan military technology to local police forces raises serious questions and we should demand to know more. The expansion of warrantless surveillance to unarmed vehicles with capabilities that exceed any helicopter or light plane currently in operation is also a problem. The general militarization of police is well-documented and alarming, as is the shift in rhetoric and actions in the Dorner case from capture-and-try to capture-and-kill.</p>

<p>But we do a disservice to our efforts at resolving these important issues when we resort to untruths or conspiracy theories.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="christopher dorner" /><category term="drones" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="los angeles" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you’ve been on Twitter today, you’ve probably seen it promoted as fact that surveillance drones have been sent into operation over Los Angeles as part of the multi-state manhunt for former cop Christopher Dorner alleged to be on a killing spree. The worst articles imply that the drones are armed and the government has authorized Dorner’s death, using language that’s ambiguous to the point of being deceptive, which is almost certainly untrue. But a closer look at the articles raises another concern: all of the reports are citing a single article which is flawed at best, and at worst may even be fabricated. Are the police using a drone at all?]]></summary></entry></feed>