<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/meta.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:04:09-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/meta.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Hosting change</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/07/hosting-change/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hosting change" /><published>2017-07-28T17:54:36-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-28T17:54:36-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/07/hosting-change</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/07/hosting-change/"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick meta note: I’ve moved this site to a new hosting situation, but there shouldn’t be any disruption to its availability. I’ll probably also be looking into different CMS options while I’m here at Recurse Center.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="meta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Just a quick meta note: I’ve moved this site to a new hosting situation, but there shouldn’t be any disruption to its availability. I’ll probably also be looking into different CMS options while I’m here at Recurse Center.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New plugin: WP Emphasis</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/new-plugin-wp-emphasis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New plugin: WP Emphasis" /><published>2012-11-25T03:39:50-05:00</published><updated>2012-11-25T03:39:50-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/new-plugin-wp-emphasis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/new-plugin-wp-emphasis/"><![CDATA[<p>Advanced users of the New York Times may know about the “two-shift click” trick on that website: hit the shift button twice on any article page, and you then have the option to link to specific paragraphs or even highlight arbitrary sentences throughout the article, in a way that’s stored in the URL so you can send it around. It’s a shame it’s not more widely known — it’s pretty amazing.</p>

<p>Anyway, it works through <a href="http://open.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/01/11/emphasis-update-and-source/">a little Javascript plug-in called Emphasis</a>, developed in-house at the Times and <a href="https://github.com/NYTimes/Emphasis">released open-source</a> ((with no obvious license, alas)). I poked around a little bit and found that a developer named Ben Balter has released <a href="https://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wp-emphasis/">a WordPress plugin to implement Emphasis on blogs</a>, and so I decided to give it a spin. Now you can link to any paragraph and highlight any sentence in any post: just hit shift twice and click the pilcrow or the sentence and the URL bar will update.</p>

<p>Every site in the world should provide at least anchor links to different paragraphs, and Emphasis seems like a pretty good method for doing it. For now I just hope it’s helpful, but in the future I’d love to see more people using it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="javascript" /><category term="meta" /><category term="new york times" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Advanced users of the New York Times may know about the “two-shift click” trick on that website: hit the shift button twice on any article page, and you then have the option to link to specific paragraphs or even highlight arbitrary sentences throughout the article, in a way that’s stored in the URL so you can send it around. It’s a shame it’s not more widely known — it’s pretty amazing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Site redesign</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/site-redesign/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Site redesign" /><published>2012-05-06T20:22:18-04:00</published><updated>2012-05-06T20:22:18-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/site-redesign</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/site-redesign/"><![CDATA[<p>If you fall into the intersection of people who have looked at this website before yesterday and people who are looking at it after today, you may notice that I’ve given it a bit of a spitshine.</p>

<p>It’s still on WordPress, but in place of the venerable <a href="http://powazek.com/depo-skinny">DePo Skinny</a> theme, it’s now using a custom theme that I built on top of <a href="http://themeshaper.com/thematic/">the Thematic framework</a>. The most notable differences are that I’ve pushed all of the margins outward, made all the text bigger, and pulled the information from the bottom up to a new sidebar. My 1-column days are over.</p>

<p>Also, I’ve used <a href="http://favoritecolor.co/007FFF">my favorite color</a> as the hover for all of the links.</p>

<p>I had made and modified WordPress themes before, but I was surprised to discover how long it has been. I’d never, for example, used a “<a href="https://codex.wordpress.org/Child_Themes">Child Theme</a>,” which appear to have been state-of-the-art since, like, 2009. There’s a bit of a conceptual learning curve, but using one you can develop a whole theme basically only using CSS with only touches of basically copy-and-paste PHP. In addition to <a href="https://codex.wordpress.org/Child_Themes">the WordPress Codex entry</a>, I found <a href="http://themeshaper.com/modify-wordpress-themes/">the ThemeShaper tutorial</a> really helpful.</p>

<p>One note about responsive design: I don’t have it. I was conflicted about that, and the next redesign may support it, but I wanted to get something finished and it seems like smartphones do pretty well with reflowing the content.</p>

<p>I’ll probably work out some of the kinks over the next couple of days, but if you find something that seems unusual, please let me know.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="design" /><category term="meta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you fall into the intersection of people who have looked at this website before yesterday and people who are looking at it after today, you may notice that I’ve given it a bit of a spitshine.]]></summary></entry></feed>