<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/mobile.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:29:15-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/mobile.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">The crypto triple threat club</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/the-crypto-triple-threat-club/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The crypto triple threat club" /><published>2012-06-11T04:24:03-04:00</published><updated>2012-06-11T04:24:03-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/the-crypto-triple-threat-club</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/the-crypto-triple-threat-club/"><![CDATA[<p>My written one-to-one communication patterns can be grouped into three major categories: longform, synchronous shortform, and asynchronous shortform. For the most part I use email, IMs, and SMS, respectively, for those purposes.</p>

<p>Each of those technologies has its own end-to-end encryption protocol. ((In some cases, more than one. I’m just listing the ones I use.)) Email has the venerable OpenPGP protocol and <a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">the GnuPG suite of programs</a>; IM has <a href="http://www.cypherpunks.ca/otr/">OTR for Off-the-Record Messaging</a> on Pidgin and Adium on the desktop, and<a href="https://guardianproject.info/apps/gibber/">Gibberbot</a> and <a href="https://chatsecure.org/">ChatSecure</a> on mobile; and SMS has <a href="https://github.com/whispersystems/textsecure">TextSecure</a>, a free software Android SMS application that does encryption locally and over the wire.</p>

<div class="wp-caption alignright" id="attachment_728" style="width: 293px">[![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/textsecureqr.png "TextSecure QR code")](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/textsecureqr.png)My TextSecure fingreprint, as a QR code generated by the application.

</div>
<p>There’s a small but growing cadre of my friends with whom I’ve exchanged keys on all three protocols. ((Seriously, it’s growing. I added <a href="http://interi.org/">maiki</a> to the club just tonight.)) They’re the crypto triple threats. I want to build that list out further: if I’m having an end-to-end conversation with you, I’d like it to be encrypted end-to-end.</p>

<p>Some of these keys are harder than others to exchange. Email encryption is notoriously difficult to get right, while OTR is much simpler to start working with. TextSecure is a great example of the <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/03/a-modest-defense-of-qr-codes/">rare good QR code use case</a>.</p>

<p>These are communication tools, so they’re especially affected by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metcalfe%27s_law">Metcalfe’s Law</a>. That makes it even more important to get people to join the triple threat club. It also means that for each of these protocols, there are lots of people who want to help you figure it out. I’m one of those people. Let’s talk!</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cell phones" /><category term="communication" /><category term="encryption" /><category term="mobile" /><category term="qr codes" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My written one-to-one communication patterns can be grouped into three major categories: longform, synchronous shortform, and asynchronous shortform. For the most part I use email, IMs, and SMS, respectively, for those purposes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Clickwrap privacy isn’t the answer</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/02/clickwrap-privacy-isnt-the-answer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clickwrap privacy isn’t the answer" /><published>2012-02-27T03:37:16-05:00</published><updated>2012-02-27T03:37:16-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/02/clickwrap-privacy-isnt-the-answer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/02/clickwrap-privacy-isnt-the-answer/"><![CDATA[<p>Two sets of mobile app privacy stories have broken into the mainstream press this month. The first half of the month was dominated by “addressbook-gate”, where Path (and then, it turns out, <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2012/02/14/iphone-address-book/">many other iOS applications</a>) were found to be <a href="http://mclov.in/2012/02/08/path-uploads-your-entire-address-book-to-their-servers.html">uploading and storing users’ phone contact lists to their servers</a>.</p>

<p>In the firestorm that followed, many people — including <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2012/02/15/congress-apple-address-book/">some US Representatives</a> — called on Apple raise the walls of their garden and address the issue by limiting app access to the address book and notifying users when the application requests access. Apple agreed, and will be <a href="http://allthingsd.com/20120215/apple-app-access-to-contact-data-will-require-explicit-user-permission/">introducing those changes in a future version of iOS</a>.</p>

<p>So case closed. Until this last weekend, when the (London) Sunday Times reported that many popular mobile apps, including Facebook for Android, were “reading” user text messages. (Incidentally, the Sunday Times article is behind a paywall, and I haven’t seen a copy of the original article.) Extrapolating from <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2106627/Internet-firms-access-texts-emails-pictures-spying-smartphone-apps.html">other articles covering the Times “scoop”</a>, it looks like the story is likely about the permissions apps typically request during the installation process.</p>

<p>Apps that overreach in their requested permissions are a bad thing, but they’re <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704368004576027751867039730.html">not new</a>, and they’re not a smoking gun: developers may have legitimate and non-obvious reasons for requesting certain permissions, and they may require them for reasons that aren’t immediately clear to the end user. Facebook, for its part, <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/blog/btl/facebook-flickr-others-accused-of-reading-text-messages/70237">denied</a> “reading of user text messages” and explained that the app requires SMS read/write to test an as-yet-unreleased feature.</p>

<p>These two stories follow different arcs, but the second one certainly seems to complicate the first. The clickwrap privacy policy that Apple agreed to require is exactly the sort of permission screen that has been ignored so consistently that a major newspaper decided to publish it as a scoop.</p>

<p>Raising the garden walls is too easy an answer to a hard question. The response to these two privacy stories makes clear that people want their privacy to be respected, which requires effort and resources on the part of the developer. How do we convince developers that those expenses are worth the cost <em>before</em> a PR fiasco about their privacy practices? I don’t know what the solution is, but it’s not expanding clickwrap privacy policies.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="android" /><category term="facebook" /><category term="ios" /><category term="mobile" /><category term="privacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two sets of mobile app privacy stories have broken into the mainstream press this month. The first half of the month was dominated by “addressbook-gate”, where Path (and then, it turns out, many other iOS applications) were found to be uploading and storing users’ phone contact lists to their servers.]]></summary></entry></feed>