<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/money.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T22:01:08-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/money.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Square’s security anti-patterns</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/10/squares-security-anti-patterns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Square’s security anti-patterns" /><published>2012-10-08T03:38:13-04:00</published><updated>2012-10-08T03:38:13-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/10/squares-security-anti-patterns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/10/squares-security-anti-patterns/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://squareup.com/">Square</a> dongles really truly make processing credit cards not just easier, but possible for all sorts of groups that didn’t have access before: I’ve bought from bands selling merchandise, taxi drivers, food cart operators, and more. I’m worried, though, that Square also makes credit card fraud easier by teaching credit card users security <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-pattern">anti-patterns</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/square-reader.jpg"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/square-reader.jpg" alt="" title="Square reader on an iPad" /></a></p>

<p>In practice, using a Square reader is pretty similar to using any other credit card reader. At the money part of the transaction, you hand your card to the vendor or swipe it yourself through a little dongle hooked up to the headphone jack of an iOS or Android device. Then you enter your email, if you want a receipt sent to you, and sign with your finger on the screen.</p>

<p>That’s the standard description. But it could also be described as handing your credit card to a stranger with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Credit_card_fraud#Skimming">skimmer</a>, and then giving him your signature. That’s what makes it an anti-pattern: it has become commonly used, but is counter-productive to security efforts.</p>

<p>In the overwhelming majority of cases, both parties are honest, and nothing goes wrong. But it’s easy to imagine a few ways it could go wrong. For one thing, if the vendor is dishonest, he could intentionally record the data and use it or sell it later. That’s how a standard skimmer works, and the same problem exists every time you hand your card to the waiter at a restaurant.</p>

<p>Even if both parties are honest though, they are trusting the integrity of the software. I haven’t heard of it yet, but again it’s not too hard to imagine malware that attacks exploits in, say, Android or iOS themselves, and surreptitiously records and sends the card data to the attacker. Such malware could target a wide swath of devices and transactions, and would be more difficult to pinpoint as the source of the data leak.</p>

<p>Unlike the first scenario, this one is exacerbated in the Square era. Previously, <a href="https://www.networkworld.com/news/2011/030311-cybercriminals-targeting-point-of-sale.html?page=1">malware targeting point-of-sale devices had to be very specialized</a>. Now, though, point-of-sale devices are general purpose computers and vulnerable to commonly known exploits. And in many scenarios, they’re used for other purposes, too, exposing them to more attack vectors.</p>

<p>Really, though, the problem here is not with Square, but with the structure of credit card security. Our card numbers are a secret, and the only information required to carry out many transactions, but we also entrust them with every stranger we make a payment to.</p>

<p>We used to address this issue by an ad hoc security-by-point-of-sale system. If somebody had an official point-of-sale system, our intuition said they were trustworthy, and that was pretty robust. But it’s failing the same way that, say, <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2007/10/security_by_let.html">security-by-letterhead</a> has failed. Technology has made attacks we’ve dismissed as prohibitively difficult much easier, and we need to change our behavior to reflect that.</p>

<hr />

<p>photo: <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/cdharrison/4991885743/in/photostream/">The infamous Square card reader</a>. used under <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en">CC BY</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="money" /><category term="payment" /><category term="security" /><category term="square" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Square dongles really truly make processing credit cards not just easier, but possible for all sorts of groups that didn’t have access before: I’ve bought from bands selling merchandise, taxi drivers, food cart operators, and more. I’m worried, though, that Square also makes credit card fraud easier by teaching credit card users security anti-patterns.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Token gestures</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/03/token-gestures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Token gestures" /><published>2012-03-05T03:52:42-05:00</published><updated>2012-03-05T03:52:42-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/03/token-gestures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/03/token-gestures/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been thinking a lot about two different kinds of tokens lately. One is a fare token, which I’ve been thinking about as it relates to public transit and locational privacy. Another is a currency token, which has come up in the last few weeks as I’m reading <cite>Debt</cite> by David Graeber. Obviously there’s some overlap there, but thinking about the ways in which they differ has been really interesting, and there’s enough weird history of each to fill a Thomas Pynchon novel.</p>

<p>Fare tokens are intriguing as artifacts of a transit system, which are pretty much always interesting to me. Like system maps, which I’ve also <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2010/12/metro-maps-kindle-screensaver/">thought about a bit</a>, fare tokens are necessarily unique to one place and provide a physical history of that system’s character and aesthetic. They’re also ephemeral, anonymous, and completely commoditized. There’s some sort of paradox there: something inherently interesting about objects that are so non-descript. (Rick Prelinger put it well in a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/04/technology/internet-archives-repository-collects-thousands-of-books.html?pagewanted=all">story in the New York Times this weekend</a>: “As time passes, the works we tried to junk often prove more interesting than the ones we chose to save.”)</p>

<p>As a privacy-preserving technology, fare tokens are great. Entrance into a public transit system should be a question of authorization: are you permitted to do what you’re trying to do? The answer to that should only be contingent on whether or not you’ve paid the fare, which is a piece of data the token can communicate just fine. Too often, though, fare systems first ask who you are. Swiping (or tapping) a fare card gives the system an identifier, which it runs against a database to see whether that identifier is tied to a paid fare. There are tempting reasons to go with the latter scheme — a lost card can be replaced because the value is recorded, and the system can gather and use data about riding patterns in order to target improvements — but there’s a trade-off with rider privacy.</p>

<p>(To my mind, the trade-off is akin to that between database loyalty programs, like Target’s <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/19/magazine/shopping-habits.html?pagewanted=all">recently documented “Guest ID” system</a> and punch-card loyalty programs. Both provide rewards to return customers, but one is more privacy-friendly and generates less monetizable data.)</p>

<p>Of course, another issue with letting customers carry around the authorization information in their own token is that it depends on the issuer’s ability to reliably generate and verify their own tokens. One interesting anecdote I found out about this weekend was the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City_Subway#Token_War_with_Connecticut">New York City “Token War”</a> with Connecticut. Tokens for Connecticut Turnpike tolls were the same size and shape as NYC subway fares but cost much less, which led to Connecticut Turnpike tokens ending up in NYCTA collection boxes. Connecticut promised to change the shape of their tokens, but failed to do so for years. I’m not sure how it ended: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City_Subway#cite_note-token_war-63">one NY Times article</a> cited on the issue’s Wikipedia page but unavailable online suggests it happened when Connecticut discontinued their toll charges and paid the NYCTA for all the collected tokens; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/01/04/opinion/no-need-for-a-new-token-war.html">another article available online</a> says it ended when the NYCTA rewired their turnstiles.</p>

<p>On the other hand, you’ve got currency tokens, which make up the field of “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exonumia">exonumia</a>“. These tokens are like coins, but issued by somebody other than the government. Sometimes these tokens really take off, as in the case of the Strachan and Co Trade Tokens that were <a href="http://www.tokencoins.com/main.htm">South Africa’s first circulating indigenous currency</a>. ((It’s not often that Wikipedia disappoints, but I can’t find any real information there about these coins. Instead, there’s a charmingly Web 1.0 site, which I really like.))</p>

<p>In the US, there were a series of “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hard_times_token">hard-times tokens</a>” which circulated as currency between about 1833 and 1843, and were only officially outlawed in 1857. One of the most prominent examples was the endearingly named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feuchtwanger_Cent">Feuchtwanger cent</a>, which is now pretty collectible by exonumismatists. Lewis Feuchtwanger’s story is interesting for his persistence in minting these coins and his attempts to get them recognized officially. His appeals to Congress give the story a <cite>Mr. Smith Goes to Washington</cite> vibe — a film whose plot also turns on a coin, albeit a tossed one.</p>

<p>In any case, the parallels between these hard-times tokens and cryptocurrencies like bitcoin seem straightforward, but they’re not ones I’ve seen pointed out elsewhere. Bitcoin’s got <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/09/07/golden-cyberfetters/">some</a> <a href="http://www.technologyreview.com/computing/38392/">problems</a>, but supporters who’ve read <cite>Cryptonomicon</cite> are quick to point out the benefits: things like anonymous transactions, the ground-up minting and lack of reliance on a centralized nation-state, and the security of the currency against counterfeiting. These are laudable goals, and maybe last delivered on in the hard times era. Lewis Feuchtwanger would be proud.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="location" /><category term="money" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="public transit" /><category term="tokens" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been thinking a lot about two different kinds of tokens lately. One is a fare token, which I’ve been thinking about as it relates to public transit and locational privacy. Another is a currency token, which has come up in the last few weeks as I’m reading Debt by David Graeber. Obviously there’s some overlap there, but thinking about the ways in which they differ has been really interesting, and there’s enough weird history of each to fill a Thomas Pynchon novel.]]></summary></entry></feed>