<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/mpaa.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:04:09-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/mpaa.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Trigger warnings and movie ratings</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/08/trigger-warnings-movie-ratings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trigger warnings and movie ratings" /><published>2016-08-31T21:26:04-04:00</published><updated>2016-08-31T21:26:04-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/08/trigger-warnings-movie-ratings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/08/trigger-warnings-movie-ratings/"><![CDATA[<p>In an effort to explain trigger warnings and safe spaces to people who clearly don’t understand them—like the <a href="https://reason.com/blog/2016/08/31/critics-of-u-chicago-say-trigger-warning">University of Chicago’s dean of students</a>—a few folks have compared them to the movie ratings and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trailer_(promotion)#MPAA_rating_cards_for_theatrical_trailers">trailer cards</a> that list potentially offensive material. It’s a useful analogy, but not likely to be much comfort for people concerned about trigger warnings.</p>

<p>In the US, the movie and trailer ratings system is operated by the Motion Picture Association of America, a trade organization. The actual process by which they set and deliver those ratings has long been somewhat secretive, but <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0493459/">the documentary “This Film Is Not Yet Rated”</a> does an impressive job of uncovering and exploring those facts. Unfortunately, it’s not just a benign means of presenting more information so that viewers can be better informed.</p>

<p>The documentary shows filmmakers describing instances where the movie raters appear to be biased against non-heternormative sexual content, and against women’s sexuality. Independent filmmakers, too, report that they get less detailed notes about <em>why</em> their films were rated a certain way.</p>

<p>If these ratings were just used for informing viewers, that might be alright; viewers could learn about the MPAA’s bias and discount certain ratings accordingly. But there’s a cascading effect: theaters refuse to show movies with certain ratings, or refuse entry to people below a certain age. (Sometimes, admirably, <a href="https://boingboing.net/2014/12/09/nyc-theater-overrules-mpaa-rat.html">they buck that trend</a>.) The same is true for other media—music and video game retailers make stocking and selling decisions based on these ratings from industry groups.</p>

<p>Good instructors should have empathy for their students, and that includes giving a fair warning when upsetting (or triggering) material is likely to be discussed. Some people worry that <a href="https://reason.com/blog/2016/08/31/critics-of-u-chicago-say-trigger-warning">such a suggestion will be mandated</a>, or that those warnings will lead to relevant but controversial content being avoided or even banned from the classroom. It’s absolutely possible to have the former without the latter, but movie ratings are not a great example of that in practice.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="movie ratings" /><category term="mpaa" /><category term="this film is not yet rated" /><category term="trigger warnings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In an effort to explain trigger warnings and safe spaces to people who clearly don’t understand them—like the University of Chicago’s dean of students—a few folks have compared them to the movie ratings and trailer cards that list potentially offensive material. It’s a useful analogy, but not likely to be much comfort for people concerned about trigger warnings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My cousin Chris</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/06/my-cousin-chris/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My cousin Chris" /><published>2014-06-16T01:40:45-04:00</published><updated>2014-06-16T01:40:45-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/06/my-cousin-chris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/06/my-cousin-chris/"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend my dad and I dug through the family tree and determined that former senator and current MPAA chief Chris Dodd is his third cousin—and so my third cousin once removed. To be precise: my great-great-great-grandfather Michael Higgins is Chris Dodd’s great-great-grandfather.</p>

<div class="wp-caption alignright" id="attachment_1370" style="width: 293px">![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/Bl1-BO2IQAAVIFV.jpg)The Senator and I.

</div>
<p>Michael Higgins was born in Knockanore, County Waterford, Ireland in 1814, and had some four or five children with his wife Margaret Geary. Between about 1865 and 1870, the couple and their children (separately) sailed for the US and settled in Pawcatuck, Connecticut.</p>

<p>One of their sons, Michael C. Higgins, married Mary Ann Burke in Connecticut. They had a son, C. Leo Higgins, who married Marie Rose Henry. Their son John Higgins was my grandfather. His eldest brother Leo died earlier this year, and there was a <a href="http://www.thewesterlysun.com/news/latestnews/3478047-129/leo-higgins-downtown-impresario-and-confidant-dies-at-93.html">nice obituary</a> in the Westerly Sun with some information about the pharmacy they ran.</p>

<p>Another of Michael Higgins’ sons, William Higgins, married twice. With his second wife, Mary McDonald, he had a daughter named Helene “Nellie” Higgins. Helene married John Murphy, and together they had a daughter Grace Murphy, who married <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_J._Dodd">Senator Thomas Dodd</a>. Chris Dodd is their son.</p>

<p>My dad had indicated before that there was some familial connection, but I didn’t expect that we’d narrow it down like this. It feels a little more concrete to know that Chris Dodd’s grandmother’s maiden name was Higgins!</p>

<p>Given how frequently our organizations views differ, especially on copyright issues, it’s surprising to know we’re related however distantly. I guess I can see the resemblance, though.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="chris dodd" /><category term="geneology" /><category term="mpaa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This weekend my dad and I dug through the family tree and determined that former senator and current MPAA chief Chris Dodd is his third cousin—and so my third cousin once removed. To be precise: my great-great-great-grandfather Michael Higgins is Chris Dodd’s great-great-grandfather.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IP above all else</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/ip-above-all-else/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IP above all else" /><published>2012-05-24T03:38:02-04:00</published><updated>2012-05-24T03:38:02-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/ip-above-all-else</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/ip-above-all-else/"><![CDATA[<p>It can be hard to point a finger at exactly what is so offensive about the way the copyright lobby pushes its agenda. The rhetoric is sometimes charged, but I don’t think the problem lies in the moral foundation of intellectual monopolies (although some people certainly object to them on <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20100519/0404029486.shtml">ethical grounds</a>). I also don’t think it’s a fundamental business problem. Some have argued that <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120503/14160618768/nobody-cares-about-fixed-costs-your-book-movie-whatever.shtml">nobody cares about content creators’ fixed costs</a>, and that their fixation on that number is misguided, but I think that premise falls apart a bit at the margins: when fans feel a connection to a creator, they <em>do</em> care about her fixed costs, and want to help her make the record or book or film.</p>

<p>No, the ethical and economic basis of copyright isn’t inherently so offensive. It’s kind of like any other business, at its core. As the former Warner Music CTO recently put it, recorded music (for example) isn’t <a href="https://twitter.com/ethank/status/203525014300004353">diamonds mined from a secret mythical land</a> — it’s just a thing that some people make and that other people — fans — enjoy. As in nearly any other business, those fans are willing to support the producer if they feel a human connection to her. Copyright is one model we’ve developed to facilitate that support, and though it’s wearing a bit at the edges, it’s not fundamentally evil or insane.</p>

<p>The problem is the mindset of “IP above all else” that seems to pervade every statement and action that the copyright and patent lobbies take. That’s the mindset that leads to WIPO <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120404/12263218371/ip-above-all-else-wipo-defies-un-sanctions-to-give-computers-to-north-korea.shtml">defying UN sanctions, shipping computers to North Korea</a> to enable it to observe international patent law. That leads to some of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/17/arts/music/17jazz.html?pagewanted=all">the world’s greatest jazz recordings to be virtually impossible to hear</a>, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/17/nyregion/ascap-asks-royalties-from-girl-scouts-and-regrets-it.html?pagewanted=all">Girl Scouts being silenced at campfires</a>, and <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/08/01/AR2007080102398.html">19-year-olds arrested at the movie theater for taking out a camera</a>. <a href="http://www.ip-watch.org/2012/05/20/india%E2%80%99s-generics-big-pharma-battle-drops-drug-prices-raises-legal-debate/">Fighting generic drugs that save lives around the world</a>, <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/04/24/us-sec-movies-idUSBRE83N15V20120424">bribery scandals over movie deals in China</a>, <a href="http://popwatch.ew.com/2012/01/23/chris-dodd-mpaa-bribery/">and even in the US</a>. Pushing for laws that even supporters admit “<a href="http://popwatch.ew.com/2012/01/23/chris-dodd-mpaa-bribery/">really did pose some risk to the Internet.</a>”</p>

<p>The list goes on and on. As much as the copyright lobby want to frame the debate around the premise of intellectual property itself, that’s really missing the point. It’s impossible to address the problems with copyright without first acknowledging its biggest supporters’ excesses at every step.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="ip" /><category term="mpaa" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It can be hard to point a finger at exactly what is so offensive about the way the copyright lobby pushes its agenda. The rhetoric is sometimes charged, but I don’t think the problem lies in the moral foundation of intellectual monopolies (although some people certainly object to them on ethical grounds). I also don’t think it’s a fundamental business problem. Some have argued that nobody cares about content creators’ fixed costs, and that their fixation on that number is misguided, but I think that premise falls apart a bit at the margins: when fans feel a connection to a creator, they do care about her fixed costs, and want to help her make the record or book or film.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Irrelevance is a far greater threat to gatekeepers than piracy — and they know it</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/02/irrelevance-is-a-far-greater-threat-to-gatekeepers-than-piracy-and-they-know-it/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Irrelevance is a far greater threat to gatekeepers than piracy — and they know it" /><published>2012-02-12T00:38:35-05:00</published><updated>2012-02-12T00:38:35-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/02/irrelevance-is-a-far-greater-threat-to-gatekeepers-than-piracy-and-they-know-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/02/irrelevance-is-a-far-greater-threat-to-gatekeepers-than-piracy-and-they-know-it/"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/01/paul-carrs-angry-nerds-is-wrong-about-everything/">I wrote about Paul Carr’s accusation of hypocrisy</a> within the tech community for opposing bad copyright legislation and then also speaking out against plagiarism. His take was wrong, but it wasn’t unusual; it’s all too common for supporters of wrongheaded copyright legislation (like SOPA, PIPA and two decades of more successful proposals) to settle on a characterization of their opponents and then cry foul when those characterizations are not consistent with reality. It’s an example of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias">confirmation bias</a>: favoring information that supports a hypothesis and discarding (or dismissing as hypocritical) information that doesn’t.</p>

<p>The problem is that it’s not very productive to assume that actions which seem internally inconsistent are taken in bad faith. It makes a lot more sense to think of your own model as incomplete, and take in the words and actions of other as feedback to inform it.</p>

<p>In that spirit, I want to dig a little deeper into the motivations of the people who support legislation for expanded copyright laws. Especially in the heat of the debate, when rhetoric is running hot, it’s too easy to assume they’re real malice or profound ignorance. But to do so <a href="http://john.jubjubs.net/2012/01/06/whats-bothering-me-about-the-sopa-discussion/">poisons the conversation</a> and makes progress less likely. Worse, it makes it difficult to predict the next move and to <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/01/will-last-weeks-blackouts-reframe-the-conversation-on-copyright-policy/">change the conversation</a>.</p>

<p>So what is it that drives the entertainment industry to promote legislation that is so offensive and anti-user it can lead to the biggest online protests in history?</p>

<p>Is it about money? The entertainment lobbyists provide plenty of stats about the money lost to “piracy”, but they know better than anybody that the movie industry is <a href="http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2011/12/13/movie-executives-see-record-profits-salaries-despite-piracy-fear-mongering/">taking in record profits</a>. And while there are problems with ever drawing a direct connection between infringement and lost revenues, the estimated impact of the “piracy” SOPA was addressed at was <a href="http://www.cato-at-liberty.org/how-copyright-industries-con-congress/">under $450 million</a> — not pocket change, but not a crippling expense to these corporations.</p>

<p>Is it that these people feel there’s an inherent moral wrong in making a copy of something without authorization? That’s the basis for <a href="http://blog.thephoenix.com/BLOGS/phlog/archive/2012/02/08/bill-keller-new-york-times-stole-our-column-should-we-sue.aspx">charges of hypocrisy against Bill Keller</a>, <a href="http://parislemon.com/post/17388386075/to-catch-a-hypocrite">the CEO of Vevo</a>, and of course <a href="http://www.vice.com/read/lamar-smith-sopa-copyright-whoops">Lamar Smith</a>, to name some very recent examples. Everybody who reads about these knew they were bound to happen — Cardinal Richileu’s <a href="http://sixlines.org/about/">famous “six lines” quote</a> might as well be updated today to specify copyright violations explicitly.</p>

<p>But more importantly, if their goal were to reduce unauthorized copying, one has to assume they’d be taking the obvious action: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/movies/comments/p3cmp/how_hollywood_could_kill_movie_piracy_if_they/">making authorized copying easier</a>. Or at least <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120131/00110017595/warner-bros-just-keeps-pushing-people-to-piracy-new-deal-also-delays-queuing.shtml">don’t make it harder</a>. As long as these companies are undermining efforts to reduce piracy, it just doesn’t seem like it’s their goal.</p>

<p>So is their motivation preserving jobs? That’s the implication in <a href="http://thehill.com/blogs/hillicon-valley/technology/205491-consumer-group-accuses-hollywood-of-threatening-politicians">Chris Dodd’s infamous and embarrassing quote</a> about politicians not staying bought:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Those who count on quote ‘Hollywood’ for support need to understand that this industry is watching very carefully who’s going to stand up for them when their job is at stake. Don’t ask me to write a check for you when you think your job is at risk and then don’t pay any attention to me when my job is at stake.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All along, the understanding has been that the jobs in question were those of the men and women working on film sets or movie theaters (or, extending the idea beyond its logical bounds, the <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20070621/004352.shtml">corn farmers</a> behind the popcorn sales). But if that’s the case, it’s not the perception of the rank-and-file. Look at Wil Wheaton, who <a href="http://wilwheaton.tumblr.com/post/16246156406/mpaa-directly-publicly-threatens-politicians-who">responded to Dodd’s quote</a> by pointing out that he has “lost more money to creative accounting, and American workers have lost more jobs to runaway production, than anything associated with what the MPAA calls piracy.”</p>

<p>But the actions of the entertainment industry start to make sense when you realize that the executives are really thinking about their own jobs. The executives driving the agenda of the MPAA are tremendously well paid, and they know why that is: for decades, they’ve been able to function as the gatekeepers between artists and the public. They’ve had “exclusive custody of the master switch”, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Master-Switch-Information-Empires-Borzoi/dp/0307269930">as Tim Wu quoted former CBS News executive Fred Friendly saying</a>. For the most part, artists have hated this arrangement. But there was no alternative.</p>

<p>Creativity didn’t begin with copyright in 1710, and nobody honestly thinks it will end with the Internet. When these executives see major success stories like <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2011/12/22/technology/louis_ck_million/index.htm">Louis C.K. selling hundreds of thousands of copies of his new special by himself</a>, or <a href="http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/115746-Tim-Schafer-Raises-1-3-Million-Update-Again">Double Fine collecting $1 million in a single day of pre-selling an adventure game</a>, or the <a href="http://mediadecoder.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/30/at-sundance-kickstarter-resembled-a-movie-studio-but-without-the-egos/">10% of Sundance films crowdfunded on Kickstarter this year</a>, they must realize that their catbird seat is in jeopardy.</p>

<p>And you can bet that scares them. They know the Internet is here to stay, and absent legislative intervention, it will continue to disrupt gatekeepers. They probably know that efforts to preserve their outdated function on the Internet, things like <a href="http://domainincite.com/riaa-backs-music-new-gtld-bid/">maneuvering to control the .music TLD</a> for “accredited” musicians, are Hail Mary passes. Too little, too late.</p>

<p>Echoing <a href="http://tim.oreilly.com/pub/a/p2p/2002/12/11/piracy.html">Tim O’Reilly a decade ago</a>, the real threat to gatekeepers is not piracy but irrelevance. They’ve gotten comfortable as the solution to a problem that fewer and fewer people have, and now they can see they’re in a bind. It’s not an excuse, but an explanation: they’re pulling out the stops to defend their position, even if it’s against the interests of their customers, and against the long-term interest of the industry itself.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="gatekeepers" /><category term="mpaa" /><category term="riaa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few weeks ago, I wrote about Paul Carr’s accusation of hypocrisy within the tech community for opposing bad copyright legislation and then also speaking out against plagiarism. His take was wrong, but it wasn’t unusual; it’s all too common for supporters of wrongheaded copyright legislation (like SOPA, PIPA and two decades of more successful proposals) to settle on a characterization of their opponents and then cry foul when those characterizations are not consistent with reality. It’s an example of confirmation bias: favoring information that supports a hypothesis and discarding (or dismissing as hypocritical) information that doesn’t.]]></summary></entry></feed>