<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/muckrock.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T22:31:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/muckrock.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Dropping docs on Jacob the painting police horse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/07/dropping-docs-on-jacob-the-painting-police-horse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dropping docs on Jacob the painting police horse" /><published>2015-08-01T02:00:27-04:00</published><updated>2015-08-01T02:00:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/07/dropping-docs-on-jacob-the-painting-police-horse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/07/dropping-docs-on-jacob-the-painting-police-horse/"><![CDATA[<p>Muckrock has written an <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/news/archives/2015/jul/30/horse-artist-jacob/">article on Jacob, the painting police horse of St. Petersburg, Florida</a>, based on <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/foi/pinellas-county-10455/horse-artist-jacob-17312/">documents I obtained through a public records request to the local police</a> in April. There’s no scandal here, but it’s fun to read about a city so smitten with their talented equestrian officers.</p>

<p>Perhaps my favorite missive comes from Kevin King in the Mayor’s Office, who writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Wayne,</p>

  <p>The painting police horse is rivaling Dali in terms of popularity in St. Pete right now.</p>

  <p>Can your office work with Yolanda Fernandez in Police on harnessing this situation?</p>

  <p>FYI – the most recent request came from Larry Biddle w Arts Xchange who would like the horse for a fundraiser (I believe)….</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But they’re pretty much all like that. Many more clips <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/news/archives/2015/jul/30/horse-artist-jacob/">over at Muckrock</a>.</p>

<p>One small note: alongside the Jacob request, I filed one on info about the trademark applications on <em>another</em> celebrity police horse in St. Petersburg—Amos the Wonder Horse—and <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/foi/pinellas-county-10455/amos-the-wonder-horse-17313/">came up empty handed</a>. That’s a bit strange, considering the trademark <a href="http://tsdr.uspto.gov/#caseNumber=86507083&amp;caseType=SERIAL_NO&amp;searchType=statusSearch">was filed in January</a>—it was just published for review a month ago—but you’ve gotta pick your battles.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="florida" /><category term="foia" /><category term="horse" /><category term="muckrock" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Muckrock has written an article on Jacob, the painting police horse of St. Petersburg, Florida, based on documents I obtained through a public records request to the local police in April. There’s no scandal here, but it’s fun to read about a city so smitten with their talented equestrian officers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Oakland’s awesome public records request system</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/05/oaklands-awesome-public-records-request-system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oakland’s awesome public records request system" /><published>2015-05-04T19:34:03-04:00</published><updated>2015-05-04T19:34:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/05/oaklands-awesome-public-records-request-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/05/oaklands-awesome-public-records-request-system/"><![CDATA[<p>Oakland’s employee compensation database is the kind of public record that should be proactively available, even with historical versions, without requiring a formal public records request. But since I couldn’t find it online, <a href="http://records.oaklandnet.com/request/8927">I filed a request</a>, and got to interact for the first time with <a href="http://www.codeforamerica.org/apps/recordtrac/">Oakland’s very cool RecordTrac system</a> for handling those requests. RecordTrac is a <a href="http://oaklandlocal.com/2013/10/oaktech-citys-new-recordtrac-app-launches-built-by-code-for-america-fellows/">Code For America fellowship project that launched a year and a half ago</a>, and it ensures <a href="http://www.cjr.org/united_states_project/recordtrac_making_the_foia_process_less_terrible.php">the entire process is online and publicly available</a>, so users can see every request that gets filed and what response it received.</p>

<p>The value of that system becomes obvious pretty quickly after you start using it. For example, when I started looking through <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZTr-DlQ2IlEJFtZGpoEEv81BbyK8zscQzKGh0TL9szo/edit?usp=sharing">the compensation database</a>, one fact that jumped out immediately is that some Oakland police officers make significantly more than their base salary in payment for overtime work. In fact, the highest paid Oakland government employee in 2014 is a police officer who got some $165,000 in overtime pay. What could possibly be going on with overtime at OPD?</p>

<p>Searching through the public requests database turns up another person’s request, <a href="http://records.oaklandnet.com/request/7964">specifically covering OPD and overtime</a>. Those documents were released in the last few days and are immediately available to me and any other interested member of the public. That’s incredibly helpful to both me and the city. I get the records I’m looking for much faster, and can send follow-up requests without waiting for another round trip, and Oakland doesn’t have to process as many duplicates.</p>

<p>It also comes in handy where there are no responsive documents. Traditionally those requests don’t see a lot of publicity because, well, there are no documents to report on. But sometimes their absence is an interesting data point itself. Take, for example, <a href="http://records.oaklandnet.com/request/7946">this request for agreements</a> between the Oakland Public Library and law enforcement on disclosing patron information. It would be a much larger story if there were agreements like that, but it’s nice, too, to be able to refer to the request turning up no responsive documents. ((After I tweeted about this request, the Oakland Public Library reached out to <a href="https://twitter.com/oaklibrary/status/593897888331083776">emphasize its opposition to that sort of agreement</a>.))</p>

<p>If all this seems familiar, it may be because services like <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/">Muckrock</a>, <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/accounts/profile/xor/">where I’m a frequent user</a>, have implemented the same kind of thing on the requester end. Every request gets a permanent URL, where all associated documents are connected and made publicly available. Like RecordTrac, it keeps the status of requests updated, and notifies requesters when new information has come in.</p>

<p>Muckrock definitely makes the public records experience better, and has built an impressive collection of returned documents. But there’s an emergent property of the agencies themselves putting all that information online in the first place.</p>

<p>Oakland was lucky to pilot this program, and the avalanche of requests related to Occupy likely taught the city a lesson about handling them efficiently.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/postcode/recordtrac#recordtrac-">RecordTrac is already free software</a>, and as of about six months ago, the developers rolled the software into a <del><a href="http://blog.postcode.io/post/101138657517/welcome-to-nextrequest-the-open-public-records">hosted product called NextRequest</a></del>. <em>(UPDATE: the main RecordTrac developer <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2015/05/oaklands-awesome-public-records-request-system/#comment-464196">reached out to clarify</a> that NextRequest is not affiliated with the original team. Apologies for the error, and I too hope governments embrace the more open solution.)</em> Hopefully that means more pickup by agencies and governments, bringing a much-needed update to the public records requesting process’s usability and transparency. It can be <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/Screenshot-from-2015-05-05-004958.png">funny to see Muckrock joke</a> about how dated much of our country’s FOIA infrastructure is. But it’d be better to see it fixed.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="foia" /><category term="muckrock" /><category term="oakland" /><category term="recordtrac" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Oakland’s employee compensation database is the kind of public record that should be proactively available, even with historical versions, without requiring a formal public records request. But since I couldn’t find it online, I filed a request, and got to interact for the first time with Oakland’s very cool RecordTrac system for handling those requests. RecordTrac is a Code For America fellowship project that launched a year and a half ago, and it ensures the entire process is online and publicly available, so users can see every request that gets filed and what response it received.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Requesting Lou Reed’s FBI file</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/10/requesting-lou-reeds-fbi-file/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Requesting Lou Reed’s FBI file" /><published>2013-10-28T02:52:23-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-28T02:52:23-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/10/requesting-lou-reeds-fbi-file</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/10/requesting-lou-reeds-fbi-file/"><![CDATA[<p>Lou Reed died today at 71. His music — especially the the four Velvet Underground records — have always been very important to me. (If you must know, not actually <em>always</em>, but starting from the time Liza at Camp Half Moon loaned me <em>Loaded</em> and I listened to it over and over on my Discman.)</p>

<p>When a person dies, the privacy exemptions to the FOIA [(b)(6) and (b)(7)(C)] no longer apply. That means a federal agency like the FBI can produce records that might not have previously been available. Using Muckrock, <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/foi/united-states-of-america-10/lou-reed-fbi-file-8671/">I’ve requested Lou Reed’s FBI file</a>, which must be filled in 4 weeks but may actually come sooner. When <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/foi/united-states-of-america-10/russell-tyrone-jones-ol-dirty-bastard-963/">Rich Jones requested Ol’ Dirty Bastard’s FBI file</a>, that came in a week (and just days before Christmas, too).</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> on November 1 I got a response from the FBI saying there were no responsive documents. I find that hard to believe, but have no choice… unless I want to start rumors that they were withheld according to <a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/5/552#c">5 USC §552(c)</a> because he was an informant or involved in ongoing crimes or something. Barring that—case closed.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="foia" /><category term="lou reed" /><category term="muckrock" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lou Reed died today at 71. His music — especially the the four Velvet Underground records — have always been very important to me. (If you must know, not actually always, but starting from the time Liza at Camp Half Moon loaned me Loaded and I listened to it over and over on my Discman.)]]></summary></entry></feed>