<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/music.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:33:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/music.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">New bot: @78_sampler, serving up old records</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/08/new-bot-78_sampler-serving-up-old-records/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New bot: @78_sampler, serving up old records" /><published>2017-08-11T13:36:49-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-11T13:36:49-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/08/new-bot-78_sampler-serving-up-old-records</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2017/08/new-bot-78_sampler-serving-up-old-records/"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet Archive hosts an <a href="https://archive.org/details/georgeblood">incredible collection</a> of over 25,000 <a href="http://great78.archive.org/">professionally digitized 78rpm records</a>. The great thing about a catalog that large is that, if you know what you want, you’re likely to find it. On the other hand, if you just want to browse it can be overwhelming and even intimidating. Each item could possibly be a delight, but it’s difficult to even think about individual records in the face of such a huge archive.</p>

<p>In that sense, would-be browsers face similar challenges with the Great 78 Project as they do with the <a href="https://usdawatercolors.nal.usda.gov/pom/home.xhtml">Pomological Watercolor Collection</a>—an archive <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/tag/pomological-watercolors/">I’ve worked with a lot</a>. Sensing that similarity, I decided to build a tool like <a href="https://twitter.com/pomological">@pomological</a> to help surface individual records.</p>

<p><span class="citation"><a href="https://twitter.com/78_sampler">@78_sampler</a> tweets every two hours with a randomly selected record from the Archive’s collection. It was important to me that the audio fit smoothly and natively into a Twitter timeline, so I decided to render each tune into a video file using the Archive’s still image of the record as the visual. Twitter limits videos to 2:20—exactly 140 seconds, cute—which is shorter than most 78 tunes, so while rendering the video I truncate the clip at that point with a short audio fade at the end.</span></p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/thisisparker/78_sampler">code to do all this</a> is a short Python script which I’ve posted online. It relies on ffmpeg to do the video encoding. Crafting ffmpeg commands is famously convoluted, and it’s a little frustrating to format those commands to be called from Python. Maybe that’s something I’ll do differently in the future but, for now, this works and I can dip my cup into the deep Archive well with a little more ease than before.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="bots" /><category term="internet archive" /><category term="music" /><category term="programming" /><category term="python" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Internet Archive hosts an incredible collection of over 25,000 professionally digitized 78rpm records. The great thing about a catalog that large is that, if you know what you want, you’re likely to find it. On the other hand, if you just want to browse it can be overwhelming and even intimidating. Each item could possibly be a delight, but it’s difficult to even think about individual records in the face of such a huge archive.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taylor Swift and Garth Brooks each took on their generation’s music bogeyman</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/taylor-swift-and-garth-brooks-each-took-on-their-generations-music-bogeyman/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taylor Swift and Garth Brooks each took on their generation’s music bogeyman" /><published>2015-07-31T03:28:21-04:00</published><updated>2015-07-31T03:28:21-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/taylor-swift-and-garth-brooks-each-took-on-their-generations-music-bogeyman</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2015/07/taylor-swift-and-garth-brooks-each-took-on-their-generations-music-bogeyman/"><![CDATA[<p>The music business tends to repeat itself. Conversations that seem completely intertwined with new technologies mirror those over earlier developments. Read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6990457-piracy">Adrian John’s <em>Piracy</em></a>, for example, and see how closely the file-sharing debate followed the one about sheet music a century earlier.</p>

<p>Even with that background, the parallels between Taylor Swift’s <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20150622/22584031428/taylor-swift-is-not-savior-artists-need.shtml">widely discussed</a> <a href="http://taylorswift.tumblr.com/post/122071902085/to-apple-love-taylor">comments</a> about Apple Music earlier this year and Garth Brooks’ outspoken stance on used CD sales are striking. It’s hard to argue with Swift—she is, after all, a shrewd businesswoman, and who knows what the future holds—but the fact that Brooks’ fears proved so unfounded take some of the winds out of her sails. We may be at the end of history, and today’s problems might be totally unlike the ones we faced before, but probably not.</p>

<p>Here’s an excerpt of <a href="http://taylorswift.tumblr.com/post/122071902085/to-apple-love-taylor">what Swift said about Apple’s free trial</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m sure you are aware that Apple Music will be offering a free 3 month trial to anyone who signs up for the service. I’m not sure you know that Apple Music will not be paying writers, producers, or artists for those three months. I find it to be shocking, disappointing, and completely unlike this historically progressive and generous company.</p>

  <p>This is not about me. Thankfully I am on my fifth album and can support myself, my band, crew, and entire management team by playing live shows. This is about the new artist or band that has just released their first single and will not be paid for its success. This is about the young songwriter who just got his or her first cut and thought that the royalties from that would get them out of debt. This is about the producer who works tirelessly to innovate and create, just like the innovators and creators at Apple are pioneering in their field…but will not get paid for a quarter of a year’s worth of plays on his or her songs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And here’s a journalist from the <em>Seattle Post-Intelligencer</em> <a href="http://www.deseretnews.com/article/304702/GARTH-BROOKS-HASNT-THROWN-IN-THE-HAT-ON-USED-CD-CONTROVERSY.html?pg=all">paraphrasing Brooks’ comments at his sold-out arena concert</a>, a few months after announcing he would only be selling his new record at stores that did not carry used CDs.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Brooks said that because no royalties are paid on the sale of used CDs, writers, labels, publishers and artists were being cheated. He said he would only supply chains that sell used CDs with his cassettes, and hinted that he might be working on another “format” to thwart such sales.</p>

  <p>Brooks said he does not need any money, but lesser-known artists could suffer if secondhand CD sales take off. If used CD sales were to go into massive retail, he said, it would severely affect people in the recording industry, creating a sales loop that would profit only stores but not the creators, publishers and artists.</p>

  <p>CD retailers, meanwhile, have argued that the cost of new CDs is too high for young buyers, and that selling used CDs exposes an artist’s music to different audiences.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For both Swift and Brooks—each among the best-selling acts of their generation—an emerging marketplace that makes music more accessible—but less well-compensated—was worth speaking out about. They both note that it’s not about them, but about the principle, and that the unpaid exposure would hurt new musicians. Both point to the middleman’s profits as an obvious evil.</p>

<p>To my mind, both artists are mistaken about the value of exposure and discoverability. Tim O’Reilly’s observation that <a href="http://www.openp2p.com/pub/a/p2p/2002/12/11/piracy.html">obscurity is a greater threat to the emerging artist than piracy</a> remains true; it’s also true that obscurity is a greater threat than used record sales, free trials, and most everything else.</p>

<p>But on the other counts, too, Garth Brooks was wrong. Used CD sales didn’t undermine the music industry and they didn’t keep new artists from finding audiences.</p>

<p>We know this because his <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/1993-08-13/business/fi-23386_1_garth-brooks">plan to sell only through certain CD stores failed</a>, amidst anti-trust investigations into his record label.</p>

<p>Taylor Swift was, at least narrowly, right. Apple Music should’ve been paying royalties for its free trials all along. But elsewhere, her skepticism about streaming and business models that include “free” might not be well placed. Unfortunately, because music licensing in this space is fundamentally more of a permissions culture than selling plastic disks was, we may never find out.</p>

<p><em>Update: This post has been <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20150731/06131031809/taylor-swifts-streaming-rant-nearly-identical-to-garth-brooks-used-cd-rant.shtml">re-published on Techdirt</a>. Thanks, Mike!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="first sale" /><category term="garth brooks" /><category term="music" /><category term="piracy" /><category term="taylor swift" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The music business tends to repeat itself. Conversations that seem completely intertwined with new technologies mirror those over earlier developments. Read Adrian John’s Piracy, for example, and see how closely the file-sharing debate followed the one about sheet music a century earlier.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Valerie Simpson on sampling and creativity</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/07/valerie-simpson-sampling-creativity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Valerie Simpson on sampling and creativity" /><published>2014-07-10T20:42:47-04:00</published><updated>2014-07-10T20:42:47-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/07/valerie-simpson-sampling-creativity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/07/valerie-simpson-sampling-creativity/"><![CDATA[<p>I tuned in to <a href="http://www.npr.org/2013/07/19/203624950/valerie-simpson-on-song-travels">an older episode of the public radio show “Song Travels”</a> on a drive the other featuring performances and a discussion with Valerie Simpson. Simpson is a musician and with her husband made up the legendary married Ashford &amp; Simpson songwriting duo, behind “Ain’t No Mountain High Enough” and a million other tunes.</p>

<p>I thought her comments on other artists sampling her recordings was interesting. Here’s a clip from the show, and a partial transcription:</p>

<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" controls="controls" id="audio-1381-2" preload="none" style="width: 100%;"><source src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20130719_pj_vsimpson-clip.mp3?_=2" type="audio/mpeg" />&lt;/source&gt;[https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20130719\_pj\_vsimpson-clip.mp3](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20130719_pj_vsimpson-clip.mp3)</audio>

<blockquote>
  <p>I always think of it as a separate entity. I don’t, you know, I don’t get hung up on it. I’m glad that these young performers, you know, hear something and want to create another piece of music. I call it another piece, because usually they use so little of whatever was yours in their new thing, and then you claim a sizeable portion of it, so you have two things now in existence. And so, I’m cool with that.</p>

  <p>…like I say, it’s another baby born.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>She also talks in the clip about how different record deals throughout her career means she some sampling deals can be done without her input, but that artists often seek it anyway.</p>

<p>Of course it helps that Simpson gets paid for samples. But it strikes me as really cool that she sees artistic creativity as a positive sum effort, and that other people sampling her work doesn’t diminish that work at all.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="music" /><category term="sampling" /><category term="valerie simpson" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I tuned in to an older episode of the public radio show “Song Travels” on a drive the other featuring performances and a discussion with Valerie Simpson. Simpson is a musician and with her husband made up the legendary married Ashford &amp; Simpson songwriting duo, behind “Ain’t No Mountain High Enough” and a million other tunes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A closer look at the “Girl on Fire” copyright lawsuit</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/12/a-closer-look-at-the-girl-on-fire-copyright-lawsuit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A closer look at the “Girl on Fire” copyright lawsuit" /><published>2012-12-20T05:32:56-05:00</published><updated>2012-12-20T05:32:56-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/12/a-closer-look-at-the-girl-on-fire-copyright-lawsuit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/12/a-closer-look-at-the-girl-on-fire-copyright-lawsuit/"><![CDATA[<p>Last week Earl Shuman, a songwriter behind several hits in the 50s and 60s, <a href="http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr-esq/alicia-keys-sued-girl-fire-403147">sued Alicia Keys for copyright infringement in her recent single “Girl on Fire.”</a> He alleges that the song infringes a tune he wrote in 1962, which was recorded as “Hey There Lonely Girl” by Eddie Holman and which peaked at #2 on <a href="http://www.billboard.com/charts/hot-100#/charts/hot-100?chartDate=1970-02-21">the Billboard top 100 in the week of February 21, 1970</a>. ((It just couldn’t quite beat <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YXPJOUD7G0">“Thank You Falettinme Be Mice Elf Agin.”</a>))</p>

<p>Shuman’s allegations are incorrect. There’s some similarity between the two songs, as I’ll show below, but it does not approach the level of copyright infringement. It should not result in Keys having to license Shuman’s composition or settle with him to use the song.</p>

<p>The complaint is a bit unusual in that it doesn’t really present evidence of copying. It quotes heavily from <a href="http://www.showbiz411.com/2012/11/25/alicia-keys-girl-on-fire-also-a-lonely-girl-from-1970">a blog post about the Keys song</a>, which first noted the similarity. In a later post, the same blogger (Roger Friedman) describes <a href="http://www.showbiz411.com/2012/12/04/alicia-keys-hey-there-lonely-girl-writer-is-very-much-alive-and-wants-his-money">a subsequent interaction with Shuman</a>, by that point lawyered up and looking for some remuneration.</p>

<h2 id="hearing-the-similarities">Hearing the similarities</h2>

<p>At issue, apparently, is one line in the Alicia Keys song, which she sings about halfway through, and doesn’t repeat. For comparison’s sake, I’ve taken it out of context and placed it next to the similar line from the Holman song:</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F71930345%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-ecTBc&amp;color=ff6600&amp;auto_play=false&amp;show_artwork=false" width="100%"></iframe>

<p>You can hear the melodic similarity. In technical terms, both songs feature the phrase “lonely girl” sung in a arpeggiated descending minor triad, followed by a second descending major triad (the top three notes of a minor seven chord). But if Keys knows Holman’s song, which seems likely, it’s hard to think of her reference as anything other than a quote.</p>

<h2 id="quotes-not-samples">Quotes, not samples</h2>

<p>In Friedman’s blog post, he refers to that as an uncredited “sample.” He does it in kind of a snippy way, too: “Do they teach this sampling stuff at Juilliard?”</p>

<p>Friedman is incorrect to apply the term sample here. Unless he’s suggesting that Keys has incorporated Holman’s recording into her recording, there’s isn’t any sampling. What Keys has done is quoting, a term used in music in much the same way it’s used in writing. When MC Hammer <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=otCpCn0l4Wo">raps over a looped section of “Superfreak,”</a> that’s a sample. When Eric Clapton plays the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IDZqmF3zS04&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=2m1s">first few notes of “Blue Moon” in the guitar solo on “Sunshine of Your Love,”</a> that’s a quote.</p>

<p>Some people think samples are inherently uncreative or unoriginal, and I think those people need to lighten up and listen to some music. But you’d have to be pretty far off the deep end to think that musical quotes are also unacceptable, or that each one requires a license agreement.</p>

<p>Mixing up samples and quotes is especially hazardous in this case. For one thing, sampling of short segments of a song would require getting permission from the owner of the copyright in the sound recording, not the owner of the composition. Shuman’s the songwriter, so he controls the composition, but not Holman’s recording. ((The owner of the sound recording is almost certainly Holman’s record label, ABC Records, which folded into MCA Records, which folded into Geffen. Can you imagine why clearing such a sample might be difficult?))</p>

<p>For another thing, samples are subject to a very strict interpretation of the law. Some people read the landmark <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridgeport_Music,_Inc._v._Dimension_Films">Bridgeport v. Dimension</a> case to say that no sampling is allowed at all without a license, no matter how short or insubstantial the sample is. But that’s not the case with musical quotes. In that case you get to do a full fair use analysis of the use, and these allegations wouldn’t stand up against that.</p>

<h2 id="girls-and-boys">Girls and boys</h2>

<p>So we’re talking about one line in a composition that was quoted, not sampled. How much of the original composition did Keys quote, then? Well, it may be useful to go back, here, to the original recording of the song. Before Holman’s smash hit 1970 version, Ruby &amp; the Romantics recorded it in 1963. But the first recording (and the composition) was called “Lonely Boy.” Here’s the relevant section:</p>

<iframe frameborder="no" height="166" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F71930434%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-F4LYv&amp;color=ff6600&amp;auto_play=false&amp;show_artwork=false" width="100%"></iframe>

<p>This is the original composition, and it’s about a boy not a girl. The song sheet attached to the complaint, too, is for a song titled “Lonely Boy.” That means we’re down to the word “lonely.” (Also, to my ear, the timing is a bit different in this version, with less swing than in either Holman’s or Keys’, but really that’s splitting hairs.) Even assuming that Keys was intentionally and explicitly making an overt reference to Holman’s recording when she sang the “lonely girl” line, it requires an extraordinary stretch to say that reference constitutes an infringement on the original recording.</p>

<p>Alicia Keys quoting even as many as six notes and a word or two from a popular song in a teeny tiny section of her new single just isn’t copyright infringement. I feel for Shuman as a songwriter, but he (and his lawyer) are wrong on this one.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="alicia keys" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="earl shuman" /><category term="music" /><category term="recording" /><category term="sampling" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last week Earl Shuman, a songwriter behind several hits in the 50s and 60s, sued Alicia Keys for copyright infringement in her recent single “Girl on Fire.” He alleges that the song infringes a tune he wrote in 1962, which was recorded as “Hey There Lonely Girl” by Eddie Holman and which peaked at #2 on the Billboard top 100 in the week of February 21, 1970. ((It just couldn’t quite beat “Thank You Falettinme Be Mice Elf Agin.”))]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Answering Paul Kelly’s “how many?” questions</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/answering-paul-kellys-how-many-questions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Answering Paul Kelly’s “how many?” questions" /><published>2012-09-03T04:09:55-04:00</published><updated>2012-09-03T04:09:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/answering-paul-kellys-how-many-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/answering-paul-kellys-how-many-questions/"><![CDATA[<p>I like this song by Paul Kelly, called “Careless.” It’s embedded below:</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="435" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Fq7X_6PlilE" width="580"></iframe>

<p>He asks a few questions in the song, and I’ve got the answers.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many cabs in New York City?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are <a href="http://www.nyc.gov/html/tlc/html/about/about.shtml">13,237 taxis</a> regulated by the New York City Taxi and Limousine Commission.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many angels on a pin?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think the answer to this is pretty conclusively <a href="http://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?db=comics&amp;id=2576">between one and 30 vigintillion</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many notes in a saxophone?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This one’s a bit tougher. These days, the standard accepted range for saxophone is between a B♭ below the treble clef to an F♯ above it. That’s about two and a half octaves, or a total of 32 notes. ((The glib answer, of course, is that there are twelve notes, repeated in various octaves.)) It’s possible, if a bit convoluted, to play a low A and a high G, so we can add two for a total of 34 notes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How many tears in a bottle of gin?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Assuming an average bottle size of 750 mL, and an average tear size of 6.2 µl (as per the research of <a href="http://www.iovs.org/content/5/3/264.full.pdf">S. Mishima, A. Gasset, S. D. Klyce, Jr., and J. L. Baum [pdf]</a>), a bottle of gin could fit <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=750+ml+%2F+6.2+µl">121,000 tears</a>. I don’t know why you’d want to do that, though.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="australia" /><category term="music" /><category term="paul kelly" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I like this song by Paul Kelly, called “Careless.” It’s embedded below:]]></summary></entry></feed>