<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/patent.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:04:09-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/patent.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Digging in to the USPTO FOIA 2014 log</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/digging-uspto-2014-foia-log/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digging in to the USPTO FOIA 2014 log" /><published>2014-11-02T19:13:18-05:00</published><updated>2014-11-02T19:13:18-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/digging-uspto-2014-foia-log</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/11/digging-uspto-2014-foia-log/"><![CDATA[<p>The USPTO has released a log of the FOIA requests it has processed in the fiscal year 2014 in response to <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/foi/united-states-of-america-10/foia-log-2014-13686/">a request I submitted early last month</a>. ((The US government’s fiscal calendar runs October to October, so FY2014 has been over for a month.)) Looking through these logs is interesting because you can start to pick out a little narrative for many of the requests, and you can get a sense of the public’s connection with an agency. The USPTO’s log is manageable, too: they only handle about 250-300 FOIA requests per year, and in my experience have been very timely with replies.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.muckrock.com/foi/united-states-of-america-10/foia-log-2014-13686/#1350531-responsive-documents">full PDF from the USPTO</a>—and <a href="http://muckrock.s3.amazonaws.com/files_static/uspto-fy2014-foia-log.csv">my cleaned up CSV of the data</a>—are available from Muckrock. I’ve gone through and picked out some of the things that struck me as interesting.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The request that took the longest to fulfill was <a href="http://patentlyo.com/author/dennis-crouch">Dennis Crouch’s (of Patently O)</a> for “Nomination documents for Michelle Lee as Deputy Directorof the USPTO; documents discussing whether the Michelle Lee’s nomination process was proper and/or followed the law.” It took 98 days.</li>
  <li>At least 8 of the 256 requests were about the Washington football team whose trademark has recently been challenged. They requests variously wanted communications with the public, with Congress, and with the relevant trademark judges.</li>
  <li>One Josef Viel requested in March a “list of all the retailers that sell disposable underwear.” In September—six months later—he was back, looking for a “list of manufacturers that produce disposable underwear and retailers that sell them.”</li>
  <li>Two requests close to my heart asked for information about a trademark by Banksy and USPTO documents on The Pirate Bay. I’ve reached out to those filers to see if they got anything interesting. (Note: the Banksy request has to do with an interesting trademark situation related to the registration of names or pseudonyms; EverythingTrademarks has a <a href="http://everythingtrademarks.com/2013/12/07/banksy/">really great write-up of what’s going on</a>.)</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.keionline.org/">Knowledge Ecology International</a> and <a href="https://www.publicknowledge.org/">Public Knowledge</a> each appeared: KEI was looking for information about VP Biden’s communications with the government of India about the cancer drug Herceptin, and PK wanted a <a href="http://patentlyo.com/lawjournal/2014/11/uspto-on-101.html">list of patent applications that were withdrawn</a> from allowance as a result of <em>Alice v. CLS Bank</em>.</li>
  <li>A couple of secrecy related things, pertaining to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Invention_Secrecy_Act">Invention Secrecy Act</a> that creates sort of a parallel classified patent system. <a href="http://fas.org/blogs/secrecy/">Steven Aftergood</a> requested a <a href="http://fas.org/blogs/secrecy/2013/10/invention-secrecy-2013/">copy of the latest Secrecy Review Activity Report</a>; Jonathan Byrne has two separate requests for info about the Invention Secrecy Act (which might be the result of a defective first request) and then a follow up specifically about this previously classified patent for a <a href="https://www.google.com/patents/US6728328">safety control circuit for a neutronic reactor</a>; and <a href="https://twitter.com/JasonLeopold">Jason Leopold</a> requested a list of rescinded secrecy orders.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="foia" /><category term="patent" /><category term="uspto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The USPTO has released a log of the FOIA requests it has processed in the fiscal year 2014 in response to a request I submitted early last month. ((The US government’s fiscal calendar runs October to October, so FY2014 has been over for a month.)) Looking through these logs is interesting because you can start to pick out a little narrative for many of the requests, and you can get a sense of the public’s connection with an agency. The USPTO’s log is manageable, too: they only handle about 250-300 FOIA requests per year, and in my experience have been very timely with replies.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Copying and creativity at day one of XOXO</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/copying-and-creativity-at-day-one-of-xoxo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copying and creativity at day one of XOXO" /><published>2012-09-15T21:26:18-04:00</published><updated>2012-09-15T21:26:18-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/copying-and-creativity-at-day-one-of-xoxo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/09/copying-and-creativity-at-day-one-of-xoxo/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/xoxosign.jpg"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/IMG_10213.jpg" alt="XOXO" title="XOXO" /></a>The talks at day one of <a href="http://xoxofest.com/">the XOXO festival</a> have been incredibly high quality: actual innovators and creators of disruptive media and technology have relayed their experiences of eliminating middlemen and charting new territory for success. It’s just amazing to see what a cool group of people have come together for this event.</p>

<p>One common theme within the talks has been the interaction between innovation, copying, and the effect of copyright and patents. More exciting, these creators have all arrived at a similar mindset and are able to articulate it well.</p>

<h2 id="innovation-depends-on-copying">Innovation depends on copying</h2>

<p>There were so many examples of artists and creators talking about the relationship between their own creativity and the influences of others.</p>

<p>Ron Carmen, the developer behind the game <a href="http://www.worldofgoo.com/">World of Goo</a>, talked about how he learned video game development by copying a game he liked. “That’s what you do with things you like. You copy them.” <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/jaaaaaaa">Julia Nunes</a>, the YouTube ukulele superstar, started by doing covers until she was writing original songs.</p>

<p>Bre Pettis, whose company <a href="http://www.makerbot.com/">MakerBot</a> makes inexpensive 3D printers, said that their tech development was based on “expired patents, open source code, and epic internal innovation.”</p>

<p>Dan Harmon, the creator of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Community_%28TV_series%29">the TV series Community</a>, was explicit about his influences in television and talked about how frustrating it was to work with television executives who didn’t know and breathe its common culture.</p>

<h2 id="copycats-are-frustrating-but-not-worth-your-time">Copycats are frustrating, but not worth your time</h2>

<p>Many of the talks acknowledged the problem that innovators face costs and risks that uncreative copycats do not, which can cause problems. The guys at Studio Neat showed a slide of a direct ripoff of the <a href="http://www.studioneat.com/products/glif-for-iphone-4">Glif</a>, their iPhone kickstand and tripod mount that they funded through Kickstarter. Even the packaging was basically identical. They weren’t happy about it — even the slide was painful to show, they said — but came to the conclusion that their time was better spent innovating than trying to chase down the copycats. “Don’t spend your time chasing down copycats; make them chase you.”</p>

<p>Their story was not unique. Ron Carmen, the game developer, had plenty of experience with ripoffs, including from larger companies. Bre Pettis at MakerBot talked about companies that have taken their open source plans and cut corners to sell cheaper printers. On the other hand, a proliferation of 3D printers, and the corresponding creativity at scale, are good for them as a company. So the difficulty, he said, is releasing their plans in a way that “makes people copy, but encourages innovation.”</p>

<h2 id="restrictions-on-copying--especially-patents--are-overrated">Restrictions on copying — especially patents — are “overrated”</h2>

<p>“Overrated” was the word the guys at Studio Neat used for patents. Patents aren’t a silver bullet or a magical force field against copying, and spending time in court is worse than spending time innovating. In their field, which moves fast, the first mover advantage is more important than a legal monopoly.</p>

<p>MakerBot’s Bre Pettis said that he always assumed the patent system would collapse before his company was big enough to have to deal with it, but now we’re “stuck with it.” His company makes printers that are between $1,000 and $2,000, but compete with $200,000 models. The companies that make those have patents that they are eager to enforce, making innovation in that space difficult.</p>

<h2 id="the-best-way-to-be-in-the-right-place-at-the-right-time-is-to-be-in-all-the-places-all-the-time">The best way to be in the right place at the right time is to be in all the places all the time</h2>

<p>Almost all of the speakers described a moment where their works “tipped,” and suddenly became much more popular. The ukulele player Julia Nunes had one of the best descriptions about how it doesn’t come in the form of “a big break,” but rather as many small leaps and opportunities, from being featured on the front page of YouTube to getting to open for Ben Folds to appearing on Conan O’Brien.</p>

<p>The other speakers had similar “breaks”: for Studio Neat it was John Gruber posting <a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/10/04/glif">a link to their project on his website</a>; for the creators of <a href="http://buy.indiegamethemovie.com/"><em>Indie Game: the Movie</em></a>, it was Andy Baio tweeting about them. What these breaks have in common is that they were unforeseen, and the result of a piece of content making it into the right person’s hands at just the right moment.</p>

<p>So how do you facilitate that? None of the speakers said it directly ((Julia Nunes came closest when she said “I make myself incredibly easy to find.”)) but the surest way to be in the right place at the right time is to be all the places all the time. This is hard for people to do, but it’s easy for content: just make it easy to copy and distribute your work, and your fans will take care of the rest.</p>

<p>Cory Doctorow refers to this strategy as “<a href="http://www.locusmag.com/Features/2008/05/cory-doctorow-think-like-dandelion.html">thinking like a dandelion</a>.” Instead of fretting and focusing on each copy, make as many as you can and make it easy for others to make them too.</p>

<h2>***</h2>

<p>One of the remarkable things about this conference has been the invigorating effect it has on my creativity. Seeing these people talk about making things — I want to make things! Thinking like a dandelion, and getting my creativity out there, seems like a great way to start.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="innovation" /><category term="patent" /><category term="xoxo" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The talks at day one of the XOXO festival have been incredibly high quality: actual innovators and creators of disruptive media and technology have relayed their experiences of eliminating middlemen and charting new territory for success. It’s just amazing to see what a cool group of people have come together for this event.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patenting away an open science opportunity</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/patenting-away-open-science-opportunity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patenting away an open science opportunity" /><published>2012-08-28T03:46:13-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-28T03:46:13-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/patenting-away-open-science-opportunity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/patenting-away-open-science-opportunity/"><![CDATA[<p>By almost any measure, Jack Andraka, the 15-year-old science prodigy from Maryland, should be a hero of the open science movement. After all, he has gotten a lot of well-deserved attention in the past few months for his work <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bruceupbin/2012/06/18/wait-did-this-15-year-old-from-maryland-just-change-cancer-treatment/">developing a new test for pancreatic cancer</a>. By his own estimates, the test he developed is 168 times faster and 26,667 times cheaper than the existing state-of-the-art test. He says the insight for the test came to him while he was “<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-19291258">chilling out in biology class</a>,” and that it was helped along by search engines and free online science papers.</p>

<p>On its face, this is a major victory for open science. The right person was able to find the right materials and combine them in such a way to make some important scientific progress, all because there were few barriers in place to stop him. Even better, he was rewarded for this development immediately, with a bounty much greater than most high school sophomores can expect to see in a year — for his efforts, he was awarded the Intel Science Fair grand prize of $75,000, and smaller category prizes for <a href="http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2012-05-24/news/bs-ar-student-intel-winner-20120523_1_top-prize-grand-prize-intel-science-fair">a total of $100,500</a>.</p>

<p>I want to close it up there, and just congratulate him on being such a remarkable example of the power of open access. But, alas, there’s a hitch. From <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bruceupbin/2012/06/18/wait-did-this-15-year-old-from-maryland-just-change-cancer-treatment/">the long Forbes article about his discovery</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>He says he’s been contacted by four companies, including Quest Diagnostics, about potentially licensing or commercializing the idea. “I got a really fierce patent lawyer right after I won ISEF,” says Andraka, laughing, from his home in Maryland.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have a few problems with that statement. Underlying all of them: why is he even seeking a patent? Patents are Constitutional only insofar as they <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_Clause">promote the progress of science and the useful arts</a>. But in this story, it was the <em>lack</em> of restrictions that allowed progress.</p>

<p>A patent would undermine at least one significant component of his discovery. It’s all but inevitable that the impressive savings from his test will be reduced when the cost of lawyers, licensing, and monopoly pricing get factored in. It’s still going to be much cheaper than the existing test, but it will also be less widely available as its distribution is limited by the single point of licensing.</p>

<p>Further, it’s not even clear he’s eligible for a patent since <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/supreme-court-gets-it-right-no-patents-laws-nature">the Supreme Court ruling in Mayo v. Prometheus</a>. That case, decided earlier this year, actually concerned a patent on a medical diagnostic test. The Court held that observations of a natural correlation do not constitute patent-eligible subject matter.</p>

<p>Nobody’s knocking his achievement, and it’s incredibly impressive and good for humanity that Jack Andraka was able to make this discovery. I just wish he’d take a page from the book of the great Jonas Salk, who, when asked who owned the patent on his breakthrough polio vaccine, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/11/25/magazine/once-again-a-man-with-a-mission.html?pagewanted=all">responded simply</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Well, the people, I would say. There is no patent. Could you patent the sun?</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cancer" /><category term="jack andraka" /><category term="open access" /><category term="open science" /><category term="patent" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By almost any measure, Jack Andraka, the 15-year-old science prodigy from Maryland, should be a hero of the open science movement. After all, he has gotten a lot of well-deserved attention in the past few months for his work developing a new test for pancreatic cancer. By his own estimates, the test he developed is 168 times faster and 26,667 times cheaper than the existing state-of-the-art test. He says the insight for the test came to him while he was “chilling out in biology class,” and that it was helped along by search engines and free online science papers.]]></summary></entry></feed>