<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/piracy.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T19:46:48-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/piracy.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Taylor Swift and Garth Brooks each took on their generation’s music bogeyman</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/07/taylor-swift-and-garth-brooks-each-took-on-their-generations-music-bogeyman/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taylor Swift and Garth Brooks each took on their generation’s music bogeyman" /><published>2015-07-31T03:28:21-04:00</published><updated>2015-07-31T03:28:21-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/07/taylor-swift-and-garth-brooks-each-took-on-their-generations-music-bogeyman</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/07/taylor-swift-and-garth-brooks-each-took-on-their-generations-music-bogeyman/"><![CDATA[<p>The music business tends to repeat itself. Conversations that seem completely intertwined with new technologies mirror those over earlier developments. Read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6990457-piracy">Adrian John’s <em>Piracy</em></a>, for example, and see how closely the file-sharing debate followed the one about sheet music a century earlier.</p>

<p>Even with that background, the parallels between Taylor Swift’s <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20150622/22584031428/taylor-swift-is-not-savior-artists-need.shtml">widely discussed</a> <a href="http://taylorswift.tumblr.com/post/122071902085/to-apple-love-taylor">comments</a> about Apple Music earlier this year and Garth Brooks’ outspoken stance on used CD sales are striking. It’s hard to argue with Swift—she is, after all, a shrewd businesswoman, and who knows what the future holds—but the fact that Brooks’ fears proved so unfounded take some of the winds out of her sails. We may be at the end of history, and today’s problems might be totally unlike the ones we faced before, but probably not.</p>

<p>Here’s an excerpt of <a href="http://taylorswift.tumblr.com/post/122071902085/to-apple-love-taylor">what Swift said about Apple’s free trial</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m sure you are aware that Apple Music will be offering a free 3 month trial to anyone who signs up for the service. I’m not sure you know that Apple Music will not be paying writers, producers, or artists for those three months. I find it to be shocking, disappointing, and completely unlike this historically progressive and generous company.</p>

  <p>This is not about me. Thankfully I am on my fifth album and can support myself, my band, crew, and entire management team by playing live shows. This is about the new artist or band that has just released their first single and will not be paid for its success. This is about the young songwriter who just got his or her first cut and thought that the royalties from that would get them out of debt. This is about the producer who works tirelessly to innovate and create, just like the innovators and creators at Apple are pioneering in their field…but will not get paid for a quarter of a year’s worth of plays on his or her songs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And here’s a journalist from the <em>Seattle Post-Intelligencer</em> <a href="http://www.deseretnews.com/article/304702/GARTH-BROOKS-HASNT-THROWN-IN-THE-HAT-ON-USED-CD-CONTROVERSY.html?pg=all">paraphrasing Brooks’ comments at his sold-out arena concert</a>, a few months after announcing he would only be selling his new record at stores that did not carry used CDs.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Brooks said that because no royalties are paid on the sale of used CDs, writers, labels, publishers and artists were being cheated. He said he would only supply chains that sell used CDs with his cassettes, and hinted that he might be working on another “format” to thwart such sales.</p>

  <p>Brooks said he does not need any money, but lesser-known artists could suffer if secondhand CD sales take off. If used CD sales were to go into massive retail, he said, it would severely affect people in the recording industry, creating a sales loop that would profit only stores but not the creators, publishers and artists.</p>

  <p>CD retailers, meanwhile, have argued that the cost of new CDs is too high for young buyers, and that selling used CDs exposes an artist’s music to different audiences.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For both Swift and Brooks—each among the best-selling acts of their generation—an emerging marketplace that makes music more accessible—but less well-compensated—was worth speaking out about. They both note that it’s not about them, but about the principle, and that the unpaid exposure would hurt new musicians. Both point to the middleman’s profits as an obvious evil.</p>

<p>To my mind, both artists are mistaken about the value of exposure and discoverability. Tim O’Reilly’s observation that <a href="http://www.openp2p.com/pub/a/p2p/2002/12/11/piracy.html">obscurity is a greater threat to the emerging artist than piracy</a> remains true; it’s also true that obscurity is a greater threat than used record sales, free trials, and most everything else.</p>

<p>But on the other counts, too, Garth Brooks was wrong. Used CD sales didn’t undermine the music industry and they didn’t keep new artists from finding audiences.</p>

<p>We know this because his <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/1993-08-13/business/fi-23386_1_garth-brooks">plan to sell only through certain CD stores failed</a>, amidst anti-trust investigations into his record label.</p>

<p>Taylor Swift was, at least narrowly, right. Apple Music should’ve been paying royalties for its free trials all along. But elsewhere, her skepticism about streaming and business models that include “free” might not be well placed. Unfortunately, because music licensing in this space is fundamentally more of a permissions culture than selling plastic disks was, we may never find out.</p>

<p><em>Update: This post has been <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20150731/06131031809/taylor-swifts-streaming-rant-nearly-identical-to-garth-brooks-used-cd-rant.shtml">re-published on Techdirt</a>. Thanks, Mike!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="first sale" /><category term="garth brooks" /><category term="music" /><category term="piracy" /><category term="taylor swift" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The music business tends to repeat itself. Conversations that seem completely intertwined with new technologies mirror those over earlier developments. Read Adrian John’s Piracy, for example, and see how closely the file-sharing debate followed the one about sheet music a century earlier.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ulysses piracy case and “Innocence of Muslims”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/03/the-ulysses-piracy-case-and-innocence-of-muslims/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ulysses piracy case and “Innocence of Muslims”" /><published>2014-03-23T19:18:20-04:00</published><updated>2014-03-23T19:18:20-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/03/the-ulysses-piracy-case-and-innocence-of-muslims</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/03/the-ulysses-piracy-case-and-innocence-of-muslims/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve just finished reading Robert Spoo’s book “<a href="http://global.oup.com/academic/product/without-copyrights-9780199927876">Without Copyrights</a>,” an academic look at the history of American publishing in the 19th and early 20th centuries, when American copyright first did not apply at all to works first published abroad, and later applied only with strict manufacturing and notice requirements. The first half of the book documents the interesting practice of copyright-like trade courtesy among publishers, through which those businesses kept the costs of books relatively stable, paid authors through voluntary payments, and internally punished defectors from the system.</p>

<p>But the second half was even more interesting. It covers the suit James Joyce filed against Samuel Roth for his unauthorized publication of <em>Ulysses</em> in the US, and the suit Joyce and Random House fought to publish and unexpurgated copy of the book, which was then considered obscene. That first case, <em>Joyce v. Roth</em>, was especially salient in light of the recent copyright case <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/02/bad-facts-really-bad-law-court-orders-google-censor-controversial-video-based"><em>Garcia v. Google</em></a>, the “Innocence of Muslims” case.</p>

<p><em>Ulysses</em> was one of the books affected by early 20th century copyright law’s manufacturing requirements. Its controversial contents prevented an American publication simultaneous with its European debut, throwing the work quickly into the US public domain. ((It’s a bit more complicated than that, especially owing to a serialized American version, but I think the broad strokes suffice here.)) As a result, Joyce had no American copyright claim to go after Roth with.</p>

<p>Instead of copyright then, <em>Joyce v. Roth</em> alleged <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/176451/copyright-without-law?page=0,1">violations of a New York state privacy law</a>, with Joyce claiming that Roth had misappropriated his name and image in order to sell magazines. Essentially, Joyce couldn’t object to Roth reprinting the text of Ulysses (expurgated or otherwise), but could try to refuse him the right to put Joyce’s name on the cover.</p>

<p>Roth was fighting a lot of legal battles at the time, and ultimately settled before the case was decided on its merits. It seems somewhat doubtful Joyce could’ve won, not least because the statute he sued under had a specific exemption for putting authors’ names on books. So: Joyce used a flimsy privacy claim to prevent the dissemination by a bad actor ((Well, some people really didn’t like Roth. Neither Spoo nor Ezra Pound nor this author are willing to go very far in demonizing him.)) of an objectionable work.</p>

<p>Compare that to <em>Garcia v. Google</em>, wherein Cindy Lee Garcia is using an <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20140313/01051626558/google-points-out-that-even-copyright-office-thinks-judge-kozinskis-innocence-muslims-ruling-is-wrong.shtml">(extremely)</a> flimsy copyright claim towards the same ends. She’s trying to prevent the dissemination by a bad actor, here <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nakoula_Basseley_Nakoula">Nakoula Basseley Nakoula</a>, of an objectionable work, “Innocence of Muslims.” Joyce’s was being tricky with privacy law in order to enforce a copyright concern; Garcia is doing the same with copyright law to enforce a privacy concern.</p>

<p>In both cases, it’s likely that many observers identify and sympathize with the plaintiff—but that doesn’t grant license to contort the law to serve a good ends. Had Joyce won outright, the precedent could have had all sorts of unintended consequences: it could have jeopardized other publishers of the public domain, created incentives for improper attribution, and had chilling effects on literary criticism. The same applies for Garcia, should the Ninth Circuit’s position remain in place.</p>

<p>“Without Copyrights,” like 2009’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/109147551">“Piracy” by Adrian Johns</a>, is a pretty incredible reminder of how closely current debates around tech policy—copyright, free speech, privacy, and more—mirror those from a century or more ago.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="garcia v. google" /><category term="james joyce" /><category term="piracy" /><category term="robert spoo" /><category term="samuel roth" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve just finished reading Robert Spoo’s book “Without Copyrights,” an academic look at the history of American publishing in the 19th and early 20th centuries, when American copyright first did not apply at all to works first published abroad, and later applied only with strict manufacturing and notice requirements. The first half of the book documents the interesting practice of copyright-like trade courtesy among publishers, through which those businesses kept the costs of books relatively stable, paid authors through voluntary payments, and internally punished defectors from the system.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The pirate drawings of 1922</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The pirate drawings of 1922" /><published>2013-05-30T20:43:52-04:00</published><updated>2013-05-30T20:43:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I posted a <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/ship-in-a-bottle/">ship in a bottle</a> from the <a href="http://archive.org/details/pirates00john">1922 book “Pirates,”</a> and today I’ve had a chance to clean up a few more images, including most of the actual named pirates described in the book. The book seems to be scanned on a setting for text, and so the pictures require just a little bit of correction and cleaning. I’m pretty happy with the way these images turned out. Of course, since the book was released in 1922, all of these are in the public domain. So if you need a pirate drawing, go ahead.</p>

<style type="text/css">
			#gallery-8 {
				margin: auto;
			}
			#gallery-8 .gallery-item {
				float: left;
				margin-top: 10px;
				text-align: center;
				width: 25%;
			}
			#gallery-8 img {
				border: 2px solid #cfcfcf;
			}
			#gallery-8 .gallery-caption {
				margin-left: 0;
			}
			/* see gallery_shortcode() in wp-includes/media.php */
		</style>

<div class="gallery galleryid-1203 gallery-columns-4 gallery-size-thumbnail" id="gallery-8"><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon portrait"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/majorstedebonnet-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/majorstedebonnet/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1209"> Major Stede Bonnet </dd></dl><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon portrait"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/captwilliamkid-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/captwilliamkid/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1208"> Captain William Kid </dd></dl><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon portrait"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/captavery-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/captavery/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1204"> Captain Avery </dd></dl><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon portrait"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/captjohngow-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/captjohngow/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1205"> Captain John Gow </dd></dl>  
<dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon portrait"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/captjohnrackham-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/captjohnrackham/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1206"> Captain John Rackham </dd></dl><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon portrait"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/captteach-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/captteach/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1207"> Captain Teach </dd></dl><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon landscape"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/pirateship-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/pirateship/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1210"> A pirate ship at sea </dd></dl><dl class="gallery-item"> <dt class="gallery-icon landscape"> [![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/shipinabottle1-150x150.png)](https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/05/the-pirate-drawings-of-1922/shipinabottle-2/) </dt> <dd class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-8-1211"> Ship in a bottle </dd></dl>  
 </div>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="claud lovat fraser" /><category term="piracy" /><category term="pirates" /><category term="public domain" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday I posted a ship in a bottle from the 1922 book “Pirates,” and today I’ve had a chance to clean up a few more images, including most of the actual named pirates described in the book. The book seems to be scanned on a setting for text, and so the pictures require just a little bit of correction and cleaning. I’m pretty happy with the way these images turned out. Of course, since the book was released in 1922, all of these are in the public domain. So if you need a pirate drawing, go ahead.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting the present in Cory Doctorow’s “Pirate Cinema”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting the present in Cory Doctorow’s “Pirate Cinema”" /><published>2013-02-04T11:00:13-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-04T11:00:13-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema/"><![CDATA[<p>Cory Doctorow is coming through town again, this time on his tour for <cite>Homeland</cite>, the sequel to his excellent young adult novel <cite>Little Brother</cite>. Cory likes to talk about how his fiction “predicts the present”: taking the bits of future that are already here, just not yet evenly distributed, and applying them more widely. It’s a neat trick that makes his sci-fi seem eerily prescient, and I know <cite>Little Brother</cite> has been boosted by supporters of Occupy who saw much of their story foretold in his writing.</p>

<p>In another of Cory’s young adult books, the recent <a href="http://craphound.com/pc/about/"><cite>Pirate Cinema</cite></a>, much of the plot focuses on draconian copyright enforcement systems and backlash. Of course, there’s a rich history to pull from: the battles over SOPA and ACTA were just the latest in a long narrative that Cory has been engaged with for years. His “Theft of Intellectual Property Bill (TIP)” might have been fiction, but it’s a logical extension of what we’ve already seen.</p>

<p>Combine predicting the present with some old-fashioned coincidence, and things start to get spooky. Take Cory’s “Jimmy Preston,” who in <cite>Pirate Cinema</cite> gets a then-unprecedented five-year prison term for sharing music files. Cory writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But he’d collected 450,000 songs on his hard drive through endless, tedious, tireless hours of downloading. From what anyone could tell, he didn’t even listen to them: he just liked cataloging them, correcting their metadata, organizing them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Compare that to the real-life Jeremiah Perkins, who just a few months after <cite>Pirate Cinema</cite>‘s release was <a href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2013/01/record-filing-sharing-term/">also sentenced to five years for filesharing</a>. According to a report prepared on behalf ot the movie studios, his group iMAGINE was well-known for <a href="http://torrentfreak.com/imagine-bittorrent-piracy-group-sysop-jailed-40-months-121130/">“their consistently good quality of audio captures” and “their high volume of releases”</a>.</p>

<p>I hope that Jeremiah Perkins doesn’t face the same ultimate fate as Cory’s Jimmy Preston, who didn’t do well in prison. Even more importantly, I hope we don’t see more jailtime for filesharers.</p>

<p>When the book came out, I saw at least one review that said the action was too over-the-top, the law too excessive, the studio groups too vindictive to possibly reflect reality. Detractors should take note: when the book came out, the mainstream probably wouldn’t believe a five-year sentence for file-sharing. Then it happened. Cory’s good at predicting the present.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cory doctorow" /><category term="file sharing" /><category term="imagine" /><category term="piracy" /><category term="pirate cinema" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cory Doctorow is coming through town again, this time on his tour for Homeland, the sequel to his excellent young adult novel Little Brother. Cory likes to talk about how his fiction “predicts the present”: taking the bits of future that are already here, just not yet evenly distributed, and applying them more widely. It’s a neat trick that makes his sci-fi seem eerily prescient, and I know Little Brother has been boosted by supporters of Occupy who saw much of their story foretold in his writing.]]></summary></entry></feed>