<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/politics.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:33:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/politics.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">My 2012 San Francisco ballot</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/2012-san-francisco-ballot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My 2012 San Francisco ballot" /><published>2012-11-04T23:52:17-05:00</published><updated>2012-11-04T23:52:17-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/2012-san-francisco-ballot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/11/2012-san-francisco-ballot/"><![CDATA[<p>On Tuesday, I’ll be voting in person for the first time in my native California. I’ve only ever voted by mail before. (I voted from Berlin in the 2008 presidential election, and had a charming exchange in broken German with the women working at the post office. They, like nearly all of Germany, were following the election as big Obama fans, so I had little trouble convincing them of the significance of the letter I was handing off.)</p>

<p>I’m taking more care this year to get informed on each of the ballot initiatives for California and San Francisco, and to make good decisions on them. I’ve read most of the information in the official packet on these choices, and also consulted the <a href="https://www.aclunc.org/legislation/ca_propositions/index.shtml">ACLU Northern California</a> recommendations, the <a href="http://www.sfgate.com/propositions/">SF Gate endorsements</a>, the <a href="http://www.sfbg.com/2012/10/03/endorsements-2012-san-francisco-propositions?page=0,0">SF Bay Guardian endorsements</a>, this column from <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2012/10/california-propositions-november-2012">Kevin Drum at Mother Jones</a>, and a few others.</p>

<p>Here’s where I stand for now; I’m putting this up here as much as a record for me as for anybody else, but they’re subject to change before election day. If you think I’m making a terrible mistake, let me know.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Yes on Prop 30 — both 30 and 38 address spending on education and prevent a $5 billion cut to public schools, but 30 is the better proposal.</li>
  <li>No on Prop 31 — from most accounts, a ballot initiative is the wrong place to make this sort of budget policy.</li>
  <li>No on Prop 32 — this is one of those zombie initiatives that keep coming back, and would weaken the political power of unions in favor of corporations.</li>
  <li>No on Prop 33 — I haven’t seen any good evidence this would help anybody but the insurance company whose CEO has pushed it onto the ballot.</li>
  <li>Yes on Prop 34 — repeals the death penalty in CA. This one’s a very easy call for me to make: even if you’re a supporter of the death penalty in general, which I’m not, it certainly isn’t working in California.</li>
  <li>No on Prop 35 — this one’s ostensibly about sex trafficking, but overreaches in a lot of places. <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/11/eff-urges-no-vote-california-proposition-35">EFF urges opposition, too</a>.</li>
  <li>Yes on Prop 36 — three strikes doesn’t work, and causes incredible damage in California. This initiative helps restore some of the original intent of the law.</li>
  <li>Yes on Prop 37 — a bit of a tough call, as consensus seems to be that a ballot initiative is not exactly the right way to make this proposal law, and the loose language could cause problems. Mother Jones is split, too, with <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/tom-philpott/2012/10/why-i-disagree-kevin-drum-californias-gmo-labeling-proposition">another writer opposing Kevin Drum’s position</a>. But Monsanto has spent a lot of money trying to kill this, and that makes me think there must be something to it.</li>
  <li><strong>UPDATE:</strong> No on Prop 38 — originally I thought it’d be fine if both 30 and 38 passed, but I’ve read a little more about <a href="http://www.kcet.org/news/ballotbrief/ballot-measures/prop-30-prop-38-both-pass-california.html">how the two would interact</a> — namely, that the one with the larger majority gets enforced while the other one gets scrapped at worst or put in place piecemeal at best — and I’ve decided to vote against this one. I really hope 30 passes, though.</li>
  <li>Yes on Prop 39 — closes a tax loophole that is not politically viable to address through the legislature. I’d rather these sorts of things weren’t addressed through ballot initiatives, but as long as it’s here…</li>
  <li>Yes on Prop 40</li>
</ul>

<p>With regard to San Francisco measures: there appears to be a bit more constraint with how these end up on the ballot. After consulting a few sources, it looks like the way to vote is yes to all <em>except</em> Measure F. That one, though proposed by well-meaning environmentalists, would commit the city to spending $8 million evaluating an ultimately unworkable plan to drain the Hetch Hetchy Reservoir.</p>

<p>Of particular interest is Measure G, which declares as City policy that corporations should not have the same constitutional rights as human beings. Although it’s not binding, and actual laws to the same effect would get very complicated very fast, I think the general principle is a nice one for the city to endorse.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="california" /><category term="politics" /><category term="san francisco" /><category term="voting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Tuesday, I’ll be voting in person for the first time in my native California. I’ve only ever voted by mail before. (I voted from Berlin in the 2008 presidential election, and had a charming exchange in broken German with the women working at the post office. They, like nearly all of Germany, were following the election as big Obama fans, so I had little trouble convincing them of the significance of the letter I was handing off.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Women’s suffrage and the world’s oldest person</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/womens-suffrage-and-the-worlds-oldest-person/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women’s suffrage and the world’s oldest person" /><published>2012-08-29T12:30:43-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-29T12:30:43-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/womens-suffrage-and-the-worlds-oldest-person</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/womens-suffrage-and-the-worlds-oldest-person/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nineteenth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">Nineteenth Amendment to the US Constitution</a>, which granted women the right to vote, was ratified 92 years ago this month. ((It had been introduced 41 years earlier by Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton, but sometimes it takes a few decades to move the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overton_window">Overton window</a> towards sanity.))</p>

<p>Less than a century is certainly short enough that some women who are alive today were born without the right to vote. But, then, they would’ve been too young to vote at the time anyway. Is there still a woman alive today who could have been denied a vote in a presidential election on the basis of her gender? ((Of course, considering the shocking war on women being waged by the current GOP, there must be plenty of examples of disenfranchisement on the basis of gender. In this post I’m just looking at the timing of the Nineteenth Amendment.))</p>

<p>As it turns out, the answer to that question seems to be yes. The world’s oldest living person happens to be an American woman named Besse Cooper, and <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2012/08/worlds-oldest-person-besse-cooper-turns-116/">she celebrated her 116th birthday this weekend</a>. She was born in 1896 in Sullivan, Tennessee, but moved to Monroe, Georgia during World War I. That means she would have been living in Georgia when she turned 21 on August 26, 1917. (I’m going with 21 instead of 18, because that was the national voting age before the passage of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty-sixth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">Twenty-sixth Amendment in 1971</a>.)</p>

<p>1918 was a Senate election year, and Ms. Cooper would have been denied the right to vote in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate_elections,_1918">that race</a>. Incumbent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_W._Hardwick">Thomas Hardwick</a> lost in the Democratic primary, but two years later was elected governor. One of his most notable acts, incidentally, was appointing the first woman to serve in the Senate, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rebecca_Latimer_Felton">Rebecca Latimer Felton</a>. Her appointment was basically ceremonial — she only served for one day — but to date she’s still Georgia’s only female Senator.</p>

<p>Anyway, cut to two years later and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_1920">the first presidential election since Ms. Cooper’s 21st birthday</a>. Because of the recent ratification, women all over the country were set to vote for the president for the first time. Georgia, however, was not only the first state to reject the amendment, but also continued to resist it even after its ratification. In particular, the legislature <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=rIoEAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA133&amp;lpg=PA133&amp;dq=women+georgia+1920+election+presidential&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Wt-vhlwpa1&amp;sig=BuDzrLZcNu4UcUR-LjGPHeSNJfs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Z4E8UOaYLs7ciQKgyIHYDg&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=women%20georgia%201920%20election%20presidential&amp;f=false">refused to allow women to vote at the polling station</a> because they had failed to register in April and May of that year, before they were legally allowed to do so. ((This point is actually a bit contentious. The source I link to seems credible, but I’d like to hear from people who know more about this.)) Women in Georgia apparently weren’t allowed to vote until the 1922 mid-term election, and the state didn’t formally ratify the amendment until 1970.</p>

<p>Georgia went to James M. Cox, but Warren Harding won the national vote in a landslide. Four years later, Ms. Cooper may have been able to vote for the president after being denied the first time. Ninety-two years later, she may be the only living woman in the country to have had that experience.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="equality" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Nineteenth Amendment to the US Constitution, which granted women the right to vote, was ratified 92 years ago this month. ((It had been introduced 41 years earlier by Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton, but sometimes it takes a few decades to move the Overton window towards sanity.))]]></summary></entry></feed>