<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/privacy.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:42:42-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/privacy.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets: my correct opinion</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2018/08/twitter-should-allow-users-to-hide-old-tweets-my-correct-opinion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets: my correct opinion" /><published>2018-08-05T15:29:02-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T15:29:02-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2018/08/twitter-should-allow-users-to-hide-old-tweets-my-correct-opinion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2018/08/twitter-should-allow-users-to-hide-old-tweets-my-correct-opinion/"><![CDATA[<p>Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets so that they are only visible to that user, and selectively “un-hide” individual tweets from that collection so that they once again become available at their original URL, in quote tweets and threads, and in sites where they are embedded around the web.</p>

<p>The need for a mechanism to remove old tweets is very clear and becoming abundantly moreso with <a href="https://www.mediamatters.org/blog/2018/07/27/In-their-own-words-the-online-far-rights-motive-to-dig-up-liberal-figures-old-tweets-reven/220827">every rightwing campaign trawling for old statements to weaponize</a> by taking out of context. Numerous guides have been written about how and why to delete your tweets, and it’s beyond the scope of the argument I’m making today. Many of these guides, too, address the emotional difficulty of actually pulling the trigger and wiping an archive—in many cases spanning a decade or so of interaction.</p>

<p>One of the best encapsulations of this problem (and that solution) is John Herrman’s Awl 2015 piece <a href="https://www.theawl.com/2015/08/time-is-a-privacy-setting/">“Time Is a Privacy Setting.”</a> Even just the phrase in the headline is an important contribution, and gets at why simple dichotomies of “public” and “private” are so unsatisfying. A lot more goes into our understanding of privacy than a binary toggle, and time is certainly a factor.</p>

<p>And just as interesting, to me, is something Herrman said this week, in a tweet thread that began with his a link to that now three-year-old essay: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180805181404/https:/twitter.com/jwherrman/status/1024402382615142405">“You thought you were talking, but you were writing.”</a> It’s true! Twitter has managed, for many people, to clear out a barrier that can otherwise be insurmountable, letting people be comfortable writing down their thoughts and conversations. Something the tweet-deleters flirt with, but never seem to quite put their finger on, is that writing (as opposed to talking) has some real advantages in addition to the drawbacks.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>This observation is obviously not new to Twitter. My father, a writer, has always exhorted me to keep a journal or a diary, though I’ve never really been able to. One real value of Twitter, for me, has been breaking through that hesitation by setting the threshold of participation so incredibly low that I can just, y’know, write. It’d be better to keep a journal or to blog, but in many cases tweets are good enough.</p>

<p>Over the decade that I’ve been on Twitter, I’ve gone through periods of prolific writing and total dry spells. I’ve maintained this blog regularly at times, and at others it’s sat dormant for months. And the thing is, I frequently refer to and read the old entries for time periods where they exist! Human memory is fickle and fragile, and it is genuinely interesting and educational for me to look back on old writing and see the germs of ideas that later grew into real passions. Looking up old tweets isn’t quite as good, but it fills in the gaps.</p>

<p>Beyond just lowering the threshold to producing such writing, Twitter did some important things to make online writing even more valuable. Search, the villain in recent sagas, is a powerful tool when used for good. Joanne McNeil recently raised a use case I love:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">One of my favorite things things to do on twitter is search my friends’ old tweets for their reactions over the years to whatever film or book I just finished</p>&mdash; joanne mcneil (@jomc) <a href="https://twitter.com/jomc/status/1025085686947430401?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 2, 2018</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>I do that too! Yes, it’d be great if all my friends blogged about every movie they watched or book they read (and I had a good way of finding those posts when they became relevant to me), but this is a decent runner-up. If you want, too, you can see first interactions with people who later became important to you, or <a href="https://waxy.org/2015/12/tracking_the_trump_is_a_comment_section_running_for_president_joke/">all the people who’ve made a joke</a> you just thought of, or people discussing an article you’ve just read, and Twitter (helpfully, in this case) collapses the time gap between you and those people.</p>

<p>Beyond that, Twitter puts a time stamp and a URL on each of these things. In recent years it even preserves the semantics of threads. I don’t want to downplay the very real harm these attributes can cause, but it’s also true that in some situations they provide a ton of value.</p>

<p>Which brings us back to tweet deletion and why it is emotionally difficult for people to do. For better or for worse, this archive we’ve created of our own writing is valuable, and deleting tweets is permanent. (<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/im-deleting-all-my-old-tweets/">Emily Dreyfuss’ article at Wired</a> does an especially good job at grappling with it.) Every guide I’ve read to deleting tweets walks through the process of creating an “archive,” but even doing so misses some of these benefits of keeping old tweets online.</p>

<p>Archiving-then-deleting may preserve a copy for you, but it permanently rips each tweet out of its context in threads, at a URL, within quote tweets, embedded in articles, and in the Search index.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Maybe you want to do all those things, and you should have the power to do so! But with a corpus of tens of thousands of tweets, in many cases, it is overwhelming to permanently make that decision for everything all at once.</p>

<p>(Side note: that permanence is in large part a result of Twitter’s centralization. Under a more decentralized model,<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> where we controlled our own domains, you could maybe just rebuild your database from a backup and point all the right URLs to all the right content. There’s pros and cons to such centralization—and in particular, people seem to love the guarantee that the archive hasn’t been tampered with—but in any case that’s the situation we’re in and what can you do.)</p>

<p>So here’s the solution, referred to up top. Twitter should give users a new option to “hide” old tweets, which would look to every other user like deletion, but which would be a reversible operation. Your hidden tweets should still appear in your searches and views of old threads, but greyed out to indicate they’re not otherwise available. And—and this is probably the hardest part—Twitter should introduce a per-tweet configurability for these settings.</p>

<p>That’s the kicker. Individual tweets could be deleted (fully gone), hidden (just for you), private (for your followers, no retweets), or public. That would be a big change! But it’s important.</p>

<p>(Another side note: when I posted this opinion on Twitter, I got a few responses that such an option should not be available for public figures or politicians or what-have-you. I tend to think that we should not rely on Twitter to preserve these public records, and that their introduction of a feature that has real benefits to real users shouldn’t be hindered by the possible exploitation by shifty officials. And just as with <a href="https://theconversation.com/donald-trumps-tweets-are-now-presidential-records-71973">deleting tweets</a> or <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/23/business/media/trump-twitter-block.html">blocking critics</a>, the behavior can be barred without Twitter needing to intervene.)</p>

<p>Twitter the company has mismanaged Twitter the product in a dozen different ways, and its policies on speech, censorship, harassment, and abuse have often been incoherent. It’s also provided an invaluable platform for many of my favorite writers and thinkers, and done so in a way that is reasonably consistent with the technology of the web.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> Giving users more tools—in this case a new privacy setting with more granularity—is the right next step in overcoming the former without diminishing the latter.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>By definition, most of the articles about deleting tweets are written by writers. Writers, again by definition, tend to write more stuff down. So maybe the benefits of having a place to write stuff down if you otherwise wouldn’t isn’t quite as clear to them. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Beyond that, there’s no easy way to present your archive on your own terms to anybody but yourself, a <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2017/04/building-mastodon-frozen/">feature I’ve argued for in other contexts</a>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Check out <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a>. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Two good things that stand out: canonical URLs for every tweet, and the fact that unavailable embedded tweets degrade gracefully into text. On the other hand, the normalization and ubiquitous use of a URL shortener sucks. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="mastodon" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="twitter" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets so that they are only visible to that user, and selectively “un-hide” individual tweets from that collection so that they once again become available at their original URL, in quote tweets and threads, and in sites where they are embedded around the web.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amazon backdoor exposed wishlist mailing addresses</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/01/earlier-amazon-backdoor-exposed-wishlist-mailing-addresses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon backdoor exposed wishlist mailing addresses" /><published>2016-01-24T23:15:22-05:00</published><updated>2016-01-24T23:15:22-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/01/earlier-amazon-backdoor-exposed-wishlist-mailing-addresses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2016/01/earlier-amazon-backdoor-exposed-wishlist-mailing-addresses/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s an article circulating right now about how <a href="https://medium.com/@espringe/amazon-s-customer-service-backdoor-be375b3428c4#.hqxfxuajw">Amazon customer service can be exploited to reveal targeted mailing addresses</a>. I discovered and reported a similar vulnerability in December of 2014, which was reported to me as fixed in May of 2015. I haven’t publicly documented that process until now.</p>

<p>The vulnerability I discovered relates to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/registry/search">Amazon wishlists</a>. Users can associate wishlists with a private address, so that people can buy and ship them gifts without having the recipient’s private information. That address should be kept confidential throughout the entire process, but I found that third party shippers—routinely used for Amazon sites outside of the United States—would sometimes include it in confirmation emails.</p>

<p>In particular: I used Amazon.ca to send a book to a friend, and Canada Post delivered her full address to me in an email. In this exchange, Amazon’s confirmation email properly showed my friend’s address as redacted, but Canada Post revealed it in its entirety.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screenshot_2016-01-24_19-57-19.png" alt="Amazon confirmation" /></p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/canada-post-confirmation.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>That would be unacceptable in any circumstance. But it’s all the worse because some of the people who use Amazon wishlists are especially vulnerable to targeted harassment. The service is popular, for instance, <a href="http://www.dailydot.com/lifestyle/amazon-sex-worker-wish-lists/">among camgirls and sex workers accepting gifts</a>. I’ve also seen wishlists from Twitter microcelebrities, who get occasional threats and unwanted creepy overtures, as well as wishlists from women who are trying to get some support after leaving an abusive domestic situation. For many of these people, a revealed address can be devastating.</p>

<p>I contacted <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html/ref=hp_left_sib?ie=UTF8&amp;nodeId=201182150">Amazon Security</a> via email, ((They make a PGP key available, but <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=200724850">only distribute it over unauthenticated HTTP</a>. All the more reason Amazon should switch to entirely HTTPS.)) and got a confirmation number and a response from a human that it had been assigned to somebody. The fix, introduced in May, seems to simply removed the second confirmation email direct from Canada Post.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screenshot_2016-01-24_20-05-52.png" alt="My email to Amazon Security" /></p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screenshot_2016-01-24_20-06-23.png" alt="Amazon Security fix" /></p>

<p>Although the five month window to fix this situation seemed too long to me, I didn’t want to go public until it had been addressed. An attacker who knew about this vulnerability could easily exploit it for the cost of the cheapest item on a particular wishlist, and the only fix a user could make was removing their address entirely.</p>

<p>Given that particular combination—easy, cheap exploitation, and no alternative path to security—it seemed irresponsible in this case to disclose the problem publicly. Others may disagree.</p>

<p>This isn’t the first time wishlists have inadvertently leaked address data—it happened <a href="http://wishlistexposed.blogspot.com/">at least once before in 2011</a>. Nor do I know for sure that the fix has been applied worldwide, as I only tested in Canada. Unfortunately, <a href="https://ssd.eff.org/en/module/introduction-threat-modeling">for people who could face threats if their address were revealed</a>, Amazon seems like a dangerous service to share it with.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="amazon" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s an article circulating right now about how Amazon customer service can be exploited to reveal targeted mailing addresses. I discovered and reported a similar vulnerability in December of 2014, which was reported to me as fixed in May of 2015. I haven’t publicly documented that process until now.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An email signature to encourage encryption use</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/08/email-signature-nudge-encryption-use/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An email signature to encourage encryption use" /><published>2014-08-10T20:38:38-04:00</published><updated>2014-08-10T20:38:38-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/08/email-signature-nudge-encryption-use</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/08/email-signature-nudge-encryption-use/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/pgp.png" alt="" />A great way to encourage more ubiquitous email encryption is to let people you’re emailing know that you’re equipped to use it, and that they can be too.</p>

<p>Some people use PGP signatures for that purpose, but inline signatures can be off-putting to people who don’t know what they are, and attachments can be similarly confusing. (Not to mention that, <a href="https://xkcd.com/1181/">as XKCD notes</a>, the security benefits are pretty slim.)</p>

<p>A one-line addition to an email signature is a good compromise. I propose the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I prefer to use encrypted email. My public key fingerprint is 4FF3 AA1B D29E 1638 32DE C765 9433 5F88 9A36 7709. Learn how to encrypt your email with <a href="https://emailselfdefense.fsf.org/en/">the Email Self Defense guide</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In my case, because I’ve got my key available on an HTTPS site, I’d probably <a href="https://www.eff.org/files/2013/11/03/parkerkey.txt">link to it directly</a> as well.</p>

<p>This system isn’t perfect, and in particular is not a very secure way to distribute your fingerprint. But it could be a good nudge to people who might be considering learning about email encryption while flagging you as somebody who might be able to help, and especially if you post to publicly archived mailing lists, it’s a way of getting your fingerprint tied to your emails in lots of places.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="crypto" /><category term="encryption" /><category term="pgp" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A great way to encourage more ubiquitous email encryption is to let people you’re emailing know that you’re equipped to use it, and that they can be too.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Illegal spying below: my trip over Utah</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/06/illegal-spying-below-my-trip-over-utah/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Illegal spying below: my trip over Utah" /><published>2014-06-29T01:09:04-04:00</published><updated>2014-06-29T01:09:04-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/06/illegal-spying-below-my-trip-over-utah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/06/illegal-spying-below-my-trip-over-utah/"><![CDATA[<p>I flew in an airship over the NSA’s Utah data center yesterday, as part of a joint action organized by Greenpeace and EFF. It was really a remarkable experience, and we were lucky enough to get it covered by a pretty wide range of media. Here’s a small sample:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The Guardian: <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jun/27/surveillance-activists-launch-135ft-airship-nsa">‘Illegal spying below’: activists launch airship in protest at NSA surveillance</a></li>
  <li>Wired: <a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/06/protestors-launch-a-135-foot-blimp-over-the-nsas-utah-data-center/">Protestors Launch a 135-Foot Blimp Over the NSA’s Utah Data Center</a></li>
  <li>NBC News: <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/storyline/nsa-snooping/illegal-spying-below-blimp-flies-over-nsa-utah-data-center-n142916">“Illegal Spying Below”: Blimp Flies Over NSA Utah Data Center in Protest</a></li>
  <li>Huffington Post: <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/06/27/blimp-buzzes-nsa-data-cen_n_5538298.html">Blimp Buzzes NSA Data Center In Anti-Surveillance Protest</a></li>
  <li>CNET: <a href="http://www.cnet.com/news/nsa-spying-protest-takes-to-the-skies-in-utah/">NSA spying protest takes to the skies in Utah</a></li>
  <li>Newsweek: <a href="http://www.newsweek.com/activists-fly-airship-over-nsas-data-center-256503">Activists Fly Airship over the NSA’s Data Center</a></li>
  <li>Ars Technica: <a href="http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2014/06/airship-flies-above-nsa-data-center-decries-illegal-spying-below/">Airship flies above NSA data center, decries “Illegal Spying Below”</a></li>
  <li>Boing Boing: <a href="http://boingboing.net/2014/06/27/anti-surveillance-protesters-f.html">Anti-surveillance protesters fly internet freedom blimp over NSA facility in Utah</a></li>
  <li>The Salt Lake Tribune: <a href="http://www.sltrib.com/sltrib/news/58123092-78/twitter-center-eff-blimp.html.csp">Activists fly blimp over Utah’s NSA center</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The airship itself looked pretty incredible. <a href="https://www.eff.org/press/releases/diverse-groups-fly-airship-over-nsas-utah-data-center-protest-illegal-internet-spying">EFF has more photos taken from the helicopter</a>, but here’s one, credit to Greenpeace:</p>

<p><a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/8.14.68_utah_airship_flight.2072.jpg"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/8.14.68_utah_airship_flight.2072.jpg" alt="Utah Airship Flight" /></a></p>

<p>I also got some photos from in the airship itself. The obligatory selfie with me and Sim, the pilot for Greenpeace:</p>

<p><a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/BrJDuZaCUAMYCf_.jpg"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/BrJDuZaCUAMYCf_.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>And of course some of the data center itself (here in the background):</p>

<p><a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/BrJV3_ZCcAAUCbd.jpg"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/BrJV3_ZCcAAUCbd.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>More to come, both in terms of story and images. Follow the EFF blog to keep up!</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="activism" /><category term="airship" /><category term="greenpeace" /><category term="nsa" /><category term="pictures" /><category term="privacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I flew in an airship over the NSA’s Utah data center yesterday, as part of a joint action organized by Greenpeace and EFF. It was really a remarkable experience, and we were lucky enough to get it covered by a pretty wide range of media. Here’s a small sample:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Androids Dream of Electric Free Speech?</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/do-androids-dream-of-electric-free-speech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Androids Dream of Electric Free Speech?" /><published>2014-05-23T03:32:39-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-23T03:32:39-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/do-androids-dream-of-electric-free-speech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/05/do-androids-dream-of-electric-free-speech/"><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2439423">new paper called “Do Androids Dream of Electric Free Speech?”</a> argues that legal scholars could benefit from looking more to science fiction works when writing about concepts like copyright, censorship, and privacy. It’s an interesting paper, and spends time going into some theories of why sci-fi is relevant as well as examining the issues that the genre explores. From the article:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That said, all legal scholarship does not need to uniform, and taking some risks by creating plausible (even if not probable) hypothetical examples based on the visions of science fiction authors offers the opportunity to enhance the value of legal scholarship to the field of media and communications law. We researchers are in a position to answer questions that may not be as practical or necessary for judges and legislators today, but may very well be considered by them in the future if and when some of the projections become reality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I had a chance to speak with the author, Daxton “Chip” Stewart, after writing about my blog post on <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2014/04/where-is-the-copyright-maximalist-dystopian-sci-fi/">the lack of copyright maximalist dystopian sci-fi</a> on Twitter. I was surprised and happy to see that he ended up citing that blog post and some of the works discussed in it, as well as a <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema/">post I wrote about Cory Doctorow’s <em>Pirate Cinema</em></a>. But I’d have enjoyed the paper even without the citations!</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="free speech" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="sci-fi" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new paper called “Do Androids Dream of Electric Free Speech?” argues that legal scholars could benefit from looking more to science fiction works when writing about concepts like copyright, censorship, and privacy. It’s an interesting paper, and spends time going into some theories of why sci-fi is relevant as well as examining the issues that the genre explores. From the article:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Supreme Court’s real technology problem</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/the-supreme-courts-real-technology-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Supreme Court’s real technology problem" /><published>2014-04-30T20:24:21-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-30T20:24:21-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/the-supreme-courts-real-technology-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/the-supreme-courts-real-technology-problem/"><![CDATA[<p>I spent a lot of the last week shaking my head at the commentary on the Supreme Court and its (lack of) technical expertise. Much of the criticism came in response to the oral arguments in <em>Aereo</em>, and broke down in two areas: it either <a href="http://sarahjeong.net/2014/04/22/supreme-court-justices-are-not-good-with-computers/">misunderstood the nature of Supreme Court oral arguments and their transcripts</a>, or <a href="http://sarahjeong.net/2014/04/23/scotus-is-bad-at-computers-part-2/">mistook familiarity with a handful of Silicon Valley products with actual tech savviness</a>.</p>

<p>But in a series of cases yesterday about law enforcement searches of cell phones, we caught a glimpse of the Supreme Court’s real technology problem. Here’s what it comes down to: it’s not essential that the Court knows specifics about how technology itself works—and as Timothy Lee argues, that <a href="http://www.vox.com/2014/4/23/5644154/the-supreme-courts-technical-cluelessness-makes-them-better-justices">might even tempt them to make technology-based decisions that don’t generalize well</a>. However, it <em>is</em> essential that the Court understands how people use technology, especially in areas where they’re trying to elaborate a standard of what expectations are “reasonable.”</p>

<p>So when Chief Justice Roberts suggests that <a href="https://twitter.com/xor/status/461257425517961216">a person carrying two cell phones might reasonably be suspected of dealing drugs</a>, that raises major red flags. Not because of any special facts about how cell phones work, but because (for example) at least half of the lawyers in the Supreme Court Bar brought two cell phones with them to the courthouse that day. Should those attorneys (along with the many, many other people who carry multiple devices) reasonably expect less privacy because the Chief Justice is out of touch with that fact?</p>

<p>Contrast that with <a href="https://twitter.com/xor/status/461239651043250179">Justice Kagan’s point about storage location in the same argument</a>. Justice Kagan suggested, correctly, that people don’t always know what is stored on their device and what is stored “in the cloud.” The actual answer to that question should be immaterial; the point is that it’s absurd for a person’s privacy interest to hinge on which hard drive private data is stored on. ((That speaks to a need to revisit the sort-of ridiculous third-party doctrine, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2012/01/23/a-supreme-court-justices-radical-proposal-regarding-the-privacy-of-your-google-searches-facebook-account-phone-records/">which Justice Sotomayor has suggested</a>, but one battle at a time.)) Instead, the important fact here, which Justice Kagan recognizes, is that the distinction between local and cloud storage just doesn’t matter to many people, and so it can’t be the basis of a reasonable-expectation-of-privacy test.</p>

<p>If you’re feeling less generous, you might take Justice Kagan’s point as evidence that she herself doesn’t know where her files are stored. And in fact, that’s probably true—but it’s not important. You don’t actually need to know much about filesystems and remote storage to know that it’s a bad idea for the law to treat it differently.</p>

<p>That’s not to say that technical implementation details are never relevant. Relevant details, though, should (and almost always do) get addressed in the briefs, long before the oral argument takes place. They don’t usually read like software manuals, either: they’re often rich with analogies to help explain not just how the tech works, but what body of law should apply.</p>

<p>What can’t really be explained in a brief, though, is a community’s relationship with a technology. You can get at parts of it, citing authorities like surveys and expert witnesses, but a real feeling for what people expect from their software and devices is something that has to be observed. If the nine justices on the Supreme Court can’t bring that knowledge to the arguments, the public suffers greatly. Again, Justice Kagan seems to recognize this fact when she says of cell phones:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They’re computers. They have as much computing capacity as ­­ as laptops did five years ago. And ­­ and everybody under a certain age, let’s say under 40, has everything on them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Justice Kagan is not under 40, and might not have everything stored on a phone (or on an online service accessible through her phone). But that quote shows me that she at least knows where other people’s expectations are different. Chief Justice Roberts’s questions show me exactly the opposite.</p>

<p>The justices live an unusual and sheltered life: they have no concerns about job security, and spend much of their time grappling with abstract questions that have profound effects on this country’s law. But if they fail to recognize where their assumptions about society and technology break from the norm—or indeed, where they are making assumptions in the first place—we’re all in trouble.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="aereo" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="supreme court" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I spent a lot of the last week shaking my head at the commentary on the Supreme Court and its (lack of) technical expertise. Much of the criticism came in response to the oral arguments in Aereo, and broke down in two areas: it either misunderstood the nature of Supreme Court oral arguments and their transcripts, or mistook familiarity with a handful of Silicon Valley products with actual tech savviness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tuesday: Oakland City Hall to fight the Domain Awareness Center</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/11/tuesday-oakland-city-hall-to-fight-the-domain-awareness-center/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tuesday: Oakland City Hall to fight the Domain Awareness Center" /><published>2013-11-17T18:09:02-05:00</published><updated>2013-11-17T18:09:02-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/11/tuesday-oakland-city-hall-to-fight-the-domain-awareness-center</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/11/tuesday-oakland-city-hall-to-fight-the-domain-awareness-center/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://oaklandwiki.org/DAC"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/stopdac.png" alt="stopdac" /></a></p>

<p>This Tuesday, November 19, <a href="https://www.indybay.org/newsitems/2013/11/14/18746384.php">Oakland City Council will hear comments</a> on its plan to spend $7 million of DHS money on <a href="http://oaklandwiki.org/DAC">a “Domain Awareness Center”</a> that would aggregate surveillance data from many different channels about the residents of Oakland. The New York Times wrote up <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/14/technology/privacy-fears-as-surveillance-grows-in-cities.html">some of the privacy concerns</a> people have with such a plan. I made the flyer above (please share widely!), will be attending, and have submitted a comment card.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="activism" /><category term="oakland" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="surveillance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scalia’s powerful dissent in Maryland v. King</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/06/scalias-powerful-dissent-in-maryland-v-king/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scalia’s powerful dissent in Maryland v. King" /><published>2013-06-18T02:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-06-18T02:51:00-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/06/scalias-powerful-dissent-in-maryland-v-king</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/06/scalias-powerful-dissent-in-maryland-v-king/"><![CDATA[<p>The Supreme Court released a decision earlier this month that I think history will reflect on as a mistake. In <cite>Maryland v. King</cite>, the Court held that suspects arrested for “major crimes” could have their DNA collected and stored.</p>

<p>I rarely find myself in agreement with Scalia, but I think this quote from him sums up my frustration with the majority opinion.</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/scaliaunquotes-614x1024.jpg" alt="scaliaunquotes" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="antonin scalia" /><category term="dna" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="supreme court" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Supreme Court released a decision earlier this month that I think history will reflect on as a mistake. In Maryland v. King, the Court held that suspects arrested for “major crimes” could have their DNA collected and stored.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Where was the outrage then?” ask the trolls</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/05/where-was-the-outrage-then-ask-the-trolls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Where was the outrage then?” ask the trolls" /><published>2013-05-08T12:55:38-04:00</published><updated>2013-05-08T12:55:38-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/05/where-was-the-outrage-then-ask-the-trolls</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/05/where-was-the-outrage-then-ask-the-trolls/"><![CDATA[<p>Working on drones, and increasingly in the conversation around Google Glass, I keep hearing a common refrain from people who don’t understand other people’s concerns. “There are surveillance cameras on every corner in major cities, helicopters with cameras overhead, and constant tracking in a million other ways,” the argument goes, “and where is the outrage about those things?”</p>

<p>I find this very strange. For one thing, it seems to imply that society’s got one shot to weigh in on a new branch of technology when its root is being formed. Like there’s a speak-now-or-forever-hold-your-peace moment where if the outrage isn’t sufficiently intense then we have to take our lumps and accept new developments forever. Of course, though, that’s crazy.</p>

<p>But for another thing, I can tell you where the outrage was. A lot of the concerns around drones and Glass that are being picked up and amplified now are the exact same concerns that people were voicing around ubiquitous CCTV cameras and warrantless wiretapping and the TSA and what-have-you.</p>

<p>I don’t think, generally, you should be able to silence an argument because somebody wasn’t making a similar argument earlier. But it seems especially ill-advised to me to try to catch the privacy community in such a loophole. The group of people that are actively outraged about privacy violations may be small, but it is fiercely principled.</p>

<p>So, in response to “Where was the outrage then?” First, it doesn’t matter. Here is the outrage now. But second, it was always there, simmering beneath the surface, and if you haven’t seen it then maybe you’re not the expert on these issues that you thought you were.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="surveillance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Working on drones, and increasingly in the conversation around Google Glass, I keep hearing a common refrain from people who don’t understand other people’s concerns. “There are surveillance cameras on every corner in major cities, helicopters with cameras overhead, and constant tracking in a million other ways,” the argument goes, “and where is the outrage about those things?”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SXSW panel proposals</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/sxsw-panel-proposals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SXSW panel proposals" /><published>2012-08-20T02:21:29-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-20T02:21:29-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/sxsw-panel-proposals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/sxsw-panel-proposals/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve submitted two proposals for panels at next year’s South by Southwest festival in Austin. I really hope one of them gets picked. The PanelPicker is currently open for voting (I’d appreciate your votes!) and then I’ll know later this year if I’m in.</p>

<p><a href="http://panelpicker.sxsw.com/vote/4022">Ebooks: A Coming War for the Soul of the Library</a> will be with my friends Audrey Evans and Nancy Sims (<a href="https://twitter.com/copyrightlibn">@CopyrightLibn</a>) and cover the issues libraries face as publishers push for an ebook licensing model to replace the current <a href="http://www.copyright.gov/title17/92chap1.html#108">108</a> and first sale regime. I made a video to explain the panel:</p>

<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/HncrSUaJMfI" width="560"></iframe>

<p>The second panel proposal is called <a href="http://panelpicker.sxsw.com/vote/6458">Drones Gone Wild</a>, and will be with my colleague Trevor, as well as <a href="http://twitter.com/rcalo">Ryan Calo</a> and Nabiha Syed, who’s currently a First Amendment Fellow for the New York Times and who has been instrumental in <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/eff-and-muckrock-partner-see-how-your-local-police-are-using-drones">the EFF/MuckRock drone request campaign</a>. (Trevor and I previously <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/07/pwn-the-drones-presentation-at-hope/">spoke together about drones at HOPE</a> and we co-operate <a href="https://twitter.com/drones">@drones</a>.) We’ll be talking about the rise of domestic drones and the privacy problems they introduce.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="drones" /><category term="e-books" /><category term="EFF" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="sxsw" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve submitted two proposals for panels at next year’s South by Southwest festival in Austin. I really hope one of them gets picked. The PanelPicker is currently open for voting (I’d appreciate your votes!) and then I’ll know later this year if I’m in.]]></summary></entry></feed>