<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/publishing.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:29:15-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/publishing.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">1923 zine and website launch</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2019/03/1923-zine-and-website-launch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1923 zine and website launch" /><published>2019-03-23T14:24:45-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-23T14:24:45-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2019/03/1923-zine-and-website-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2019/03/1923-zine-and-website-launch/"><![CDATA[<p>Towards the beginning of this year I ran a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/887675031/1923-a-monthly-zine-of-public-domain-treasures/description">Kickstarter campaign for a monthly zine</a> of archival material from the year 1923.</p>

<p>That year has some copyright and public domain significance. For twenty years following <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_Term_Extension_Act">the 1998 Copyright Term Extension Act</a>, 1922 was the most recent publication year for which a given work could be categorically determined to be in the public domain. That made “1922 and earlier” <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20151102/16255832697/copyright-terms-how-historical-journalism-is-disappearing.shtml">a common category for digitized databases</a> of older works. On January 1, that border advanced for the first time in two decades, and the zine is something of a celebration of that fact.</p>

<p>Anyway.</p>

<p>The zines sold out quickly—I only intended to offer a hundred subscriptions, which were snapped up in about two hours—and so I added a “digital subscription” option. That meant I would have to figure out how to distribute the zines digitally too, but I was probably going to want to do that anyhow.</p>

<p>I sent out and posted (for backers only) the first two issues together after the campaign closed in the beginning of February. This week I sent out and posted the third issue, and so I’ve removed the “paywall” for the first two.</p>

<p>Which means: you can now check out the January and Feburary issues of <em>1923</em> at <a href="https://1923.press/">1923.press</a>.</p>

<p>This has been a big endeavor for me, and I’ve had to learn a lot about a tiny area of publishing and fulfillment.</p>

<p>In the coming days I’m going to publish some notes about my zine-creating process, which I think is sort of idiosyncratic but may also be instructional. I’ve written a few scripts and one-liners to ease the process, and I’d love if those ended up being helpful to other zine makers!</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="kickstarter" /><category term="public domain" /><category term="publishing" /><category term="zine" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Towards the beginning of this year I ran a Kickstarter campaign for a monthly zine of archival material from the year 1923.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Screenshot_2019-02-16_11-56-40.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Screenshot_2019-02-16_11-56-40.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">DRM means missed opportunities for e-books</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/04/drm-means-missed-opportunities-for-e-books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DRM means missed opportunities for e-books" /><published>2012-04-08T13:08:27-04:00</published><updated>2012-04-08T13:08:27-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/04/drm-means-missed-opportunities-for-e-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/04/drm-means-missed-opportunities-for-e-books/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s no surprise that the major traditional publishers are afraid of e-books. Like record labels and movie studios before them, publishers have seen the spectre of disruptive technology on the horizon and have dug in their heels. Where they’ve accepted e-books they’ve done so half-heartedly, neutralizing the benefits of the new medium with <a href="http://mako.cc/copyrighteous/20120306-00">opaque DRM schemes</a> that emulate the limitations of print books as closely as possible. As <a href="http://blog.findings.com/post/20527246081/how-we-will-read-clay-shirky">Clay Shirky puts it</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The original promise of the e-book was not a promise to the reader, it was a promise to the publisher: “We will design something that appears on a screen, but it will be as inconvenient as if it were a physical object.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>How could inconvenience be a selling point to a publisher? It’s because they fear <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/03/britannica-bookstores-and-bundled-values/">bundle failure</a>. Publishers have always been able to <a href="http://questioncopyright.org/understanding_free_content">bundle the text of a book (the “content”) with a physical volume (the “container”)</a>. When that’s the case, selling books is almost like selling any other physical object, with infrastructure in place for designing, manufacturing, distributing, and selling at retail. Convenient e-books threaten to unsettle that arrangement — they make attractive the idea of consuming just the publisher’s content, and not its container.</p>

<p>The unanswered question that is driving publisher e-book strategy is about the perceived value breakdown of that bundle. How much have people been paying for just the content, and how much were they paying for the nice container? When publishers talk about the need to avoid “devaluing” books with low e-book prices, they’re talking about this question.</p>

<p>One shortsighted answer presumes that the value of an e-book is the value of a hardcover minus the perceived cost of printing. This premise, in fact, informs the e-book pricing strategy of most publishers. But it’s both incorrect and dangerous. It leads to the strategic error of situating e-books as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Substitute_good">substitute goods</a>, instead of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complementary_good">complementary goods</a>, for a publisher’s other offerings.</p>

<p>When there’s a substitute good for something you sell, you’ve got to either work against it or make it as profitable as the good it’s displacing. DRM comes from an effort to do both. It diminishes the advantages of e-books over their printed counterparts and strives to limit their distribution to full-price retail sales. ((Going, of course, one step further than printed books. Publishers haven’t historically been able to control secondary sales or sharing.))</p>

<p>If instead publishers recognized the text as a complementary good, they’d be in the much more comfortable position of trying to increase the demand for it. After all, the actual publication and distribution of volumes is already just one step on the end of a long workflow, each step of which is supposed to make the text better and increase demand. It’s crazy to subvert that whole chain to preserve the last link, just because it’s the one at which the actual revenue comes in.</p>

<p>So what are the goods and services for which the text of a book can be a complement? That’s where publishers earn their paycheck. It could be events with authors, merchandise, film rights, beautiful print editions — the point is that it is easier to monetize a popular book than an obscure one, even if you’re not making most of the profits on sales of the book.</p>

<p>DRM renders <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_innovation">user innovation</a> difficult at best, and so limits the possibility of runaway demand. And it <a href="http://blog.grossmeier.net/2012/03/25/why-i-dont-buy-ebooks-anymore/">makes the e-book, the closest thing yet to the content alone, <em>less</em> valuable</a>. Taken together, that means missed opportunities for publishers and authors.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="clay shirky" /><category term="drm" /><category term="e-books" /><category term="economics" /><category term="publishing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s no surprise that the major traditional publishers are afraid of e-books. Like record labels and movie studios before them, publishers have seen the spectre of disruptive technology on the horizon and have dug in their heels. Where they’ve accepted e-books they’ve done so half-heartedly, neutralizing the benefits of the new medium with opaque DRM schemes that emulate the limitations of print books as closely as possible. As Clay Shirky puts it:]]></summary></entry></feed>