<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/science.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:04:09-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/science.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">New policy: don’t share coverage of academic research unless the research is open access</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/new-policy-dont-share-coverage-of-academic-research-unless-the-research-is-open-access/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New policy: don’t share coverage of academic research unless the research is open access" /><published>2013-02-04T00:57:44-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-04T00:57:44-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/new-policy-dont-share-coverage-of-academic-research-unless-the-research-is-open-access</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/new-policy-dont-share-coverage-of-academic-research-unless-the-research-is-open-access/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve identified a little gap in my support of open access publishing that I hope to remedy with this new practice. When I encounter a news article about a new study or paper, the first thing I do is look for the underlying paper. (It’s a good idea anyway, given the standard complaints about science journalism.) If the underlying paper is not available for at least public access, I’m not going to talk about it. As my friend Tom put it, “<a href="https://twitter.com/flamsmark/status/295992579286261760">It’s not published until it’s open access. I’ll talk about it once it’s published.</a>”</p>

<p>I don’t know how much of an effect this can have, but I know that it stems from a real problem. Academics don’t choose to publish in traditional, closed access journals because they offer any better deal; rather, it’s a career booster. A publication in a “top” journal comes with prestige, which is major currency to researchers trying to make a name. As a result, in <a href="http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k77982&amp;tabgroupid=icb.tabgroup143448">Harvard Library’s memo encouraging open access</a>, for example, the Faculty Advisory Council cites a need to “move prestige” to open access publications.</p>

<p>The hope, with my new policy, is that academics who want more members of the public to read about their results might choose a publication option that people haven’t pledged not to share, and maybe journalists will know that covering closed access papers results in less social engagement. It’s a long shot, but it’s something I can do.</p>

<p>So here goes. You want a story about how <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/22/science/some-shark-embryos-can-detect-predators.html">shark embryos can detect predators from inside the womb</a>? You got it. <a href="http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052551">The underlying research is in PLoS One</a>. But that story about how many animals cats kill a year? Sorry, that one’s locked up.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="open access" /><category term="science" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve identified a little gap in my support of open access publishing that I hope to remedy with this new practice. When I encounter a news article about a new study or paper, the first thing I do is look for the underlying paper. (It’s a good idea anyway, given the standard complaints about science journalism.) If the underlying paper is not available for at least public access, I’m not going to talk about it. As my friend Tom put it, “It’s not published until it’s open access. I’ll talk about it once it’s published.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patenting away an open science opportunity</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/patenting-away-open-science-opportunity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patenting away an open science opportunity" /><published>2012-08-28T03:46:13-04:00</published><updated>2012-08-28T03:46:13-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/patenting-away-open-science-opportunity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/08/patenting-away-open-science-opportunity/"><![CDATA[<p>By almost any measure, Jack Andraka, the 15-year-old science prodigy from Maryland, should be a hero of the open science movement. After all, he has gotten a lot of well-deserved attention in the past few months for his work <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bruceupbin/2012/06/18/wait-did-this-15-year-old-from-maryland-just-change-cancer-treatment/">developing a new test for pancreatic cancer</a>. By his own estimates, the test he developed is 168 times faster and 26,667 times cheaper than the existing state-of-the-art test. He says the insight for the test came to him while he was “<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-19291258">chilling out in biology class</a>,” and that it was helped along by search engines and free online science papers.</p>

<p>On its face, this is a major victory for open science. The right person was able to find the right materials and combine them in such a way to make some important scientific progress, all because there were few barriers in place to stop him. Even better, he was rewarded for this development immediately, with a bounty much greater than most high school sophomores can expect to see in a year — for his efforts, he was awarded the Intel Science Fair grand prize of $75,000, and smaller category prizes for <a href="http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2012-05-24/news/bs-ar-student-intel-winner-20120523_1_top-prize-grand-prize-intel-science-fair">a total of $100,500</a>.</p>

<p>I want to close it up there, and just congratulate him on being such a remarkable example of the power of open access. But, alas, there’s a hitch. From <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bruceupbin/2012/06/18/wait-did-this-15-year-old-from-maryland-just-change-cancer-treatment/">the long Forbes article about his discovery</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>He says he’s been contacted by four companies, including Quest Diagnostics, about potentially licensing or commercializing the idea. “I got a really fierce patent lawyer right after I won ISEF,” says Andraka, laughing, from his home in Maryland.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have a few problems with that statement. Underlying all of them: why is he even seeking a patent? Patents are Constitutional only insofar as they <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_Clause">promote the progress of science and the useful arts</a>. But in this story, it was the <em>lack</em> of restrictions that allowed progress.</p>

<p>A patent would undermine at least one significant component of his discovery. It’s all but inevitable that the impressive savings from his test will be reduced when the cost of lawyers, licensing, and monopoly pricing get factored in. It’s still going to be much cheaper than the existing test, but it will also be less widely available as its distribution is limited by the single point of licensing.</p>

<p>Further, it’s not even clear he’s eligible for a patent since <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/supreme-court-gets-it-right-no-patents-laws-nature">the Supreme Court ruling in Mayo v. Prometheus</a>. That case, decided earlier this year, actually concerned a patent on a medical diagnostic test. The Court held that observations of a natural correlation do not constitute patent-eligible subject matter.</p>

<p>Nobody’s knocking his achievement, and it’s incredibly impressive and good for humanity that Jack Andraka was able to make this discovery. I just wish he’d take a page from the book of the great Jonas Salk, who, when asked who owned the patent on his breakthrough polio vaccine, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/11/25/magazine/once-again-a-man-with-a-mission.html?pagewanted=all">responded simply</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Well, the people, I would say. There is no patent. Could you patent the sun?</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cancer" /><category term="jack andraka" /><category term="open access" /><category term="open science" /><category term="patent" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By almost any measure, Jack Andraka, the 15-year-old science prodigy from Maryland, should be a hero of the open science movement. After all, he has gotten a lot of well-deserved attention in the past few months for his work developing a new test for pancreatic cancer. By his own estimates, the test he developed is 168 times faster and 26,667 times cheaper than the existing state-of-the-art test. He says the insight for the test came to him while he was “chilling out in biology class,” and that it was helped along by search engines and free online science papers.]]></summary></entry></feed>