<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/sopa.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:33:55-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/sopa.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Predicting the present in Cory Doctorow’s “Pirate Cinema”</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting the present in Cory Doctorow’s “Pirate Cinema”" /><published>2013-02-04T11:00:13-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-04T11:00:13-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/predicting-the-present-in-cory-doctorows-pirate-cinema/"><![CDATA[<p>Cory Doctorow is coming through town again, this time on his tour for <cite>Homeland</cite>, the sequel to his excellent young adult novel <cite>Little Brother</cite>. Cory likes to talk about how his fiction “predicts the present”: taking the bits of future that are already here, just not yet evenly distributed, and applying them more widely. It’s a neat trick that makes his sci-fi seem eerily prescient, and I know <cite>Little Brother</cite> has been boosted by supporters of Occupy who saw much of their story foretold in his writing.</p>

<p>In another of Cory’s young adult books, the recent <a href="http://craphound.com/pc/about/"><cite>Pirate Cinema</cite></a>, much of the plot focuses on draconian copyright enforcement systems and backlash. Of course, there’s a rich history to pull from: the battles over SOPA and ACTA were just the latest in a long narrative that Cory has been engaged with for years. His “Theft of Intellectual Property Bill (TIP)” might have been fiction, but it’s a logical extension of what we’ve already seen.</p>

<p>Combine predicting the present with some old-fashioned coincidence, and things start to get spooky. Take Cory’s “Jimmy Preston,” who in <cite>Pirate Cinema</cite> gets a then-unprecedented five-year prison term for sharing music files. Cory writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But he’d collected 450,000 songs on his hard drive through endless, tedious, tireless hours of downloading. From what anyone could tell, he didn’t even listen to them: he just liked cataloging them, correcting their metadata, organizing them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Compare that to the real-life Jeremiah Perkins, who just a few months after <cite>Pirate Cinema</cite>‘s release was <a href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2013/01/record-filing-sharing-term/">also sentenced to five years for filesharing</a>. According to a report prepared on behalf ot the movie studios, his group iMAGINE was well-known for <a href="http://torrentfreak.com/imagine-bittorrent-piracy-group-sysop-jailed-40-months-121130/">“their consistently good quality of audio captures” and “their high volume of releases”</a>.</p>

<p>I hope that Jeremiah Perkins doesn’t face the same ultimate fate as Cory’s Jimmy Preston, who didn’t do well in prison. Even more importantly, I hope we don’t see more jailtime for filesharers.</p>

<p>When the book came out, I saw at least one review that said the action was too over-the-top, the law too excessive, the studio groups too vindictive to possibly reflect reality. Detractors should take note: when the book came out, the mainstream probably wouldn’t believe a five-year sentence for file-sharing. Then it happened. Cory’s good at predicting the present.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cory doctorow" /><category term="file sharing" /><category term="imagine" /><category term="piracy" /><category term="pirate cinema" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cory Doctorow is coming through town again, this time on his tour for Homeland, the sequel to his excellent young adult novel Little Brother. Cory likes to talk about how his fiction “predicts the present”: taking the bits of future that are already here, just not yet evenly distributed, and applying them more widely. It’s a neat trick that makes his sci-fi seem eerily prescient, and I know Little Brother has been boosted by supporters of Occupy who saw much of their story foretold in his writing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IP above all else</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/ip-above-all-else/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IP above all else" /><published>2012-05-24T03:38:02-04:00</published><updated>2012-05-24T03:38:02-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/ip-above-all-else</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/05/ip-above-all-else/"><![CDATA[<p>It can be hard to point a finger at exactly what is so offensive about the way the copyright lobby pushes its agenda. The rhetoric is sometimes charged, but I don’t think the problem lies in the moral foundation of intellectual monopolies (although some people certainly object to them on <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20100519/0404029486.shtml">ethical grounds</a>). I also don’t think it’s a fundamental business problem. Some have argued that <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120503/14160618768/nobody-cares-about-fixed-costs-your-book-movie-whatever.shtml">nobody cares about content creators’ fixed costs</a>, and that their fixation on that number is misguided, but I think that premise falls apart a bit at the margins: when fans feel a connection to a creator, they <em>do</em> care about her fixed costs, and want to help her make the record or book or film.</p>

<p>No, the ethical and economic basis of copyright isn’t inherently so offensive. It’s kind of like any other business, at its core. As the former Warner Music CTO recently put it, recorded music (for example) isn’t <a href="https://twitter.com/ethank/status/203525014300004353">diamonds mined from a secret mythical land</a> — it’s just a thing that some people make and that other people — fans — enjoy. As in nearly any other business, those fans are willing to support the producer if they feel a human connection to her. Copyright is one model we’ve developed to facilitate that support, and though it’s wearing a bit at the edges, it’s not fundamentally evil or insane.</p>

<p>The problem is the mindset of “IP above all else” that seems to pervade every statement and action that the copyright and patent lobbies take. That’s the mindset that leads to WIPO <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120404/12263218371/ip-above-all-else-wipo-defies-un-sanctions-to-give-computers-to-north-korea.shtml">defying UN sanctions, shipping computers to North Korea</a> to enable it to observe international patent law. That leads to some of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/17/arts/music/17jazz.html?pagewanted=all">the world’s greatest jazz recordings to be virtually impossible to hear</a>, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/17/nyregion/ascap-asks-royalties-from-girl-scouts-and-regrets-it.html?pagewanted=all">Girl Scouts being silenced at campfires</a>, and <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/08/01/AR2007080102398.html">19-year-olds arrested at the movie theater for taking out a camera</a>. <a href="http://www.ip-watch.org/2012/05/20/india%E2%80%99s-generics-big-pharma-battle-drops-drug-prices-raises-legal-debate/">Fighting generic drugs that save lives around the world</a>, <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/04/24/us-sec-movies-idUSBRE83N15V20120424">bribery scandals over movie deals in China</a>, <a href="http://popwatch.ew.com/2012/01/23/chris-dodd-mpaa-bribery/">and even in the US</a>. Pushing for laws that even supporters admit “<a href="http://popwatch.ew.com/2012/01/23/chris-dodd-mpaa-bribery/">really did pose some risk to the Internet.</a>”</p>

<p>The list goes on and on. As much as the copyright lobby want to frame the debate around the premise of intellectual property itself, that’s really missing the point. It’s impossible to address the problems with copyright without first acknowledging its biggest supporters’ excesses at every step.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="ip" /><category term="mpaa" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It can be hard to point a finger at exactly what is so offensive about the way the copyright lobby pushes its agenda. The rhetoric is sometimes charged, but I don’t think the problem lies in the moral foundation of intellectual monopolies (although some people certainly object to them on ethical grounds). I also don’t think it’s a fundamental business problem. Some have argued that nobody cares about content creators’ fixed costs, and that their fixation on that number is misguided, but I think that premise falls apart a bit at the margins: when fans feel a connection to a creator, they do care about her fixed costs, and want to help her make the record or book or film.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will last week’s blackouts reframe the conversation on copyright policy?</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/will-last-weeks-blackouts-reframe-the-conversation-on-copyright-policy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will last week’s blackouts reframe the conversation on copyright policy?" /><published>2012-01-23T02:25:15-05:00</published><updated>2012-01-23T02:25:15-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/will-last-weeks-blackouts-reframe-the-conversation-on-copyright-policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/will-last-weeks-blackouts-reframe-the-conversation-on-copyright-policy/"><![CDATA[<p>This online blackouts last week were not only the largest in recent history, but in a narrow sense, they might be the most effective ever. Imagine: online protests and the resulting media coverage and legislator calls led to the shelving of two “sure thing” bills over the course of two days.</p>

<p>But the protests shouldn’t just be considered in that narrow a frame. As <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2012/jan/20/struggle-against-sopa-and-pipa-is-not-over">Dan Gillmor</a> and <a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/01/20/the-next-sopa">Marco Arment</a> correctly point out, any victory against specific legislation in this field is bound to be ephemeral. The entertainment lobbying groups aren’t going to rest in drafting new laws to slip by under the public notice.</p>

<p>So the question becomes: were the online protests effective on any scale beyond the legislation at hand? I think the answer to that is yes. For one thing, these online protests brought copyright policy to the public attention, and that’s almost always a good thing. The moment at this week’s South Carolina GOP primary debate where <a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/law/2012/01/20/republican-candidates-talk-sopa/">all four candidates came out strongly against SOPA and PIPA</a> felt unprecedented in the copyright world. In a field where “<a href="http://www.authorama.com/free-culture-2.html">common sense revolts</a>” at the industry-penned laws that are on the books, public attention is a real first step to reform.</p>

<p>Another change that I hope persists is the way that contested facts are being framed. One of the frustrating things about statements against the bills has been the formula they all seem to follow: we all agree that piracy is a major problem, but these bills are the wrong way to address them. Joshua McVeigh-Schultz at USC has done <a href="http://culturedigitally.org/2012/01/sopa-and-the-framing-of-contested-facts">some good writing on this phenomenon</a>.</p>

<p>Until the last few days, people who were questioning the premise, by suggesting that maybe piracy isn’t a serious economic problem, were on the fringe. Rick Falkvinge of the Pirate Party opposed the statements on the grounds that we need to “<a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120102/16374417254/it-is-time-to-stop-pretending-to-endorse-copyright-monopoly.shtml">stop pretending to endorse the copyright monopoly</a>“. Tim O’Reilly has been persistent and eloquent in <a href="https://plus.google.com/107033731246200681024/posts/BEDukdz2B1r">questioning the economic harm of piracy</a>. And of course Julian Sanchez’s <a href="http://www.cato-at-liberty.org/how-copyright-industries-con-congress/">spot-on analysis for the Cato Institute</a> has consistently called the MPAA et al out on their funny numbers.</p>

<p>But in the past few days, I think we’re starting to see this discussion creep into the mainstream — or at least from the “copyright nerd” to the “general nerd” arena. Not only have musician <a href="http://www.jonathancoulton.com/2012/01/21/megaupload/">Jonathan Coulton</a> and actor <a href="http://wilwheaton.tumblr.com/post/16246156406/mpaa-directly-publicly-threatens-politicians-who">Wil Wheaton</a> (admittedly, both nerd icons) come out with statements that piracy is not the issue, but sites like <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2012/01/21/does-online-piracy-hurt-the-economy-a-look-at-the-numbers/">Forbes</a> and <a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2012/01/12/how-much-do-music-and-movie-piracy-really-hurt-the-u-s-economy/">Freakonomics</a> have picked up the question as well.</p>

<p>Detractors of the Occupy movement complain that those protesters’ issues were too nebulous. Without specific demands they couldn’t expect to effect change. In the short term, it’s true that they couldn’t claim the legislative victory that this round of protests have. But the Occupy protests were absolutely able to <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/peter-dreier/occupy-wall-street-media_b_1069250.html">change the conversation</a>. As Alexis Madrigal describes in the Atlantic this week, the Occupy protests <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/01/the-sopa-blackout-created-a-big-problem/251578/">created a problem</a> in the particular set of “foregrounding” a set of issues into something that should be addressed. Madrigal is skeptical that the anti-SOPA efforts will be able to bridge from specific to general, but I remain hopeful.</p>

<p>Finally, it’s important to consider how this week’s actions have changed the face of online protest. Anil Dash has taken <a href="http://dashes.com/anil/2012/01/the-history-and-future-of-web-protest.html">a good look at the history and future of online protest</a>, with thoughts about how it might develop. I’m encouraged by the Reddit front page lighting up with stories about ACTA, and Hacker News discussing anew the <a href="http://ycombinator.com/rfs9.html">YCRFS 9 proposal to kill Hollywood</a>. There’s energy in the air, and it’s being directed in the right place. Hopefully now we can look at ways to proactively shape copyright policy in a way that benefits the public, instead of reacting to bad legislation one after another.</p>

<p>There are a lot of places to reform copyright. Joel Spolsky has <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/117114202722218150209/posts/4GgaRiSyaTf">put together a good list of them</a>, if you’re interested. We can’t know yet, but I hope to look back on the events of this week as a starting point for big changes.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="activism" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="pipa" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This online blackouts last week were not only the largest in recent history, but in a narrow sense, they might be the most effective ever. Imagine: online protests and the resulting media coverage and legislator calls led to the shelving of two “sure thing” bills over the course of two days.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s bothering John Lilly about the SOPA discussion</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/whats-bothering-john-lilly-about-the-sopa-discussion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s bothering John Lilly about the SOPA discussion" /><published>2012-01-07T22:08:49-05:00</published><updated>2012-01-07T22:08:49-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/whats-bothering-john-lilly-about-the-sopa-discussion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/whats-bothering-john-lilly-about-the-sopa-discussion/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://john.jubjubs.net/2012/01/06/whats-bothering-me-about-the-sopa-discussion/">Over on his blog</a>, John Lilly provides the best sort of analysis of the SOPA conversation — reasonable and measured. The problem with the “dialogue” so far, he says, is that (1) it has basically consisted of each side calling the other names, (2) which isn’t going to help now, and (3) will set a bad precedent for making new tech policy.</p>

<p>Expanding on that first point, he says that while the bill’s supporters may have kicked things off by accusing the tech community of engaging in, supporting, and profiting from piracy, that community should not respond with further name-calling and accusations of censorship. Instead, the tech sector should acknowledge the real problem with online piracy overseas and work together with the content industry to address it.</p>

<p>I really appreciate calls for civility, especially in a discussion that has gotten as heated as the one around SOPA and PROTECT IP. But as an active participant in that discussion, three things immediately popped out at me that deserve attention.</p>

<p>John wants there to be a “nuanced, technically-informed, respectful discussion/debate/conversation/working relationship” between these two parties, but doesn’t see a way that can happen. He may be right when he says that one missing piece is civility. But another is that both parties need to approach this discussion honestly. Supporters of this bill have, in <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20111214/04100017081/chris-dodd-resorting-to-outright-lying-desperate-attempt-to-get-sopa-passed.shtml">example</a> after <a href="http://www.cato-at-liberty.org/how-copyright-industries-con-congress/">example</a>, demonstrated no remorse in lying outright to support their position.</p>

<p>Opponents of the bill point out when its supporters are lying, and when they seem to be <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/week-censorship">advocating for measures suited for repressive regimes</a>. Maybe these are attacks, but they are also true. While both sides may need to tone down the vitriol, there is no hope of progress until everybody first agrees to give the process enough respect to stick to the truth.</p>

<p>(I’ll acknowledge that, in some cases, the bill’s supporters may simply be misinformed; that lack of information would be a consequence of them not taking the debate seriously. Or that they’re not being dishonest, per se, but <a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/intellectualdishonesty">intellectually dishonest</a>. It’s hard to know without being in their head, but in any case, the point stands.)</p>

<p>John also rightly points out that we need to be thinking critically about how copyright law can and should work today, and he claims that part of that process needs to be acknowledging the real problem facing rightsholders. I agree, of course, with the first part. But I think the second needs to be examined closer. Rightsholders might only have a “real problem” in a very limited sense of the word.</p>

<p>The ease of copying can absolutely lead to missed profit opportunities. But <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/01/sopa-is-a-symbol-of-the-movie-industrys-failure-to-innovate/250967/">as Steve Blank points out in the Atlantic</a>, the content industry’s track record of identifying which technologies will ultimately be profitable is abysmal, and they’re also not alone in dealing with “piracy”. Every area of commerce grapples with the fact that bad actors can thwart controls, but only the content industries are willing (and able!) to destroy innovation in other sectors to control it. ((The content industry may even be better off than other industries when it comes to piracy, because the version they face — copyright infringement — <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2011/12/15/piracy_is_a_form_of_theft_and_copyright_infringement_is_neither.html">isn’t even theft</a>.))</p>

<p>Combine that history with the first point — that studios and labels are willing to flat-out lie to support their points — and it becomes hard to take their “problem” seriously. The tech community isn’t denying that Internet users can download Hollywood movies off servers in Sweden, but what does that actually mean for their business? The rightsholders’ plain insincerity, the lack of real data to support their position, and their uncanny knack for attacking each new technology as it emerges conspire against the precariousness of their position.</p>

<p>Finally, and this is a point John acknowledges, these bills were not introduced in a way to foster a conversation. If the content industries were interested in a real conversation, they’d find willing participants. Trying to push through legislation that they wrote in secret with “<a href="http://news.cnet.com/8301-31921_3-57343367-281/meet-sopa-author-lamar-smith-hollywoods-favorite-republican/">Hollywood’s favorite Republican</a>“, to a Congress <a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1111/68448.html">they’ve spent $91 million lobbying</a> this year alone, does not demonstrate a good faith effort on their part.</p>

<p>A discussion about how copyright should be shaped and enforced in the face of changing technology and norms is a good one to have. But the people who recognize the importance of technology continue to be denied the opportunity to have that conversation with the other stakeholders. Instead, we have been put on the defensive against incoming legislative U-boats. Without a doubt, a meaningful dialogue would be better now and for the future; unfortunately, our only option at the moment is to point out the glaring flaws in these proposals and keep fighting them until they sink.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="john lilly" /><category term="response" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over on his blog, John Lilly provides the best sort of analysis of the SOPA conversation — reasonable and measured. The problem with the “dialogue” so far, he says, is that (1) it has basically consisted of each side calling the other names, (2) which isn’t going to help now, and (3) will set a bad precedent for making new tech policy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SOPA, figuratively speaking</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2011/11/sopa-figuratively-speaking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SOPA, figuratively speaking" /><published>2011-11-29T22:16:46-05:00</published><updated>2011-11-29T22:16:46-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2011/11/sopa-figuratively-speaking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2011/11/sopa-figuratively-speaking/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been impressed with the quality of language used to describe the Stop Online Piracy Act. The bill is a disaster for the internet, and its opponents are devising some pretty creative ways of expressing that. Two of my favorites:</p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/compost/post/stop-sopa/2011/11/16/gIQAlEtNSN_blog.html">Alexandra Petri on the Washington Post ComPost blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This isn’t even throwing the baby out with the bathwater. This is bludgeoning the baby repeatedly with a sledgehammer and then throwing out the whole bathroom.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From <a href="http://www.alistapart.com/articles/say-no-to-sopa/">Jeffrey Zeldman on A List Apart</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>SOPA approaches the piracy problem with a broad brush, lights that brush on fire, and soaks the whole internet in gasoline.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>UPDATE: Dec 9</strong>: From the great <a href="http://ammori.org/2011/12/08/controversial-copyright-bills-would-violate-first-amendment-letters-to-congress-by-laurence-tribe-and-me/">Marvin Ammori</a>, on his letter with Laurence Tribe:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The bills are not limited; they’re sledgehammers not scalpels.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>UPDATE: Dec 13</strong>: From <a href="http://www.cato-at-liberty.org/the-new-sopa-now-with-slightly-less-awfulness/">Julian Sanchez at the Cato Institute</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A third clause says the bill shouldn’t be construed in a way that would impair the security or integrity of the network—which is a bit like slapping a label on a cake stipulating that it shouldn’t be construed to make you fat.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/nbepe/sopa_in_a_nutshell_if_a_criminal_hid_counterfeit/">user roxtafari on Reddit</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>SOPA in a nutshell: If a criminal hid counterfeit goods in a bank safe deposit box, SOPA would allow the legitimate IP owner to shut down the entire bank and all other branches without any notice, search warrant, or due process.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>UPDATE: Dec 18</strong>: From <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/everything-you-need-to-know-about-congresss-online-piracy-bills-in-one-post/2011/12/16/gIQAz4ggyO_blog.html">Brad Plumer on Washington Post’s Wonkblog</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Essentially, copyright holders are asking for a really enormous sledgehammer to play this game of whack-a-mole.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ll keep updating as I come across good ones, and let me know in the comments if you’ve seen one.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="sopa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been impressed with the quality of language used to describe the Stop Online Piracy Act. The bill is a disaster for the internet, and its opponents are devising some pretty creative ways of expressing that. Two of my favorites:]]></summary></entry></feed>