<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/technology.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T17:42:42-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/tag/technology.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Supreme Court’s real technology problem</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/the-supreme-courts-real-technology-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Supreme Court’s real technology problem" /><published>2014-04-30T20:24:21-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-30T20:24:21-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/the-supreme-courts-real-technology-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2014/04/the-supreme-courts-real-technology-problem/"><![CDATA[<p>I spent a lot of the last week shaking my head at the commentary on the Supreme Court and its (lack of) technical expertise. Much of the criticism came in response to the oral arguments in <em>Aereo</em>, and broke down in two areas: it either <a href="http://sarahjeong.net/2014/04/22/supreme-court-justices-are-not-good-with-computers/">misunderstood the nature of Supreme Court oral arguments and their transcripts</a>, or <a href="http://sarahjeong.net/2014/04/23/scotus-is-bad-at-computers-part-2/">mistook familiarity with a handful of Silicon Valley products with actual tech savviness</a>.</p>

<p>But in a series of cases yesterday about law enforcement searches of cell phones, we caught a glimpse of the Supreme Court’s real technology problem. Here’s what it comes down to: it’s not essential that the Court knows specifics about how technology itself works—and as Timothy Lee argues, that <a href="http://www.vox.com/2014/4/23/5644154/the-supreme-courts-technical-cluelessness-makes-them-better-justices">might even tempt them to make technology-based decisions that don’t generalize well</a>. However, it <em>is</em> essential that the Court understands how people use technology, especially in areas where they’re trying to elaborate a standard of what expectations are “reasonable.”</p>

<p>So when Chief Justice Roberts suggests that <a href="https://twitter.com/xor/status/461257425517961216">a person carrying two cell phones might reasonably be suspected of dealing drugs</a>, that raises major red flags. Not because of any special facts about how cell phones work, but because (for example) at least half of the lawyers in the Supreme Court Bar brought two cell phones with them to the courthouse that day. Should those attorneys (along with the many, many other people who carry multiple devices) reasonably expect less privacy because the Chief Justice is out of touch with that fact?</p>

<p>Contrast that with <a href="https://twitter.com/xor/status/461239651043250179">Justice Kagan’s point about storage location in the same argument</a>. Justice Kagan suggested, correctly, that people don’t always know what is stored on their device and what is stored “in the cloud.” The actual answer to that question should be immaterial; the point is that it’s absurd for a person’s privacy interest to hinge on which hard drive private data is stored on. ((That speaks to a need to revisit the sort-of ridiculous third-party doctrine, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2012/01/23/a-supreme-court-justices-radical-proposal-regarding-the-privacy-of-your-google-searches-facebook-account-phone-records/">which Justice Sotomayor has suggested</a>, but one battle at a time.)) Instead, the important fact here, which Justice Kagan recognizes, is that the distinction between local and cloud storage just doesn’t matter to many people, and so it can’t be the basis of a reasonable-expectation-of-privacy test.</p>

<p>If you’re feeling less generous, you might take Justice Kagan’s point as evidence that she herself doesn’t know where her files are stored. And in fact, that’s probably true—but it’s not important. You don’t actually need to know much about filesystems and remote storage to know that it’s a bad idea for the law to treat it differently.</p>

<p>That’s not to say that technical implementation details are never relevant. Relevant details, though, should (and almost always do) get addressed in the briefs, long before the oral argument takes place. They don’t usually read like software manuals, either: they’re often rich with analogies to help explain not just how the tech works, but what body of law should apply.</p>

<p>What can’t really be explained in a brief, though, is a community’s relationship with a technology. You can get at parts of it, citing authorities like surveys and expert witnesses, but a real feeling for what people expect from their software and devices is something that has to be observed. If the nine justices on the Supreme Court can’t bring that knowledge to the arguments, the public suffers greatly. Again, Justice Kagan seems to recognize this fact when she says of cell phones:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They’re computers. They have as much computing capacity as ­­ as laptops did five years ago. And ­­ and everybody under a certain age, let’s say under 40, has everything on them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Justice Kagan is not under 40, and might not have everything stored on a phone (or on an online service accessible through her phone). But that quote shows me that she at least knows where other people’s expectations are different. Chief Justice Roberts’s questions show me exactly the opposite.</p>

<p>The justices live an unusual and sheltered life: they have no concerns about job security, and spend much of their time grappling with abstract questions that have profound effects on this country’s law. But if they fail to recognize where their assumptions about society and technology break from the norm—or indeed, where they are making assumptions in the first place—we’re all in trouble.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="aereo" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="supreme court" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I spent a lot of the last week shaking my head at the commentary on the Supreme Court and its (lack of) technical expertise. Much of the criticism came in response to the oral arguments in Aereo, and broke down in two areas: it either misunderstood the nature of Supreme Court oral arguments and their transcripts, or mistook familiarity with a handful of Silicon Valley products with actual tech savviness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two great pieces on women in tech</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/two-great-pieces-on-women-in-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two great pieces on women in tech" /><published>2013-02-09T03:32:54-05:00</published><updated>2013-02-09T03:32:54-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/two-great-pieces-on-women-in-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2013/02/two-great-pieces-on-women-in-tech/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s recently been a lot of great writing on women and the problem of gender inequality in the tech field. I recommend these three pieces in particular:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://marihuertas.tumblr.com/post/42437255194">“Not a Beard”</a> by Mari Huertas, who was a member of Obama’s re-election tech team. In an effort to indicate that the team was more San Francisco than Washington, many articles joke about the beards on the team. Needless to say, Mari does not have a beard. From the piece:</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>I want other females, young and old, to feel encouraged by the women who worked on this re-election campaign and in technology, civics, and government as a whole. I want girls and young professionals to find their way by the determined wakes we leave. We’re doing important, satisfying, fun work – we should broaden and extend our purview so more can wade into the fray.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://firstround.com/article/How-Etsy-Grew-their-Number-of-Female-Engineers-by-500-in-One-Year">“How Etsy Grew their Number of Female Engineers by Almost 500% in One Year”</a> by Brett Berson, a member of an investment group that hosted Etsy’s CTO for a talk on the subject. It’s important to note that it wasn’t a cheap or easy fix: it involved spending money intelligently on “Hacker Grants” and consistently and proactively reaching out. But it’s also been worth it, increasing diversity on the team and increasing the quality of applicants, male and female.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Even science recognizes that diversity is important: research from both the Kellogg and Sloan Schools suggest that cognitively diverse teams perform better on hard problems.</p>

      <p>Beyond that, though, hiring for diversity will set up better recruiting opportunities.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’m consistently frustrated by the homogeny of the tech scene in San Francisco and generally, and it’s encouraging to see that people are addressing the problem. It’s a long road ahead, and it extends even beyond gender issues. Another great piece called <a href="http://jamellebouie.net/blog/2013/2/3/and-read-all-over">“And Read All Over”</a> by Jamelle Bouie has done an excellent job, for example, of demonstrating the (mostly) unbearable whiteness of the tech journalism community.</p>

<p>Anyway, I think the importance of these issues is even greater than their obvious effect on the discussion around equality in the tech community. As technical developments increasingly have profound effects on our privacy, speech, and civil liberties, I feel much more comfortable with diverse teams making those decisions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="etsy" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="mari huertas" /><category term="technology" /><category term="women" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s recently been a lot of great writing on women and the problem of gender inequality in the tech field. I recommend these three pieces in particular:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The crypto triple threat club</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/the-crypto-triple-threat-club/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The crypto triple threat club" /><published>2012-06-11T04:24:03-04:00</published><updated>2012-06-11T04:24:03-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/the-crypto-triple-threat-club</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/the-crypto-triple-threat-club/"><![CDATA[<p>My written one-to-one communication patterns can be grouped into three major categories: longform, synchronous shortform, and asynchronous shortform. For the most part I use email, IMs, and SMS, respectively, for those purposes.</p>

<p>Each of those technologies has its own end-to-end encryption protocol. ((In some cases, more than one. I’m just listing the ones I use.)) Email has the venerable OpenPGP protocol and <a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">the GnuPG suite of programs</a>; IM has <a href="http://www.cypherpunks.ca/otr/">OTR for Off-the-Record Messaging</a> on Pidgin and Adium on the desktop, and<a href="https://guardianproject.info/apps/gibber/">Gibberbot</a> and <a href="https://chatsecure.org/">ChatSecure</a> on mobile; and SMS has <a href="https://github.com/whispersystems/textsecure">TextSecure</a>, a free software Android SMS application that does encryption locally and over the wire.</p>

<div class="wp-caption alignright" id="attachment_728" style="width: 293px">[![](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/textsecureqr.png "TextSecure QR code")](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/textsecureqr.png)My TextSecure fingreprint, as a QR code generated by the application.

</div>
<p>There’s a small but growing cadre of my friends with whom I’ve exchanged keys on all three protocols. ((Seriously, it’s growing. I added <a href="http://interi.org/">maiki</a> to the club just tonight.)) They’re the crypto triple threats. I want to build that list out further: if I’m having an end-to-end conversation with you, I’d like it to be encrypted end-to-end.</p>

<p>Some of these keys are harder than others to exchange. Email encryption is notoriously difficult to get right, while OTR is much simpler to start working with. TextSecure is a great example of the <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2012/03/a-modest-defense-of-qr-codes/">rare good QR code use case</a>.</p>

<p>These are communication tools, so they’re especially affected by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metcalfe%27s_law">Metcalfe’s Law</a>. That makes it even more important to get people to join the triple threat club. It also means that for each of these protocols, there are lots of people who want to help you figure it out. I’m one of those people. Let’s talk!</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="cell phones" /><category term="communication" /><category term="encryption" /><category term="mobile" /><category term="qr codes" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My written one-to-one communication patterns can be grouped into three major categories: longform, synchronous shortform, and asynchronous shortform. For the most part I use email, IMs, and SMS, respectively, for those purposes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bad civic hygiene</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/bad-civic-hygiene/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bad civic hygiene" /><published>2012-06-03T03:47:26-04:00</published><updated>2012-06-03T03:47:26-04:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/bad-civic-hygiene</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/06/bad-civic-hygiene/"><![CDATA[<p>Bruce Schneier has a great cautionary quote about technology and its tendency to be subverted:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s bad civic hygiene to build technologies that could someday be used to facilitate a police state.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He’s used the line in a few essays: one about <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2007/06/risks_of_data_r.html">data reuse and the role of the US census in Japanese internment</a>, one about <a href="https://www.schneier.com/essay-281.html">Chinese pornography filters that snoop on Internet users</a>, and one about <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2010/09/wiretapping_the.html">a failed Obama administration proposal for backdoors in encryption systems</a>, for example.</p>

<p>It’s typically insightful of Schneier to connect these stories with a common thread. Independent of the primary purpose of personal data collection, which can run the gamut from necessary to useful to invasive, the secondary purposes can be much worse. It’s sometimes difficult even for thoughtful people to consider the primary and secondary purposes of data collection independently, or to consider a technology’s designers responsible for its secondary uses.</p>

<p>That’s why the “hygiene” metaphor is so apt. Good hygiene isn’t mandated by law, but people understand that it’s an important practice. It makes cooperation with society smoother, and reduces the prevalence of <a href="http://craphound.com/complexecosystems.txt">parasites as systems get increasingly complex</a>.</p>

<p>One example: companies that track users across the web often defend the practice by explaining the virtues of their primary purpose. They may help monetize free content, or deliver more customized materials to users, or something else that society considers beneficial. But these arguments miss the point. Obviously, if the primary purpose is bad for society, it’s a short conversation that ends there. Even in the case of a compelling primary purpose, though, having a good <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2008/03/the_security_mi_1.html">security mindset</a> means thinking about the ways a system can fail. Allowing a society to inch towards a police state is a pretty serious failure. ((“<a href="https://freedom-to-tinker.com/blog/felten/security-mindset-and-harmless-failures/">Harmless failures</a>” are bad too. Ed Felten refers to those also as bad hygiene.))</p>

<p>For people making new technologies and businesses, it makes sense to not just consider how profitable or efficient or helpful they’re being — that’s their primary purpose — but how their developments can be abused. Skipping that step can lead to major problems for society. As Supreme Court Justice Louis Brandeis said, “The greatest dangers to liberty lurk in insidious encroachment by men of zeal well-meaning but without understanding.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="bruce schneier" /><category term="cory doctorow" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bruce Schneier has a great cautionary quote about technology and its tendency to be subverted:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Voluntary obsolescence: checking out of the upgrade cycle</title><link href="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/voluntary-obsolescence-checking-out-of-the-upgrade-cycle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voluntary obsolescence: checking out of the upgrade cycle" /><published>2012-01-16T01:43:37-05:00</published><updated>2012-01-16T01:43:37-05:00</updated><id>https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/voluntary-obsolescence-checking-out-of-the-upgrade-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisparker.github.io/dotnet/2012/01/voluntary-obsolescence-checking-out-of-the-upgrade-cycle/"><![CDATA[<p>This week I purchased a new cell phone. I’ve been using my current phone, an HTC Desire Z (dubbed the G2 by T-Mobile in the US), for a little over a year and it’s time for an upgrade.</p>

<p>Or maybe it’s a sidegrade. Instead of buying the newest model on the market (or waiting for one of the half a million or so introduced at CES this month) I re-bought the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nexus_One">Nexus One</a>, a phone released almost two years ago.</p>

<p>I bought my first Nexus One directly from Google when it came out, and it quickly became my all-time favorite phone. The hardware fits me perfectly — just the right weight, great screen and buttons. It’s had two follow-ups in the Nexus S and the Galaxy Nexus, but neither one has struck me the same way. Because of its background, as the first “Google Experience” phone, it fell into the hands of a lot of able hackers, and so has great community support and quick releases for the <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.com/">CyanogenMod</a> and <a href="http://www.whispersys.com/">Whisper Systems</a> software I like to use.</p>

<p>When that Nexus One was stolen in November 2010, I thought I’d appreciate the upgrade. But while the phone I got featured some souped-up specs and an upgraded OS, I just didn’t like the experience as much.</p>

<p>So for now, I’ve chosen to check out of the upgrade cycle and stick with a device that I know works for me. It’s tempting to think I’ll be out of some loop, but the truth is, the hardware I need for my phone is not that greatly different from what I needed two years ago.</p>

<p>Keeping off of the high-end upgrade cycle — because really, having the shiniest phone in your pocket is not a one-time choice, but a commitment to regular upgrades — is cheaper, less disappointing, and less likely to contribute to a mountain of stuff in my house that is just too expensive to throw away. Much better, if you know what works, to stick with it.</p>

<p>Of course, there are other approaches. Lore Sjöberg, a writer for Wired, wrote about <a href="http://www.wired.com/underwire/2009/10/alt-text-cult/">founding the Cult of the Somewhat Delayed</a> a few years back. His cult would consist of people who kept on top of the latest advances in technology and culture, but with a two-year offset. This month, devotees would be checking out the movies, news, and gadgets from January 2010, which makes my new phone a crazy device from the future.</p>

<p>Those not ready to take the two-year plunge might check out <a href="http://lastyearsmodel.org/">Last Year’s Model</a>, a project to get people to hold on to their devices a little longer. They advertise their MySpace page as a way to keep up with the project, which makes me think it’s either a bit out of date, or they’re very committed to the cause.</p>

<p>In any case, I’m happy to live at a time where the progress we can achieve in two years is enough to give the feeling of obsolescence. But I’m also happy to know that I’m not really out of the loop if I decide to skip the upgrade.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="android" /><category term="cell phones" /><category term="gadgets" /><category term="gear" /><category term="nexus one" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This week I purchased a new cell phone. I’ve been using my current phone, an HTC Desire Z (dubbed the G2 by T-Mobile in the US), for a little over a year and it’s time for an upgrade.]]></summary></entry></feed>