<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/wikipedia.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T22:31:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/wikipedia.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Honoring the history of Charleston’s Emanuel AME Church on Wikipedia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/06/honoring-the-history-of-charlestons-emanuel-ame-church-on-wikipedia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Honoring the history of Charleston’s Emanuel AME Church on Wikipedia" /><published>2015-06-19T23:15:03-04:00</published><updated>2015-06-19T23:15:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/06/honoring-the-history-of-charlestons-emanuel-ame-church-on-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/06/honoring-the-history-of-charlestons-emanuel-ame-church-on-wikipedia/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/19/us/charleston-church-shooting.html">tragedy that unfolded in Charleston this week</a> is practically beyond words: a racist gunman committing what can only be described as an act of terrorism, taking the lives of nine people who had just invited him into their bible study community. Many people have spoken much more eloquently than I’m capable of about the white supremacist system that allows, encourages this kind of violence.</p>

<p>Because yes, as horrible as these murders are, they are best understood as a symptom of a larger environment than some terrible anomaly. And other symptoms are less obvious, but profoundly tragic.</p>

<div class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_1512" style="width: 484px">![The steeple of Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church, Charleston, SC" by Spencer Means is licensed under CC BY-SA 2.0](https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/11050690653_fe970999d3_z.jpg)[“The steeple of Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church, Charleston, SC”](https://www.flickr.com/photos/hunky_punk/11050690653/) by [Spencer Means](https://www.flickr.com/photos/hunky_punk/) is licensed under [CC BY-SA 2.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/).

</div>
<p>Wikipedia articles are, for better or for worse, a metric with a disproportionate impact on people’s perception of what is valuable. Thanks to its aim to be an encyclopedia of all human knowledge and its ubiquity at the top of search results, many people use it as a shorthand evaluation of importance. This isn’t a new observation—the organizers of <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon/">the Art + Feminism Editathons</a>, for example, have pointed to studies about how <a href="http://motherboard.vice.com/read/editing-sexism-out-of-wikipedia">article lengths reflected gender bias on the site</a>.</p>

<p>Before Wednesday’s shooting, the Emanuel AME Church in Charleston had no Wikipedia page. It’s a monumentally historic place—the oldest black church in the south, co-founded by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denmark_Vesey">Denmark Vesey</a>, and has hosted the likes of Booker T. Washington and Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. And yet, its absence from the Wikipedia belied that significance. Worse, it has knock-on effects: journalists absolutely refer to Wikipedia articles to quickly get up to speed on issues, and pundits look to it for context. The history of racist violence at Emanuel AME is critical context to this week’s news, but to Wikipedia readers it might as well have not existed.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emanuel_African_Methodist_Episcopal_Church">Putting the page together</a> was one way I that could contribute positively to that conversation, and—importantly—that I could do so without centering my own voice. Wikipedia authorship is imminently knowable but generally unknown.</p>

<p>On Wednesday night I started the article and asked on Twitter for people to help. Really, my contributions were minimal—I started a stub, found a picture, and put in some references. Over the last two days, over 40 different people have made over 150 edits to the page, and it is now <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emanuel_African_Methodist_Episcopal_Church">a real and impressive article</a>. Peter Murray, a library technologist in Columbus, made this <a href="http://dltj.org/article/emanuel-african-methodist-episcopal-church-wikipedia-page-visualized/">amazing visualization of the page’s growth</a> over just a few days. It’s not there yet, but it’s getting to be the article that such a beautiful and historic site deserves.</p>

<p>And in the last two days alone, the page has been viewed 36,000 times. This stuff matters.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="charleston" /><category term="racism" /><category term="wikipedia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The tragedy that unfolded in Charleston this week is practically beyond words: a racist gunman committing what can only be described as an act of terrorism, taking the lives of nine people who had just invited him into their bible study community. Many people have spoken much more eloquently than I’m capable of about the white supremacist system that allows, encourages this kind of violence.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ex Postal Facto and mail art</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/02/ex-postal-facto-and-mail-art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ex Postal Facto and mail art" /><published>2014-02-17T01:34:50-05:00</published><updated>2014-02-17T01:34:50-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/02/ex-postal-facto-and-mail-art</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/02/ex-postal-facto-and-mail-art/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I got a chance to check out the last day of <a href="http://expostalfacto.wordpress.com/">the Ex Postal Facto conference</a>, made up of a few panels at the San Francisco Public Library. The conference was dedicated to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mail_art">mail art</a>, and today’s panels featured a handful of people that have been in that scene for decades, including these two:</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/360px-Anna_Banana_at_the_Ex_Postal_Facto_mail_art_conference.jpg" alt="360px-Anna_Banana_at_the_Ex_Postal_Facto_mail_art_conference" /><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/360px-Lowell_Darling_in_San_Francisco_February_2014.jpg" alt="360px-Lowell_Darling_in_San_Francisco,_February_2014" /></p>

<p>Those are pictures I took today of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Banana">Anna Banana</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lowell_Darling">Lowell Darling</a>. (I added Anna’s to her existing Wikipedia article, and created a new one for Lowell.)</p>

<p>I wasn’t really familiar with mail art at all and after today I feel like I’ve been missing out. But you could hardly get a better introduction than the one I had today: incredibly friendly leaders of the community having a great time meeting in person and sharing stories about the 40+ year history of the art movement.</p>

<p>Actually, it felt a lot like a hacker conference, but for a totally different community.</p>

<p>Speaking of hacker parallels, I was struck by how the timelines of the mail art community and the golden age of phone phreaking lined up. It’s really striking because in neither case was it really facilitated by new technical developments. Rather it was just people digging in and really exploring the communications networks they were using.</p>

<p>I had a great time and plan to dig more into mail art in the next few weeks. One fun project might be to try to find a cheap pinhole perforator to make <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artistamp">artistamps</a>—or to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gaCn7HWJ1YU">fashion one out of an old sewing machine</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="libraries" /><category term="mail art" /><category term="san francisco" /><category term="wikipedia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I got a chance to check out the last day of the Ex Postal Facto conference, made up of a few panels at the San Francisco Public Library. The conference was dedicated to mail art, and today’s panels featured a handful of people that have been in that scene for decades, including these two:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art+Feminism Wikipedia edit-a-thon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art+Feminism Wikipedia edit-a-thon" /><published>2014-02-03T04:11:30-05:00</published><updated>2014-02-03T04:11:30-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/02/artfeminism-wikipedia-edit-a-thon/"><![CDATA[<p>I had a great time this weekend editing Wikipedia at the San Francisco satellite of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Meetup/ArtAndFeminism">Art+Feminism edit-a-thon</a>. Check out the venue:</p>

<p><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/BfaobBGCMAE0C4N.jpg" alt="Art and Feminism edit-a-thon" /></p>

<p>There were a few dozen people there, mostly new to editing, all excited to contribute some work. And we got a lot of great stuff done! I spent most of the day teaching people how to use the markup (lots of people needed additional help with the citation format) and finding information about the reclusive but increasingly popular artist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutz_Bacher">Lutz Bacher</a>. I hadn’t heard of her before, but in the course of putting together that article I became very interested. I am now trying to get my hands on an early copy of a new major book of her work to see if there’s anything I can add to her bio.</p>

<p>It’s always great to see people make their first few edits, and people were so excited to make a new page and all of a sudden have the thing actually be there and available online. I think that Wikipedia’s ubiquity has really had a lot of influence on that process: people have used hundreds or thousands of articles before, and now they can actually make their own, and it’s a full-fledged part of the site immediately. That’s great.</p>

<p>Another fun thing was talking to people about copyright. Obviously, since the event focused on artists, people wanted to include images and art from the subjects. Sometimes I feel that the case for copyright reform and a freer culture requires a lot of abstraction, but this situation was dramatic and concrete. I probably converted a number of new copyfighters that day.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Meetup/ArtAndFeminism#Results">The results</a> are impressive: dozens of new articles created, dozens more cleaned up or improved, and countless new people editing Wikipedia and slowly—but surely—improving the quality of representation for all kinds of issues.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="san francisco" /><category term="wikipedia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had a great time this weekend editing Wikipedia at the San Francisco satellite of the Art+Feminism edit-a-thon. Check out the venue:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Wikipedia article: Michael S. Rogers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/01/new-wikipedia-article-michael-s-rogers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Wikipedia article: Michael S. Rogers" /><published>2014-01-26T19:10:04-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-26T19:10:04-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/01/new-wikipedia-article-michael-s-rogers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2014/01/new-wikipedia-article-michael-s-rogers/"><![CDATA[<p>For the first time in a long time I have started a new article on the Wikipedia. This one’s about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_S._Rogers">Michael S. Rogers</a>, Navy Vice Admiral and presumptive nominee for Director of the NSA and head of the U.S. Cyber Command. These two jobs are the one being vacated by General Keith Alexander after he retires in mid-March, and obviously it’ll be kind of a crazy time to be taking over the NSA.</p>

<p>I thought a long time ago that it would be harder and harder to create new Wikipedia articles as most everything is covered by the million-plus pages on the site. But of course, the list of notable things will never stop growing right alongside.</p>

<p>It seemed especially important that Michael S. Rogers have a page now, because he’s likely to be in the news a lot more if he actually does get the nomination, and it’s perilously easy to confuse him with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Rogers_(Michigan_politician)">Michigan Representative Mike Rogers</a>, Chairman of the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence. ((And there’s actually <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_D._Rogers">a second Representative Mike Rogers</a> in the House from Alabama.)) These two men have a lot of overlap in their jobs, it’ll be interesting to see how the national security community decides to disambiguate them.</p>

<p>It’s also nice that there’s a public domain photograph of the guy from his Navy bio. That made the page come together and look like a real encyclopedia article quickly. I’d forgotten the feeling I get when I first make an article—I keep hoping somebody else will come along and edit and add and flesh the thing out. I guess that will happen pretty quickly if he gets nominated and confirmed.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="michael s rogers" /><category term="nsa" /><category term="wikipedia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the first time in a long time I have started a new article on the Wikipedia. This one’s about Michael S. Rogers, Navy Vice Admiral and presumptive nominee for Director of the NSA and head of the U.S. Cyber Command. These two jobs are the one being vacated by General Keith Alexander after he retires in mid-March, and obviously it’ll be kind of a crazy time to be taking over the NSA.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The impossibility of imagining information retrieval in the past</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2012/04/the-impossibility-of-imagining-information-discovery-in-the-past/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The impossibility of imagining information retrieval in the past" /><published>2012-04-28T23:04:32-04:00</published><updated>2012-04-28T23:04:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2012/04/the-impossibility-of-imagining-information-discovery-in-the-past</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2012/04/the-impossibility-of-imagining-information-discovery-in-the-past/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>It’s harder to imagine the past that went away than it is to imagine the future. What we were prior to our latest batch of technology is, in a way, unknowable. It would be harder to accurately imagine what New York City was like the day before the advent of broadcast television than to imagine what it will be like after life-size broadcast holography comes online. But actually the New York without the television is more mysterious, because we’ve already been there and nobody paid any attention. That world is gone.</p>

  <p>My great-grandfather was born into a world where there was no recorded music. It’s very, very difficult to conceive of a world in which there is no possibility of audio recording at all. Some people were extremely upset by the first Edison recordings. It nauseated them, terrified them. It sounded like the devil, they said, this evil unnatural technology that offered the potential of hearing the dead speak. We don’t think about that when we’re driving somewhere and turn on the radio. We take it for granted.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>–<a href="http://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/6089/the-art-of-fiction-no-211-william-gibson">William Gibson, interviewed in the Paris Review no. 211</a></p>

<p>There’s a whole class of information that’s both trivially easy for Web-literate people to access today and virtually impossible to access with tools from even 10 or 15 years ago.</p>

<p>I’ve thought about this fact for a while, and one of my favorite examples has been the names of members of a band. It’s one Google or Wikipedia search away, but as Gibson suggests above, I almost cannot conceive of how to determine this without those tools.</p>

<p>Seriously: what could you do? Such information would not likely be in an encyclopedia, and maybe not in any printed reference books. You could ask at a record store, or call a radio station or the label they were on (after finding a number on the back of an LP, in a catalog, or calling an operator in the city in which they were based).</p>

<p>I’d used that example to describe the phenomenon for a long time before finding one of my favorite sections of the Wikipedia, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journey_%28band%29#Timeline">timeline of the members of Journey</a>, ((It’s also dynamically generated with a plug-in called Timeline, which makes it semantically significant and editable. It’s a pretty incredible thing.)) embedded teeny-tiny here:</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journey_%28band%29#Timeline"><img src="https://parkerhiggins.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/Screen-Shot-2012-04-28-at-7.38.48-PM.png" alt="" title="Timeline of the members of Journey" /></a></p>

<p>The difference is incredible. And it’s easier (for me at least) to imagine getting this information through an augmented reality pop-up or piped into a heads-up display than to get it in any analog way.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="future" /><category term="google" /><category term="information" /><category term="journey" /><category term="paris review" /><category term="wikipedia" /><category term="william gibson" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s harder to imagine the past that went away than it is to imagine the future. What we were prior to our latest batch of technology is, in a way, unknowable. It would be harder to accurately imagine what New York City was like the day before the advent of broadcast television than to imagine what it will be like after life-size broadcast holography comes online. But actually the New York without the television is more mysterious, because we’ve already been there and nobody paid any attention. That world is gone. My great-grandfather was born into a world where there was no recorded music. It’s very, very difficult to conceive of a world in which there is no possibility of audio recording at all. Some people were extremely upset by the first Edison recordings. It nauseated them, terrified them. It sounded like the devil, they said, this evil unnatural technology that offered the potential of hearing the dead speak. We don’t think about that when we’re driving somewhere and turn on the radio. We take it for granted.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Britannica, bookstores, and bundle failure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2012/03/britannica-bookstores-and-bundled-values/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Britannica, bookstores, and bundle failure" /><published>2012-03-18T22:56:08-04:00</published><updated>2012-03-18T22:56:08-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2012/03/britannica-bookstores-and-bundled-values</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2012/03/britannica-bookstores-and-bundled-values/"><![CDATA[<p>Tim Carmody’s <a href="http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2012/03/wikipedia-didnt-kill-brittanica-windows-did/">Wired opinion piece about Wikipedia, Windows, and the Britannica</a> is the best piece of commentary to come out of the vaunted encyclopedia’s announcement this week that they’re <a href="http://www.britannica.com/blogs/2012/03/change/">discontinuing their print edition</a> to focus on their online product.</p>

<p>Not to diminish Wikipedia’s importance in the encyclopedia world and Britannica’s decision, but there are a lot of reasons why a choice made in 1768 to distribute 32 volumes of printed book might be worth re-evaluating in 2012. Wikipedia’s open and collaborative authorship <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Errors_in_the_Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica_that_have_been_corrected_in_Wikipedia">certainly has its advantages</a>, but Carmody identifies a more important difference between the two organizations: Britannica’s business depended on the books being seen as a “marker of prestige.” As the PC toppled the encyclopedia as the “purchasable ‘edge’ for over-anxious parents,” the bundle fell apart and the value proposition no longer made sense for most of the market.</p>

<p>Far from being <a href="http://gigaom.com/2012/03/14/encyclopedias-are-like-journalism-its-better-when-they-are-open/">the inevitable victory of open over closed</a> then, Britannica’s announcement represents the complex result of values decoupled. This story is especially important for independent bookstores and public libraries to understand; they are subject to the same forces.</p>

<p>A little over two years ago, Clay Shirky wrote a great essay about <a href="http://www.shirky.com/weblog/2009/11/local-bookstores-social-hubs-and-mutualization/">local bookstores as a social hub</a> that speaks to this problem. In both cases, sales numbers are easily measured and easy to fixate on, but they are secondary to factors that are much less easily measured. For Britannica consumers, there’s the value of owning a 32-volume printed encyclopedia. That value might just not exist anymore; if that’s true, they’ve made the right decision to move away from a printed edition. (It’s probably true. According to <a href="http://mediadecoder.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/03/13/after-244-years-encyclopaedia-britannica-stops-the-presses/">the New York Times article about the announcement</a>, less than 1% of Britannica’s revenue was coming from print sales.)</p>

<p>But there are still many compelling arguments for the side-effect values of a bookstore or library as an inviting physical space dedicated to the exchange of information, even as communities and their information consumption preferences change. Keeping the bookstore’s ability to deliver these values coupled with the sale of paper books would be a mistake.</p>

<p>Institutions like bookstores and libraries (and newspapers, record labels, movie studios, etc.) are all dealing to a greater or lesser extent with the problem of bundle failure. That is to say: they can no longer count on subsidizing the real value they deliver with more monetizable ancillary functions. Instead, they have to take a critical look at what people value about them and figure out how to charge for it.</p>

<p>I’m sure it was a hard decision after a quarter millennium of print, but Britannica made the right move jettisoning a product that people weren’t interested in to focus on the one that they were. I really want bookstores and libraries to continue to succeed in the years to come, in no small part because I value the products and services they provide that I can’t directly pay for. I hope they can do the introspection to separate their core values from their most easily-measured ones in order to make the difficult decisions to make it work.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="bookstores" /><category term="britannica" /><category term="clay shirky" /><category term="libraries" /><category term="tim carmody" /><category term="wikipedia" /><category term="wired" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tim Carmody’s Wired opinion piece about Wikipedia, Windows, and the Britannica is the best piece of commentary to come out of the vaunted encyclopedia’s announcement this week that they’re discontinuing their print edition to focus on their online product.]]></summary></entry></feed>