<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/writing.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-18T18:13:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/tag/writing.xml</id><title type="html">parker higgins dot net</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets: my correct opinion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2018/08/twitter-should-allow-users-to-hide-old-tweets-my-correct-opinion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets: my correct opinion" /><published>2018-08-05T15:29:02-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T15:29:02-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2018/08/twitter-should-allow-users-to-hide-old-tweets-my-correct-opinion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2018/08/twitter-should-allow-users-to-hide-old-tweets-my-correct-opinion/"><![CDATA[<p>Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets so that they are only visible to that user, and selectively “un-hide” individual tweets from that collection so that they once again become available at their original URL, in quote tweets and threads, and in sites where they are embedded around the web.</p>

<p>The need for a mechanism to remove old tweets is very clear and becoming abundantly moreso with <a href="https://www.mediamatters.org/blog/2018/07/27/In-their-own-words-the-online-far-rights-motive-to-dig-up-liberal-figures-old-tweets-reven/220827">every rightwing campaign trawling for old statements to weaponize</a> by taking out of context. Numerous guides have been written about how and why to delete your tweets, and it’s beyond the scope of the argument I’m making today. Many of these guides, too, address the emotional difficulty of actually pulling the trigger and wiping an archive—in many cases spanning a decade or so of interaction.</p>

<p>One of the best encapsulations of this problem (and that solution) is John Herrman’s Awl 2015 piece <a href="https://www.theawl.com/2015/08/time-is-a-privacy-setting/">“Time Is a Privacy Setting.”</a> Even just the phrase in the headline is an important contribution, and gets at why simple dichotomies of “public” and “private” are so unsatisfying. A lot more goes into our understanding of privacy than a binary toggle, and time is certainly a factor.</p>

<p>And just as interesting, to me, is something Herrman said this week, in a tweet thread that began with his a link to that now three-year-old essay: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180805181404/https:/twitter.com/jwherrman/status/1024402382615142405">“You thought you were talking, but you were writing.”</a> It’s true! Twitter has managed, for many people, to clear out a barrier that can otherwise be insurmountable, letting people be comfortable writing down their thoughts and conversations. Something the tweet-deleters flirt with, but never seem to quite put their finger on, is that writing (as opposed to talking) has some real advantages in addition to the drawbacks.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>This observation is obviously not new to Twitter. My father, a writer, has always exhorted me to keep a journal or a diary, though I’ve never really been able to. One real value of Twitter, for me, has been breaking through that hesitation by setting the threshold of participation so incredibly low that I can just, y’know, write. It’d be better to keep a journal or to blog, but in many cases tweets are good enough.</p>

<p>Over the decade that I’ve been on Twitter, I’ve gone through periods of prolific writing and total dry spells. I’ve maintained this blog regularly at times, and at others it’s sat dormant for months. And the thing is, I frequently refer to and read the old entries for time periods where they exist! Human memory is fickle and fragile, and it is genuinely interesting and educational for me to look back on old writing and see the germs of ideas that later grew into real passions. Looking up old tweets isn’t quite as good, but it fills in the gaps.</p>

<p>Beyond just lowering the threshold to producing such writing, Twitter did some important things to make online writing even more valuable. Search, the villain in recent sagas, is a powerful tool when used for good. Joanne McNeil recently raised a use case I love:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">One of my favorite things things to do on twitter is search my friends’ old tweets for their reactions over the years to whatever film or book I just finished</p>&mdash; joanne mcneil (@jomc) <a href="https://twitter.com/jomc/status/1025085686947430401?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 2, 2018</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>I do that too! Yes, it’d be great if all my friends blogged about every movie they watched or book they read (and I had a good way of finding those posts when they became relevant to me), but this is a decent runner-up. If you want, too, you can see first interactions with people who later became important to you, or <a href="https://waxy.org/2015/12/tracking_the_trump_is_a_comment_section_running_for_president_joke/">all the people who’ve made a joke</a> you just thought of, or people discussing an article you’ve just read, and Twitter (helpfully, in this case) collapses the time gap between you and those people.</p>

<p>Beyond that, Twitter puts a time stamp and a URL on each of these things. In recent years it even preserves the semantics of threads. I don’t want to downplay the very real harm these attributes can cause, but it’s also true that in some situations they provide a ton of value.</p>

<p>Which brings us back to tweet deletion and why it is emotionally difficult for people to do. For better or for worse, this archive we’ve created of our own writing is valuable, and deleting tweets is permanent. (<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/im-deleting-all-my-old-tweets/">Emily Dreyfuss’ article at Wired</a> does an especially good job at grappling with it.) Every guide I’ve read to deleting tweets walks through the process of creating an “archive,” but even doing so misses some of these benefits of keeping old tweets online.</p>

<p>Archiving-then-deleting may preserve a copy for you, but it permanently rips each tweet out of its context in threads, at a URL, within quote tweets, embedded in articles, and in the Search index.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Maybe you want to do all those things, and you should have the power to do so! But with a corpus of tens of thousands of tweets, in many cases, it is overwhelming to permanently make that decision for everything all at once.</p>

<p>(Side note: that permanence is in large part a result of Twitter’s centralization. Under a more decentralized model,<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> where we controlled our own domains, you could maybe just rebuild your database from a backup and point all the right URLs to all the right content. There’s pros and cons to such centralization—and in particular, people seem to love the guarantee that the archive hasn’t been tampered with—but in any case that’s the situation we’re in and what can you do.)</p>

<p>So here’s the solution, referred to up top. Twitter should give users a new option to “hide” old tweets, which would look to every other user like deletion, but which would be a reversible operation. Your hidden tweets should still appear in your searches and views of old threads, but greyed out to indicate they’re not otherwise available. And—and this is probably the hardest part—Twitter should introduce a per-tweet configurability for these settings.</p>

<p>That’s the kicker. Individual tweets could be deleted (fully gone), hidden (just for you), private (for your followers, no retweets), or public. That would be a big change! But it’s important.</p>

<p>(Another side note: when I posted this opinion on Twitter, I got a few responses that such an option should not be available for public figures or politicians or what-have-you. I tend to think that we should not rely on Twitter to preserve these public records, and that their introduction of a feature that has real benefits to real users shouldn’t be hindered by the possible exploitation by shifty officials. And just as with <a href="https://theconversation.com/donald-trumps-tweets-are-now-presidential-records-71973">deleting tweets</a> or <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/23/business/media/trump-twitter-block.html">blocking critics</a>, the behavior can be barred without Twitter needing to intervene.)</p>

<p>Twitter the company has mismanaged Twitter the product in a dozen different ways, and its policies on speech, censorship, harassment, and abuse have often been incoherent. It’s also provided an invaluable platform for many of my favorite writers and thinkers, and done so in a way that is reasonably consistent with the technology of the web.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> Giving users more tools—in this case a new privacy setting with more granularity—is the right next step in overcoming the former without diminishing the latter.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>By definition, most of the articles about deleting tweets are written by writers. Writers, again by definition, tend to write more stuff down. So maybe the benefits of having a place to write stuff down if you otherwise wouldn’t isn’t quite as clear to them. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Beyond that, there’s no easy way to present your archive on your own terms to anybody but yourself, a <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2017/04/building-mastodon-frozen/">feature I’ve argued for in other contexts</a>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Check out <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a>. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Two good things that stand out: canonical URLs for every tweet, and the fact that unavailable embedded tweets degrade gracefully into text. On the other hand, the normalization and ubiquitous use of a URL shortener sucks. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="mastodon" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="twitter" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter should allow users to “hide” old tweets so that they are only visible to that user, and selectively “un-hide” individual tweets from that collection so that they once again become available at their original URL, in quote tweets and threads, and in sites where they are embedded around the web.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Archiving threatened outlets for the Freedom of the Press Foundation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2018/03/archiving-threatened-outlets-for-the-freedom-of-the-press-foundation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Archiving threatened outlets for the Freedom of the Press Foundation" /><published>2018-03-12T23:07:24-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-12T23:07:24-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2018/03/archiving-threatened-outlets-for-the-freedom-of-the-press-foundation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2018/03/archiving-threatened-outlets-for-the-freedom-of-the-press-foundation/"><![CDATA[<p>A little over a month ago, I launched one of the Special Projects I’ve been working on at my new job at the <a href="https://freedom.press">Freedom of the Press Foundation</a>. The <a href="https://archive-it.org/collections/9790">Threatened Outlets collection at Archive-It</a> aims to capture the archives of news sites that we deem vulnerable to “the billionaire problem,” wherein wealthy individuals or organizations can eliminate unflattering coverage through litigation or by purchasing media companies altogether. From <a href="https://freedom.press/news/archiving-alternative-press-threatened-wealthy-buyers/">the launch announcement</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Those efforts help individual journalists. But another important thing we can do to reduce the effectiveness of this kind of attack on press freedom is to commit ourselves to the wholesale preservation of threatened sites.</p>

  <p>In this case, we seek to reduce the “upside” for wealthy individuals and organizations who would eliminate embarrassing or unflattering coverage by purchasing outlets outright. In other words, we hope that sites that can’t simply be made to disappear will show some immunity to the billionaire problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To my surprise and delight, our launch received some nice and encouraging coverage, in <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/gawker-archives-freedom-of-press-foundation-toast-la-weekly/">WIRED</a>, <a href="https://beta.techcrunch.com/2018/02/01/freedom-of-the-press-foundation-will-preserve-gawkers-archives/">TechCrunch</a>, <a href="https://thenextweb.com/insider/2018/01/31/meet-archivists-saving-alt-news-sites-permanent-deletion/">The Next Web</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/01/business/media/gawker-archives-press-freedom.html">The New York Times</a>, and others. Sometimes when you’ve got your head down on something that feels like a niche topic, it’s nice to come up for air and realize that the general public is interested, too.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="archives" /><category term="freedom of the press foundation" /><category term="gawker" /><category term="internet archive" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A little over a month ago, I launched one of the Special Projects I’ve been working on at my new job at the Freedom of the Press Foundation. The Threatened Outlets collection at Archive-It aims to capture the archives of news sites that we deem vulnerable to “the billionaire problem,” wherein wealthy individuals or organizations can eliminate unflattering coverage through litigation or by purchasing media companies altogether. From the launch announcement:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All of my Deeplinks blog posts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2017/01/all-eff-deeplinks-blog-posts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All of my Deeplinks blog posts" /><published>2017-01-18T19:39:51-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-18T19:39:51-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2017/01/all-eff-deeplinks-blog-posts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2017/01/all-eff-deeplinks-blog-posts/"><![CDATA[<p>After five amazing years, I’m done (for now) at EFF. It’s impossible to boil the experience down into numbers, but here’s a big one: 215 Deeplinks blog posts bear my name as author. Here they are, collected in one place for posterity. After the <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2013/08/my-first-100-eff-deeplinks/">first hundred</a> and the <a href="https://parkerhiggins.net/2015/09/200-deeplinks-at-eff/">second hundred</a>, I picked out some of my favorites.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/07/research-and-remixes-law-wont-allow">Research and Remixes the Law Won’t Allow</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/06/canadas-entry-treaty-blind-will-come-force">With Canada’s Entry, Treaty for the Blind Will Come Into Force</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/05/eff-applauds-jury-verdict-favor-fair-use-oracle-v-google">EFF Applauds Jury Verdict In Favor of Fair Use in Oracle v. Google</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/05/stakes-are-high-oracle-v-google-public-has-already-lost-big">Stakes Are High in Oracle v. Google, But the Public Has Already Lost Big</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/05/yes-all-drm">Yes, All DRM</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/04/app-store-censorship-and-fbi-hacking-proposed-congressional-crypto-hearing">App Store Censorship and FBI Hacking Proposed at Congressional Crypto Hearing</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/03/scenes-anti-drm-protest-outside-w3c">Scenes From Anti-DRM Protest Outside W3C</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/03/apple-all-writs-act-and-limitless-surveillance">Apple Fight Could Lead To “Virtually Limitless” Surveillance Powers, Judge Warns</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/02/government-cant-force-apple-unlock-drug-case-iphone-rules-new-york-judge">Government Can’t Force Apple to Bypass iPhone Lock Screen, New York Judge Rules</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/02/webs-first-blackout-protest-cda-20-years-later">The Web’s First Blackout Protest: The CDA, 20 Years Later</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/press/releases/eff-and-cdt-file-brief-support-airbnb">EFF and CDT File Brief in Support of Airbnb</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/02/call-stories-user-uploads-and-takedown-abuse">Call For Stories: User Uploads and Takedown Abuse</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/02/tale-two-treaties-marrakesh-and-beijing-both-make-their-way-senate">A Tale of Two Treaties: Marrakesh and Beijing Both Make Their Way to the Senate</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/01/mediums-sitewide-encryption-confronts-censorship-malaysia">Medium’s Sitewide Encryption Confronts Censorship in Malaysia</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2016/01/copyright-week-2016-making-copyright-work-public">Copyright Week 2016: Making Copyright Work For The Public</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/12/whos-driving-thing-anti-drm-victories-and-milestones-2015-review">Who’s Driving This Thing? Anti-DRM Victories and Milestones: 2015 in Review</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/12/what-eff-reading-books-movies-and-tv-shows-2015">What Is EFF Reading? Books, Movies, and TV Shows of 2015</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/12/3-d-printing-case-code-speech-faces-new-challenges">In 3-D Printing Case, “Code Is Speech” Faces New Challenges</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/11/free-router-software-not-crosshairs-fcc-clarifies">Free Router Software Not In The Crosshairs, FCC Clarifies</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/11/4-key-takeaways-copyright-reform-committees-silicon-valley-listening-tour">4 Key Takeaways From Copyright Reform Committee’s Silicon Valley Listening Tour</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/11/aaron-swartz-hackathon-weekend-your-chance-hack-better-world">Aaron Swartz Hackathon This Weekend Is Your Chance To Hack for a Better World</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/10/victory-users-librarian-congress-renews-and-expands-protections-fair-uses">Victory for Users: Librarian of Congress Renews and Expands Protections for Fair Uses</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/10/apples-eula-gives-it-license-invade-your-privacy-government-claims">Apple’s EULA Gives It License to Invade Your Privacy, Government Claims</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/09/tell-president-obama-save-crypto-dangerous-backdoors">Tell President Obama: Save Crypto From Dangerous Backdoors</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/09/happy-birthday-everybody-victory-public-domain-asterisk">Happy Birthday To Everybody: Victory For The Public Domain (With An Asterisk)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/09/takedown-senders-must-consider-fair-use-ninth-circuit-rules">Takedown Senders Must Consider Fair Use, Ninth Circuit Rules</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/09/library-suspends-tor-node-after-dhs-intimidation">Library Suspends Tor Node After DHS Intimidation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/08/russias-wikipedia-ban-buckles-under-https-encryption">Russia’s Wikipedia Ban Buckles Under HTTPS Encryption</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/08/twitter-axes-accountability-projects-sparing-politicians-embarrassment">Twitter Axes Accountability Projects, Sparing Politicians Embarrassment</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/07/public-interest-groups-and-over-thousand-users-call-copyright-office-affirm-its">Public Interest Groups and Over a Thousand Users Call on the Copyright Office to Affirm Its Call for Sensible Copyright Policy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/07/copyright-office-belongs-library">The Copyright Office Belongs in a Library</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/07/what-do-we-want-next-librarian-congress">What Do We Want From the Next Librarian of Congress?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/07/tpp-copyright-trap-our-last-stand-against-undemocratic-international-agreements">TPP’s Copyright Trap</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/07/eff-25th-anniversary-minicon-details">EFF’s 25th Anniversary Minicon Preview</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/05/logjam-part-2-did-nsa-know-years-internet-was-broken">Logjam, Part 2: Did the NSA Know the Internet Was Broken?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/05/unexpected-policy-laundering-implications-garcia-v-google-dissent-reverse-policy">The Unexpected Policy Laundering Implications of the Garcia v. Google Dissent</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/05/phase-out-drm-and-legal-regimes-support-it-international-day-against-drm">Phase Out DRM and the Legal Regimes That Support It: International Day Against DRM</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/04/help-free-pacer-san-francisco-and-new-york-friday">Help Free PACER in San Francisco and New York This Friday</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/04/calling-all-new-yorkers-speak-fair-repair">Calling all New Yorkers: Speak Up for Fair Repair</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/04/investigative-reporting-mpaas-sopa-revival-effort-wins-pulitzer">Investigative Reporting on MPAA’s SOPA Revival Effort Wins Pulitzer</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/04/clipper-chips-birthday-looking-back-22-years-key-escrow-failures">On the Clipper Chip’s Birthday, Looking Back on Decades of Key Escrow Failures</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/04/not-just-space-photos-flickr-now-allows-all-users-expand-public-domain">Not Just Space Photos: Flickr Now Allows All Users To Expand the Public Domain</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/03/locking-public-access-scientific-knowledge-unlocking-scholarly-research">Locking In Public Access to Scientific Knowledge by Unlocking Scholarly Research</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/02/big-brother-listening-users-need-ability-teach-smart-tvs-new-lessons">Big Brother Is Listening: Users Need the Ability To Teach Smart TVs New Lessons</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/02/song-still-belongs-you-and-me">This Song (Still) Belongs to You and Me</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/02/who-really-owns-your-drones">Who Really Owns Your Drones?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2015/01/its-copyright-week-lets-take-copyright-back">It’s Copyright Week: Let’s Take Copyright Back</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/three-vulnerabilities-rocked-online-security-world-2014-review">Three Vulnerabilities That Rocked the Online Security World: 2014 in Review</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/effs-must-reads-and-must-sees-books-and-movies-2014">EFF’s Must-Reads and Must-Sees: Books and Movies of 2014</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/hollywood-funds-sopa-revival-through-state-officials-google-and-internet-respond">As Hollywood Funds a SOPA Revival Through State Officials, Google (And The Internet) Respond </a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/crossword-puzzle-year-copyright-news">Crossword Puzzle 2014: The Year in Copyright News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/important-innocence-muslims-copyright-case-be-re-argued-monday">Important “Innocence of Muslims” Copyright Case To Be Re-Argued Monday</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/pointing-users-drm-stripping-software-isnt-copyright-infringement-judge-rules">Pointing Users to DRM-Stripping Software Isn’t Copyright Infringement, Judge Rules</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/12/demanding-us-trade-negotiators-publish-their-public-records">EFF Demands US Trade Negotiators Publish Their Public Records</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/11/and-games-play-eff-fights-users-rights-play-and-preserve-abandoned-video-games">And The Games Play On: EFF Fights For Users’ Rights to Play and Preserve Abandoned Video Games</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/11/jailbreaking-not-crime-and-eff-fighting-keep-it-way">Jailbreaking Is Not A Crime—And EFF Is Fighting To Keep It That Way</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/10/7-privacy-tools-essential-making-citizenfour">The 7 Privacy Tools Essential to Making Snowden Documentary CITIZENFOUR</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/08/def-con-router-hacking-contest-success-fun-learning-and-profit-many">DEFCON Router Hacking Contest Reveals 15 Major Vulnerabilities</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/09/tell-governor-brown-no-warrantless-drone-use-california-cops">Tell Governor Brown: No Warrantless Drones For California Cops</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/09/new-company-transparency-reports-help-quantify-dmca-abuse">New Company Transparency Reports Help Quantify DMCA Abuse</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/09/eff-congress-get-rid-dmcas-anti-circumvention-provisions">EFF to Congress: Get Rid of DMCA’s “Anti-Circumvention” Provisions</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/08/cell-phone-guide-protesters-updated-2014-edition">Cell Phone Guide For US Protesters, Updated 2014 Edition</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/07/phone-unlocking-victory-should-be-first-step-towards-real-copyright-reform">The Phone Unlocking Victory Should Be the First Step Towards Real Copyright Reform</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/07/un-human-rights-report-and-turning-tide-against-mass-spying">UN Human Rights Report and the Turning Tide Against Mass Spying</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/07/congress-takes-copyright-term-moral-rights-and-more">Congress Takes On Copyright Term, Moral Rights, and More</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/07/releasing-public-domain-image-nsas-utah-data-center">Releasing a Public Domain Image of the NSA’s Utah Data Center</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/07/forward-secrecy-brings-better-long-term-privacy-wikipedia">Forward Secrecy Brings Better Long-Term Privacy to Wikipedia</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/06/senate-bill-brings-progress-phone-unlocking">Senate Bill Brings Progress on Phone Unlocking</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/06/another-fair-use-victory-book-scanning-hathitrust">Another Fair Use Victory for Book Scanning in HathiTrust</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/05/eff-copyight-office-fair-use-can-help-fix-orphan-works-problem">EFF to Copyright Office: Fair Use Can Help Fix the Orphan Works Problem</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/05/how-drm-harms-our-computer-security">How DRM Harms Our Computer Security</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/04/aereo-cant-be-bound-secret-interpretations-copyright-law">Aereo Can’t Be Bound by Secret Interpretations of Copyright Law</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/04/without-intellectual-property-day">Without Intellectual Property Day</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/04/aereo-supreme-court-rightly-skeptical-about-becoming-technology-regulators">In Aereo, Supreme Court Rightly Skeptical About Becoming Technology Regulators</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/04/eff-supports-cafepress-safe-harbor-claim">EFF Supports CafePress Safe Harbor Claim</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/04/australian-attorney-general-picks-surveillance-over-fair-use-us-visit">Australian Attorney General Picks Surveillance Over Fair Use on U.S. Visit</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/03/culture-enriches-everything-fair-use-and-office-time-machine">Culture Enriches Everything: Fair Use and The Office Time Machine</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/03/bringing-transparency-and-democracy-us-trade-rep">Bringing Transparency and Democracy to the US Trade Representative</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/03/eff-supports-washington-drone-bill">EFF Urges Washington to Pass Drone Bill</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/03/tech-companies-urge-senator-wyden-reject-fast-track-and-bring-transparency-tpp">Tech Companies Urge Senator Wyden to Reject Fast Track and Bring Transparency to TPP</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/03/notice-and-takedown-gets-its-day-congress">Notice-and-Takedown Gets its Day in Congress</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/11/encrypt-web-report-whos-doing-what">UPDATE: Encrypt the Web Report: Who’s Doing What</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/03/getty-images-allows-free-embedding-cost-privacy">Getty Images Allows Free Embedding, but at What Cost to Privacy?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/02/fair-use-may-be-headed-down-under">Fair Use May Be Headed Down Under</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/02/how-big-was-day-we-fight-back">How Big Was The Day We Fight Back?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/making-the-mobile-web-safer-with-https-everywhere">Making the Mobile Web Safer with HTTPS Everywhere</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/fair-use-takes-center-stage-judiciary-committee-hearing">Fair Use Takes Center Stage at Judiciary Committee Hearing</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/rating-obamas-nsa-reform-plan-eff-scorecard-explained">Rating Obama’s NSA Reform Plan: EFF Scorecard Explained</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/celebrating-fair-use-copyright-week">Celebrating Fair Use for Copyright Week</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/welcome-copyright-week">Copyright Week: Taking Copyright Back</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2014/01/remembering-aaron">Remembering Aaron</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/2013-review-trans-pacific-partnership-agreement">2013 in Review: The Trans-Pacific Partnership Agreement</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/your-android-reader-reading-you">What Do Your Android Reader Apps Know About You?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/increasing-anti-surveillance-momentum-and-necessary-and-proportionate-principles">Increasing Anti-Surveillance Momentum and the Necessary and Proportionate Principles</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/effs-reading-list-books-2013">EFF’s Reading List: Books of 2013</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/supporting-best-practices-open-government-data">Supporting Best Practices for Open Government Data</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/tpps-attack-artists-termination-rights">The TPP’s Attack on Artists’ Termination Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/tpp-wont-wrap-year-fast-track-still-threat">TPP Won’t Wrap Up This Year, But Fast Track Remains a Threat</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/12/2013-review-voluntary-copyright-agreements">2013 in Review: “Voluntary” Copyright Agreements</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/11/creative-commons-issues-update-its-copyright-license-suite">Creative Commons Issues an Update to its Copyright License Suite</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/11/fcc-chairmans-phone-unlocking-fix-good-start-consumers-need-more">FCC Chairman’s Phone Unlocking Fix Is a Good Start, But Consumers Need More</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/11/drm-cars-will-drive-consumers-crazy">DRM in Cars Will Drive Consumers Crazy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/11/tpp-leak-confirms-worst-us-negotiators-still-trying-trade-away-internet-freedoms">TPP Leak Confirms the Worst: US Negotiators Still Trying to Trade Away Internet Freedoms</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/11/aaron-swartz-hackathons-weekend-continue-his-work">Aaron Swartz Hackathons This Weekend to Continue his Work</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/mobile-tracking-code-conduct-falls-short-protecting-consumers">Mobile Tracking Code of Conduct Falls Short of Protecting Consumers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/public-interest-coalition-letter-no-fast-track-authority-trans-pacific-partnership">Public Interest Coalition Opposes Fast-Track Authority for the Trans-Pacific Partnership</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/hollywood-take-note-new-website-shows-movie-watchers-cant-get-what-they-want">Hollywood, Take Note: New Website Shows Movie Watchers Can’t Get What They Want</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/creative-commons-policy-statement-supports-real-copyright-reform">Creative Commons Policy Statement Supports Real Copyright Reform</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/10/silk-road-case-dont-blame-technology">In the Silk Road Case, Don’t Blame the Technology</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/09/copyright-masquerade-corporate-lobbying-takes-spotlight">In “A Copyright Masquerade,” Corporate Lobbying Takes the Spotlight</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/09/dear-playboy-eff-defends-groups-targeted-bogus-takedowns">Dear Playboy: Don’t Abuse Trademark Law to Silence Critics</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/09/copyright-industries-pushing-search-engine-voluntary-agreements-despite-risks">Copyright Industries Pushing for Search Engine “Voluntary Agreements,” Despite Risks to Users</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/09/how-bad-supreme-court-decision-might-have-good-constitutional-consequences">How a Bad Supreme Court Decision Could Have Good Constitutional Consequences for Copyright</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/pushing-perfect-forward-secrecy-important-web-privacy-protection">Pushing for Perfect Forward Secrecy, an Important Web Privacy Protection</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/intelligence-agency-attorney-explains-how-multi-communication-transactions-allowed">Intelligence Agency Attorney on How “Multi-Communication Transactions” Allowed for Domestic Surveillance</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/microsoft-reverses-another-anti-user-xbox-one-policy">Microsoft Reverses (Another) Anti-User Xbox One Policy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/07/markup-brings-minor-improvements-phone-unlocking-bandaid-bill">Markup Brings Minor Improvements to Phone Unlocking “Bandaid Bill”</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/07/google-news-doesnt-index-https-sites-bad-policy-reader-privacy">Bad News For Reader Privacy: Google News Doesn’t Index HTTPS Sites</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/07/fair-use-creep-and-other-copyright-bogeymen-appear-congress">“Fair Use Creep,” and Other Copyright Bogeymen, Appear in Congress</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/07/who-has-your-back-companies-demand-transparency-around-government-data-requests">Who Has Your Back? Companies Demand Transparency Around Government Data Requests</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/07/eff-rallies-protesters-restore-fourth">EFF Addresses Protesters at San Francisco’s “Restore the Fourth” Protest</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/06/through-ustr-confirmation-legislators-remain-concerned-about-lack-transparency">Obama’s Trade Rep Is Confirmed, But Legislators Remain Concerned About Secretive Trade Negotiations</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/06/call-now-to-oppose-nsa-spying">Call Now to Oppose NSA Spying</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/howto-two-factor-authentication-twitter-and-around-web">How to Enable Two-Factor Authentication on Twitter (And Everywhere Else)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/google-abandons-open-standards-instant-messaging">Google Abandons Open Standards for Instant Messaging</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/hackers-makers-and-tinkerers-heres-how-tpp-would-hurt-you">Hackers, Makers, and Tinkerers: Here’s How TPP Would Hurt You</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/new-bipartisan-bill-proposes-real-fixes-bad-copyright-law">New Bipartisan Bill Proposes Real Fixes to Bad Copyright Law</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/baking-eff-not-derby-pie-trademarked-treat">Baking With EFF: (Not) Derby Pie, the Trademarked Treat</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/prince-inducted-takedown-hall-shame-new-lifetime-aggrievement-award">Prince Inducted Into Takedown Hall of Shame With New Lifetime Aggrievement Award</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/why-isnt-gatsby-public-domain">Why Isn’t Gatsby in the Public Domain?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/05/takedown-hall-shame-inductions-may-2013">Takedown Hall of Shame Inductions, May 2013</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/04/only-thing-broadcasting-treaty-good-crushing-innovation">The Only Thing the Broadcasting Treaty Is Good For Is Crushing Innovation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/04/new-bill-would-make-bad-copyright-and-trade-policy-even-worse">A “Hollywood Ambassador” Would Make Bad Copyright Trade Policy Even Worse</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/04/copyright-trolls-offer-no-defense-frustrated-federal-judge">Copyright Trolls Offer No Defense to Frustrated Federal Judge</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/letter-congress-fix-phone-phone-unlocking-problem-and-failed-law-caused-it">Letter to Congress: Fix the Phone Unlocking Problem and the Failed Law That Caused It</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/ustr-secret-copyright-agreements-worldwide">How the US Trade Rep Ratchets Up Worldwide Copyright Laws That Could Keep Your Devices Locked Forever</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/you-bought-it-you-own-it-supreme-court-victory-common-sense-and-owners-rights">You Bought It, You Own It: Supreme Court Victory for Common Sense and Owners’ Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/updating-copyright-act-its-up-to-all-of-us">Updating the Copyright Act? It’s up to all of us.</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/win-safe-harbors-umg-v-veoh">Big Win for Safe Harbors in UMG v. Veoh</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/tale-simcity-users-struggle-against-onerous-drm">A Tale of SimCity: Users Struggle Against Onerous DRM</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/senate-demands-answers-about-aaron-swartz-more-must-be-done">Senate Demands Answers About Aaron Swartz, But More Must Be Done</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/03/white-house-supports-unlocking-phones-real-problem-runs-deeper">White House Supports Unlocking Phones — But the Real Problem Runs Deeper</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/02/alameda-county-california-sheriff-drone-protests">California Sheriff Faces Loud Privacy Protests Against Drone Plans</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/02/obama-calls-patent-reform-topple-trolls">Obama Calls for Patent Reform to Topple Trolls</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/these-are-critical-fixes-computer-fraud-and-abuse-act">Critical Fixes for the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/copyfights-next-stage-we-all-speak-together">The Copyfight’s Next Stage: We All Speak Up Together</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/what-fbi-doesnt-want-you-know-about-its-surveillance-techniques">What the FBI Doesn’t Want You To Know About Its “Secret” Surveillance Techniques</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/california-attorney-general-releases-mobile-privacy-recommendations">California Attorney General Releases Mobile Privacy Recommendations</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/copyright-vampires-attempt-suck-lifeblood-out-fair-use-video">Copyright Vampires Attempt to Suck the Lifeblood Out of Fair Use Video </a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/video-senator-ron-wyden-opposes-warrantless-surveillance">Video: Senator Ron Wyden Opposes Warrantless Surveillance</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/12/2012-review-blackout-protests-against-blacklist-bills">2012 in Review: Blackout Protests Against Blacklist Bills</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/12/open-source-software-developer-bassel-khartabil-moved-syrian-military-prison">Open Source Developer Bassel Khartabil Moved to Syrian Military Prison</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/12/calling-congress-time-fix-copyright">Calling on Congress: Time to Fix Copyright</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/11/e-reader-privacy-chart-2012-update">Who’s Tracking Your Reading Habits? An E-Book Buyer’s Guide to Privacy, 2012 Edition</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/11/congress-shouldnt-debate-copyright-reality-free-zone">Congress Shouldn’t Debate Copyright in a Reality-Free Zone</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/11/year-zero-geek-reading-san-francisco">“Year Zero” Geek Reading in San Francisco</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/10/parade-horribles-supreme-court-first-sale-kirtsaeng-v-wiley">A Parade of Horribles: Supreme Court Justices Consider the Limits of First Sale in Kirtsaeng v. Wiley</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/10/your-right-own-under-threat">Your Right to Own, Under Threat</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/10/celebrating-pioneer-award-winning-women-ada-lovelace-day">12 Pioneering Women in Tech: EFF Celebrates Ada Lovelace Day</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/10/youtube-upgrades-its-automated-copyright-enforcement-system">YouTube Upgrades Its Automated Copyright Enforcement System</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/10/sopa-dead-says-mpaas-chris-dodd-what-comes-next">SOPA Is Dead, Says MPAA’s Chris Dodd, But What Comes Next?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/09/copyrights-robot-wars-heat-algorithms-block-live-streams-first-and-ask-questions">Copyright’s Robot Wars Heat Up as Algorithms Block Live-Streams First and Ask Questions Later</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/08/research-sheds-light-on-scary-surveillance-apps">Research Sheds Light On Scary New Surveillance Apps for Smartphones</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/08/barts-cell-phone-shutdown-one-year-later">BART’s Cell Phone Shutdown, One Year Later</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/08/content-industry-war-sharing-claims-another-victim">Content Industry War on Sharing Claims Another Victim</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/08/mars-landing-videos-and-other-casualties-robot-wars">Mars Landing Videos, and Other Casualties of the Robot Wars</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/08/myvidster-victory-innovation-and-vote-sensible-copyright-law">myVidster: A Victory for Innovation and a Vote for Sensible Copyright Law</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/08/questioning-copyrights-trade-off">Questioning Copyright’s Trade-Off</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/elusive-finfisher-spyware-identified-and-analyzed">Elusive FinFisher Spyware Identified and Analyzed</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/eff-joins-epic-brief-calling-tsa-follow-law">EFF Joins EPIC With Brief Calling for TSA to Follow the Law</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/singing-obama-ad-nailed-copyright-hammer">[UPDATED] Singing Obama Ad Takedown Means More Trouble for Political Speech Online</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/eff-fcc-consumers-face-uphill-battle-fight-mobile-device-privacy">EFF to FCC: Consumers Face Uphill Battle in Fight for Mobile Device Privacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/top-10-takedowns-googles-copyright-transparency-report">Top 10 Takedowns in Google’s Copyright Transparency Report</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/eff-and-muckrock-partner-see-how-your-local-police-are-using-drones">EFF and MuckRock Partner Up to See How Your Local Police Are Using Drones</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/07/eff-joins-coalition-urging-eu-parliament-reject-acta">EFF Joins Coalition Urging EU Parliament to Reject ACTA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/06/newspaper-should-know-better-trademark-allegations-put-occupied-chicago-tribune">A Newspaper Should Know Better: Trademark Allegations Put Occupied Chicago Tribune At Risk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/06/stand-owners-rights">Stand Up for Owners’ Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/06/help-eff-find-out-how-your-local-police-agency-using-drones">Help EFF Find Out How Your Local Police Agency is Using Drones</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/06/open-access-victory-successful-access2research-petition">Open Access Victory in Successful Access2Research Petition</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/05/congressional-witnesses-agree-multistakeholderism-right-way-regulate-internet">Congressional Witnesses Agree: Multistakeholder Processes Are Right for Internet Regulation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/05/google-releases-new-copyright-transparency-report">Google Releases New Copyright Transparency Report</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/05/netherlands-passes-net-neutrality-legislation">The Netherlands Passes Net Neutrality Legislation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/05/law-professors-call-tpp-transparency">Law Professors Call for TPP Transparency</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/05/good-citizenship-online-service-providers-lets-not-let-dailykos-takedown-be">Good Citizenship for Online Service Providers: Let’s Not Let the DailyKos Takedown Be a Preview of the 2012 Campaign Season</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/05/make-every-day-day-against-drm">Make Every Day a Day Against DRM</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/04/eff-joins-two-coalition-letters-opposing-cispa">EFF Joins Two Coalition Letters Opposing CISPA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/04/trouble-trolltown">Trouble in Trolltown</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/04/hollywood-loves-sequel-really-sopa-2">Hollywood Loves a Sequel — But Really, SOPA 2?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/warning-exposure-video-game-labeling-laws-may-be-hazardous-freedom-speech">WARNING: Exposure to Video Game Labeling Laws May Be Hazardous to Freedom of Speech</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/graduated-response-deal-steamrollers-towards-july-1-launch">Graduated Response Deal Steamrollers On Towards July 1 Launch</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/highlighting-privacy-problems-apps-need-respect-user-rights-start">Highlighting a Privacy Problem: Apps Need to Respect User Rights From the Start</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/eff-takes-austin-our-picks-sxsw">EFF Takes Austin: Our Picks for SXSW</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/best-practices-respect-mobile-user-bill-rights">Mobile User Privacy Bill of Rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/02/california-ag-agreement-calls-mobile-apps-be-transparent-about-all-ways-they">California AG Agreement Calls on Mobile Apps to Be Transparent About All the Ways They Invade User Privacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/02/decade-open-access-and-challenges-ahead">A Decade of Open Access (And the Challenges Ahead)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/02/better-path-apps-respecting-users-and-their-privacy">A Better Path for Apps: Respecting Users and Their Privacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/02/dear-hollywood-open-letter-hardworking-men-and-women-entertainment-industries">Dear Hollywood: An Open Letter to the Hardworking Men and Women in the Entertainment Industries</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/01/we-have-every-right-be-furious-about-acta">We Have Every Right to Be Furious About ACTA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/01/dutch-courts-join-pirate-bay-blocking-bandwagon">Dutch Courts Join Pirate Bay Blocking Bandwagon</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/01/internet-goes-washington-january-18">The Internet Goes to Washington on January 18</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2012/01/stop-blacklist-legislation-guide-person-meetings">Stop the Blacklist Legislation: a Guide to In-Person Meetings with Your Congressional Representatives</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/2011-review-fighting-internet-blacklist-bills">2011 in Review: Fighting the Internet Blacklist Bills</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/wrapping-week-action-against-sopa">Wrapping Up a Week Of Action Against SOPA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/free-speechs-weak-links-under-internet-blacklist-bills">Free Speech’s Weak Links Under Internet Blacklist Bills</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/internet-inventors-warn-against-sopa-and-pipa">An Open Letter From Internet Engineers to the U.S. Congress</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/how-sopa-affects-students-and-educators">How SOPA Affects Students, Educators, and Libraries</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/blacklist-bills-ripe-abuse">Blacklist Bills Ripe for Abuse, Part I: “Market-Based” Systems</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/long-term-privacy-forward-secrecy">Long Term Privacy with Forward Secrecy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/protect-ip-act-very-real-very-bad-call-now-block-it">The PROTECT IP Act Is Very Real and Very Bad — Call Now to Block It</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/against-blacklist-bills-congressmen-and-senators-speak">Against the Blacklist Bills: Congressmembers and Senators Speak Up</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/sopa-down-not-yet-out">After the Hearing: SOPA Down But Not Yet Out</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/explosion-opposition-internet-blacklist-bill">An Explosion of Opposition to the Internet Blacklist Bill</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/whats-blacklist-three-sites-sopa-could-put-risk">What’s On the Blacklist? Three Sites That SOPA Could Put at Risk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/eff-mourns-passing-ilya-zhitomirskiy">EFF Mourns the Passing of Ilya Zhitomirskiy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://eff.org/deeplinks/2011/11/american-censorship-day-wednesday-and-you-can-join">American Censorship Day is this Wednesday — And You Can Join In!</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="deeplinks" /><category term="EFF" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After five amazing years, I’m done (for now) at EFF. It’s impossible to boil the experience down into numbers, but here’s a big one: 215 Deeplinks blog posts bear my name as author. Here they are, collected in one place for posterity. After the first hundred and the second hundred, I picked out some of my favorites.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choochoobot in Source’s #botweek</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/04/choochoobot-in-sources-botweek/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choochoobot in Source’s #botweek" /><published>2016-04-29T01:31:42-04:00</published><updated>2016-04-29T01:31:42-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/04/choochoobot-in-sources-botweek</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/04/choochoobot-in-sources-botweek/"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote about <a href="https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/choo-chooooooo/">some of the things I learned</a> from @choochoobot’s development (and popularity) for Source for <a href="https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/tags/botweek/">its annual #botweek</a>. It’s a little strange writing about programming projects, because I still feel very inexperienced, but I think there are some easy lessons to pull out here.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People do not behave rationally around emoji. A large and growing group of people love them more than anybody should love a font, and a small and shrinking set of people think they signal the end of polite interpersonal communication. In any case, that split has fueled the reaction to this bot, and it’s something to keep in mind: when crafting the “tone” of your tweets, you can choose to make them fun, and make people like seeing them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Much more where that came from <a href="https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/choo-chooooooo/">over at Source</a>, and I’m hoping to do more @choochoobot work this weekend.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="bots" /><category term="choochoobot" /><category term="emoji" /><category term="programming" /><category term="source" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I wrote about some of the things I learned from @choochoobot’s development (and popularity) for Source for its annual #botweek. It’s a little strange writing about programming projects, because I still feel very inexperienced, but I think there are some easy lessons to pull out here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mark Twain’s ghost haunts copyright history</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/03/mark-twains-ghost-haunts-copyright-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mark Twain’s ghost haunts copyright history" /><published>2016-03-06T01:19:47-05:00</published><updated>2016-03-06T01:19:47-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/03/mark-twains-ghost-haunts-copyright-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/03/mark-twains-ghost-haunts-copyright-history/"><![CDATA[<p>After years of toying with the idea, Kash finally convinced me to write up <a href="http://fusion.net/story/274974/mark-twains-seance-novel-jap-herron/">the bizarre copyright story that started seven years after Mark Twain’s death</a>, when his ghost reportedly dictated a new novel, via Ouija board, to Emily Grant Hutchings. His publisher said: well, if Twain wrote it, we own it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So the more firmly they insisted Twain himself was behind the work, the more they strengthened the Twain estate’s copyright argument that it, as the owner of all things written by Twain, owned this book, too. And Twain had a deal with Harper &amp; Brothers that gave it the sole rights to publish books by Twain, so Hutchings and her publisher would have to produce credible evidence that he wanted to break that deal in his afterlife.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They just don’t make them like this any more. I’ve been pretty happy with the reception this piece has gotten, too, including a <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20160302/07173633780/copyright-history-strange-case-book-authored-mark-twain-via-ouija-board.shtml">write-up by Techdirt</a> and the lead spot in <a href="http://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2016/03/04/the-shade-of-mark-twain-and-other-news/">the Paris Review’s link roundup</a> this week.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="fusion" /><category term="ghosts" /><category term="history" /><category term="mark twain" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After years of toying with the idea, Kash finally convinced me to write up the bizarre copyright story that started seven years after Mark Twain’s death, when his ghost reportedly dictated a new novel, via Ouija board, to Emily Grant Hutchings. His publisher said: well, if Twain wrote it, we own it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NYPD denies records of copyright communications it had previously acknowledged</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/02/nypd-denies-records-of-copyright-communications-it-had-previously-acknowledged/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NYPD denies records of copyright communications it had previously acknowledged" /><published>2016-02-22T00:02:27-05:00</published><updated>2016-02-22T00:02:27-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/02/nypd-denies-records-of-copyright-communications-it-had-previously-acknowledged</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2016/02/nypd-denies-records-of-copyright-communications-it-had-previously-acknowledged/"><![CDATA[<p>A few media outlets reported last summer that the NYPD, in its continuing efforts to crack down on the sometimes-annoying costumed characters in Times Square, had asked Disney and Marvel to initiate copyright action there. Disney and Marvel didn’t bite. I requested the communications (or records thereof) under New York’s Freedom of Information Law, and got told — months later — there were no such records. Strange.</p>

<p>I <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20160214/11494733601/nypd-says-it-has-no-record-asking-disney-to-use-copyright-to-shut-down-times-square-characters-despite-public-admission.shtml">wrote the whole thing up for Techdirt</a> this week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unfortunately, the nature of frustrated transparency efforts is that we don’t really have the answers. If the NYPD had promptly responded that it had no such records or would be withholding them according to a particular exemption, or even if it had given me a limited set, we could close this case. As it stands, we don’t really know anything more about the NYPD’s bizarre efforts to jam its “quality-of-life” issues into an ill-fitting copyright enforcement box.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="foia" /><category term="new york" /><category term="nypd" /><category term="techdirt" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few media outlets reported last summer that the NYPD, in its continuing efforts to crack down on the sometimes-annoying costumed characters in Times Square, had asked Disney and Marvel to initiate copyright action there. Disney and Marvel didn’t bite. I requested the communications (or records thereof) under New York’s Freedom of Information Law, and got told — months later — there were no such records. Strange.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interminable copyrights and the (future) history of journalism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/11/interminable-copyrights-and-the-future-history-of-journalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interminable copyrights and the (future) history of journalism" /><published>2015-11-08T23:53:06-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-08T23:53:06-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/11/interminable-copyrights-and-the-future-history-of-journalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/11/interminable-copyrights-and-the-future-history-of-journalism/"><![CDATA[<p>Over on Techdirt, I wrote a <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20151102/16255832697/copyright-terms-how-historical-journalism-is-disappearing.shtml">short piece about how uncertainty surrounding ridiculously long copyright terms</a> is likely keeping newspapers from the 1920s onward out of major archives. We’re very likely in the midst of a sea change in journalism, but future generations may not be able to study what we’re producing and exploring as likely business shifts make the copyright question even thornier. From the article:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the world of media journalism, we talk a lot about the future. But we can’t have a coherent conversation about that without thinking about the past and the present. And those thoughts, in turn, rely on access to the history that we’ve allowed to be locked up under effectively unlimited copyright restrictions or as orphan works.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Per usual, the comments over at Techdirt, too, have been lively.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="journalism" /><category term="newspapers" /><category term="techdirt" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over on Techdirt, I wrote a short piece about how uncertainty surrounding ridiculously long copyright terms is likely keeping newspapers from the 1920s onward out of major archives. We’re very likely in the midst of a sea change in journalism, but future generations may not be able to study what we’re producing and exploring as likely business shifts make the copyright question even thornier. From the article:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The original racist emoji issue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/04/the-original-racist-emoji-issue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The original racist emoji issue" /><published>2015-04-26T22:25:46-04:00</published><updated>2015-04-26T22:25:46-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/04/the-original-racist-emoji-issue</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/04/the-original-racist-emoji-issue/"><![CDATA[<p>Over at Ratter, I’ve written about how the unrecognized character symbol is showing up in an unfortunate context with the new emoji-of-color, and how this all relates to <a href="http://ratter.com/your-emoji-is-racist-because-it-was-born-that-way-1699292813">an Ur-issue of emoji racism</a>. In my opinion, the moment this became an issue was when Apple exported emoji that mostly looked white to us.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After all, the Unicode Consortium only provides the list of possible emoji to platforms like Apple, Android, and Twitter — it’s up to the platforms to actually draw them. Platforms like Apple got a descriptions from the Unicode Consortium like “HAPPY PERSON RAISING ONE HAND” or “POLICE OFFICER” and they created the pictures we’re all familiar with. Because Apple was one of the first platforms to draw emoji, their versions — which feature mostly white faces — became the canon.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was harder to write than I expected, but I think it’s an interesting and surprisingly convoluted issue. Hopefully this explanation helps people understand some of the forces at play here.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="emoji" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over at Ratter, I’ve written about how the unrecognized character symbol is showing up in an unfortunate context with the new emoji-of-color, and how this all relates to an Ur-issue of emoji racism. In my opinion, the moment this became an issue was when Apple exported emoji that mostly looked white to us.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anonymous speech could be caught in the online abuse crossfire</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/03/anonymous-speech-caught-online-abuse-crossfire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anonymous speech could be caught in the online abuse crossfire" /><published>2015-03-28T18:33:14-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-28T18:33:14-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/03/anonymous-speech-caught-online-abuse-crossfire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/03/anonymous-speech-caught-online-abuse-crossfire/"><![CDATA[<p>Over at Wired, <a href="http://www.wired.com/2015/03/hey-twitter-killing-anonymitys-dumb-way-fight-trolls/">I wrote a piece earlier this month</a> responding to reports from Tor users that they were having trouble using Twitter anonymously. It bears noting that we don’t really know what exactly Twitter’s up to, but given the timing of these events (and the fact that they can be consistently, if not universally, reproduced), it seems that this might be an attempt to crack down on abuse.</p>

<p>Not only will that not work, but it would do real harm to valuable speech that relies on anonymity. From the article:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unfortunately, some voices can be so profoundly silenced by a pierced veil of anonymity that they won’t be around to protest unannounced updates. For instance, activists and journalists in countries where Twitter is forbidden use Tor to circumvent the censorship technology that blocks the site, and to do so without being traceable by the national internet service providers and phone network operators. Changes that make it harder to use Twitter and Tor in combination end up doing real harm to some of the speech that is most marginalized.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The fact that we can’t tell for sure whether Twitter has targeted this speech intentionally raises more issues about the transparency we need to see in online algorithms. But even if this is an unintentional side-effect of a different policy, it’s important to recognize that hindering anonymous speech in any case comes at a great cost.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="anonymity" /><category term="tor" /><category term="wired" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over at Wired, I wrote a piece earlier this month responding to reports from Tor users that they were having trouble using Twitter anonymously. It bears noting that we don’t really know what exactly Twitter’s up to, but given the timing of these events (and the fact that they can be consistently, if not universally, reproduced), it seems that this might be an attempt to crack down on abuse.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Blurred Lines” trial starts today</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/02/blurred-lines-trial-starts-today/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Blurred Lines” trial starts today" /><published>2015-02-24T10:40:01-05:00</published><updated>2015-02-24T10:40:01-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/02/blurred-lines-trial-starts-today</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dotnet/2015/02/blurred-lines-trial-starts-today/"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a <a href="http://ratter.com/copyright-mixtape-how-the-blurred-lines-lawsuit-coul-1686104132">piece for a new-ish publication called</a> <em>Ratter</em> about the impending copyright trial between Pharrell, Robin Thicke, and the estate of Marvin Gaye, about whether the song “Blurred Lines” infringes on “Got To Give It Up.” In particular, the judge has done some unusual things in terms of what is allowable evidence, given that the Gaye song predates the lifting of notice-and-registration requirements, so <em>only</em> the material in the deposited copy of the sheet music is covered by copyright, under the 1909 Act. From my piece:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But in the last week or so, the docket filings have been piling up and the judge has <a href="https://ia801902.us.archive.org/20/items/gov.uscourts.cacd.569559/gov.uscourts.cacd.569559.231.0.pdf">changed course on that position</a>. The Gaye estate had already filed mash-ups of the two songs to demonstrate how similar they were. Perhaps inspired by those recordings, the judge suggested an unusual and uniquely modern twist: both sides could try submitting versions of “Got To Give It Up” that consist of <em>only</em> the copyrighted elements of the song. In other words, both sides should agree how to distil “Got To Give It Up” down to its basic copyrighty essence — a fire mixtape of pure copyrightium.</p>

  <p>Both sides eventually agreed to this condition and edited together the versions of “Got To Give It Up” the jury is likely to hear. If it’s not written down in the sheet music it’s off the table, meaning that the courtroom version of “Got To Give It Up” likely sounds like the MIDI version that auto-played on a Geocities home page, or a rendition by the animatronic band at Chuck E. Cheese.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Since that was published, my <em>Ratter</em> editor Kate was able to get and publish a copy of the actual courtroom recordings, and we were relieved to hear <a href="http://ratter.com/heres-the-pivotal-track-of-the-blurred-lines-copyrigh-1686896366">they sound about as weird as we’d hoped</a>.</p>

<p>In a sense, I think this case mirrors <em>Aereo</em>, but for music. That is to say, it’s undisputed that Pharrell and Thicke wanted to emulate the sound of “Got To Give It Up,” and attempted to do so in a way that deliberately complied with the law. One of the perverse outcomes of <em>Aereo</em> is that it creates the sense that a careful compliance with the law might be deemed a violation—”too cute by half,” maybe, or a Rube Goldberg machine. I hope that doesn’t happen with “Blurred Lines,” because it’s the concept of musical influence that would suffer.</p>

<p>Now after several delays, the trial begins today! While I was hoping to make it, I’ll have to watch from afar.</p>]]></content><author><name>Parker Higgins</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><category term="blurred lines" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="ratter" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I wrote a piece for a new-ish publication called Ratter about the impending copyright trial between Pharrell, Robin Thicke, and the estate of Marvin Gaye, about whether the song “Blurred Lines” infringes on “Got To Give It Up.” In particular, the judge has done some unusual things in terms of what is allowable evidence, given that the Gaye song predates the lifting of notice-and-registration requirements, so only the material in the deposited copy of the sheet music is covered by copyright, under the 1909 Act. From my piece:]]></summary></entry></feed>